this massive and comprehensive python
API course is taught by Sanji
thiagarajan he is an excellent teacher
and has taught many popular courses hey
how's it going everyone I just wanted to
welcome you to my python API development
course so in this course I'm going to
walk you through building out your very
own API in Python however keep in mind
this course is so much more than just
building out a simple API in fact as I'm
sure you saw the video length this
course does come out to a whopping 19
hours in length and so you're probably
wondering well what exactly are we going
to be covering for 19 hours we don't
need 19 hours to create an API well
first of all we're going to build out a
fully featured API that includes
authentication CR operations scheme of
validation and we're going to set up
documentation for our API because that's
very important however the learning
doesn't stop just there this course is
going to extend well past just basic API
development we'll also learn all of the
tooling that surrounds building a
complete and robust API I've dedicated a
large section of this course to learning
SQL and I've noticed that a lot of the
other API and web development courses
they just quick gloss over SQL without
diving into the nitty-gritty of how SQL
databases work and for this course we're
going to cover SQL extensively and we're
going to start from the absolute Basics
so you don't need to know a single thing
about databases or SQL in general but by
the time you complete this course you
will be very proficient at generating
database schemas you'll know core SQL
Concepts like primary Keys foreign Keys
table constraints and you can pretty
much be able to generate SQL queries to
grab the exact data that you're looking
for and on top of that I'll show you how
to integrate your SQL databases in your
API using two different methods so we'll
cover both uh using raw SQL queries as
well as or so that no matter which
method you ultimately prefer you'll have
all the skills and resources to start
building out your own projects we'll
also familiarize ourselves with database
migration tools like almic which allow
us to make incremental changes to our
database schema to track changes in git
just like we can with our regular python
code we'll also learn how to use tools
like Postman to construct HTTP packets
so that we can test our API during the
whole development process and when it
comes to testing I've added about you
know 2 to 3 hours of content going over
how to set up automated integration
tests so that when you make changes to
your code you can run these automated
tests to verify that your code changes
haven't broke any pre-existing
functionality and then after testing
we're going to move on to the deployment
phase we're going to actually deploy our
application and I didn't just include
one method of deployment I've actually
included two different deployment
scenarios the first scenario is probably
um the most most common scenario which
is deploying our app onto like an auntu
machine that can be hosted on any cloud
provider like AWS gcp Azure or even
digital ocean and you know we'll cover
things like how to set up engine X to
act as a reverse proxy we'll uh we'll
configure our own system Des service
we'll set up a firewall to block all non
HTTP traffic and we'll even set up SSL
so that our application can handle https
traffic um but after that we'll also
take a look at how we can deploy our
application onto Heroku uh just because
if you don't have um you know maybe you
can't afford to pay for uh cloud
services um or you just don't have the
ability to sign up for an account or
something like that I do want to make
sure that uh you still have a way of uh
deploying your application so that you
can show off to your friends and family
what you created so I added the hoko
section cuz they've got a very very nice
and convenient free tier where we can
deploy our entire application for free
we don't need to sign up with the credit
card so that's why I included that
second deployment scenario and since all
the cool kids are hardcore into Docker
today I'm going to show you how to dock
oriz your API in case that is your
preferred method of deployment and then
finally we're going to wrap things up by
building out our very own cicd pipeline
uh using GitHub actions this will allow
us to push out changes to GitHub
resulting in our pipeline running which
will pull our code run all of our
integration tests build all of the
necessary images and if all the tests
ultimately pass it'll actually push out
our changes to our production
environment so that we can do all of
this in an automated fashion without
having to manually go in and run each
step manually so let's let's take a look
at our text deck since this is a python
API course we will be using python to
build out our API there were a couple of
different web Frameworks in Python that
we could have used most notably D Jango
and flask I decided to use neither one
of them and I decided to use a newer
framework called Fast API and the reason
why I chose to use this framework was
because it has apis uh kind of built in
mind right it wasn't there to address
like the model view controller type
scenario it really is all about building
out apis and on top of that it is really
fast right but when I say fast it's not
just fast from a performance perspective
which it is but it's also fast from the
fact that it can it makes it really easy
uh and quick to spin up new apis and one
of my favorite features of this
framework is the auto documentation
functionality when you build an API you
have to document how your API works and
this is a very cumbersome task um
because anytime you make any changes to
your API you have to remember to update
your API or then the front end can be
making the wrong request fast API
automatically documents your API for you
so that you don't have to do it yourself
it's truly a game Cher and finally the
most important reason why I chose fast
API is because of this you see This
Magnificent Beast this is the creator of
the fast API framework and my mom always
told me when someone with the mustache
as glorious as that creates a web
framework you use that damn
framework now as I mentioned we will be
covering SQL extensively and I've
decided to go with postgress uh it
doesn't really matter what type of SQL
database you use they're all
fundamentally the same with only minor
differences I chose postris cuz that's
my favorite and who doesn't like
elephants anyways for our orm when we do
eventually migrate to orms from using
raw SQL queries we will be using SQL
Alchemy um I decided to use that because
that seems like that's the most standard
one for python I really could have chose
any of them I didn't really care which
one I used so I just picked the most
popular one so that covers our text
stack let's now take a look at the
project that we'll be building now I
would love to show you some cool flashy
website that you can show off to your
friends however we're not building a
website we're building an API and
unfortunately apis don't really have a
visual aspect to them so I don't really
have anything to show you I mean I could
I guess construct a couple HTTP packets
and send it and verify that we get the
proper Json response but that's not
really exciting so what I'm going to do
is I'm going to show you our
documentation for our project so that
you can see all the different features
that we Implement and the nice part
about the documentation is these are
interactive docs so from the
documentation I can actually send HTTP
requests to my application and get a
response back so you can really see all
of the different features things like
the authentication and the crowd
operations that we'll be performing and
setting up in our API so the app that
we're going to build for this course is
going to be a social media type
application where users can create posts
uh they can read other people's posts
they'll be able to perform all the cred
operations so they'll able to create
read update and delete
posts and we'll also be able to uh vote
on posts so you know most social media
apps have some sort of like system or
voting system uh and so we will be able
to like other users posts as well so
this is the built-in documentation that
comes with fast API and you'll be able
to see all of the API endpoints that
we're going to create in this course so
we're going to have all of the post end
point which is going to be responsible
for retrieving all posts creating posts
uh retrieving an individual post
updating a post as well as deleting a
post then we'll have the user specific
um endpoints so things like creating a
user getting a user's information uh and
then we've got our authentication which
is going to be used for logging in and
then finally we've got the one for
voting so when you want to vote on a
specific specific um uh specific post
that you like you can go ahead and like
that post so let's just use the
documentation to actually uh you know
test out our API so first things first
uh let's actually try to retrieve any or
all of our posts so if I hit this get
button right here we can actually try to
send a request to our API with the
built-in documentation so you can just
say execute right and you'll see that we
got a 401 which means that we are right
now not logged in so we are unauthorized
to retrieve any of the posts so uh the
API that we're going to build is going
to require all users to be logged in to
be to even be able to read the posts so
let's actually go ahead and create a
user and so we'll go down to the users
endpoint uh under create user and I'm
going to do try it out and it's going to
give us an example of the structure of
the data that we have to send to our API
to create a user so we need to provide a
username or an email and a
password so I'm going to create an email
I'll call this John
gmail.com and the password is going to
be something simple just for
demonstration
purposes and we'll execute that right so
it'll actually send that data back to
our back end you can see we get a 2011
which means we're successfully able to
create it you can see the ID of the user
account that was created we can see the
email is what it is and then we can see
the date that it was created at as well
and so now we can actually log in as
this user so there's a couple of
different ways to log in I can go to the
login endpoint or we can just go up here
at the top and just do authorize and
then we can provide that information so
I'll do John
gmail.com and we'll provide his password
and if we do authorize now uh we can see
that we have successfully logged in so
I'll close this out and so now if I try
to retrieve the posts and then hit
execute you could see that we were able
to retrieve all of the posts in our
database right now there's only two um
but you can see that these were created
by some other users like saniv in this
case and then sanie 123 and if we want
to create our own post we can go ahead
and do that so I'll go to the create
post endpoint
and we'll do try it out and it's going
to give us an example here so we have to
provide title content as well as is this
post going to be published or is it
going to be a draft and uh you'll
actually see uh the structure of this uh
schema uh right down
here I think it's at the bottom actually
uh so if you go to post create here this
is going to show us the uh the schema
that we have to pass so we have to
provide a title a Content so this the
asri means it's um required the
published is um not required and you can
see that it defaults to true so if we
don't provide a value it'll default to
true so let's test that out and so I'll
just say
um favorite foods is going to be the
title and then content is going to be
piz and burgers and I will remove the
published section because it is optional
and it'll default to true anyways and
we'll hit execute and if we take a look
at the response we get a 2011 which
means it's successfully created it and
you can see what the post looks like in
our dat database you've got the title
content we can see the published got
defaulted to true we can see the ID of
the post when it was created we could
see the owner ID which is you know who
created the post and so that's the ID of
our account which is 17 and we can see
the information about the owner so this
is John
gmail.com and then you know as usual we
could perform all perform all the other
crud operations so we can retrieve an
individual post update it and delete it
and then once again um if we go down
here we can also vote uh to like a post
as well uh and so you know this kind of
forms the backbone of a traditional
social media type application so once
you can really do this you can really
create any application you want and I
think this covers uh enough things from
an API perspective as well as from a SQL
and database perspective that you will
have a solid foundation to really build
out any API that you're interested in
building out and so I think that's
enough talking let's get to actually
start coding out our application in this
video we'll take a look at how to set up
python as well as vs code on a Mac
machine so the first thing we're going
to do is we're going to just search for
Python and the first result should take
us to the main python page and what we
want to do is Select downloads and it's
automatically going to give us a button
to download whatever the latest version
of python is and the nice part is it'll
automatically detect uh what platform
you're using so it'll know that we're on
a Mac and right now it says that the
latest version is 39.6 so it's going to
offer me that keep in mind if you're
watching this video in the future it's
going to show a different version and
it's okay for you to download a newer
version as long as it's later than 3.7
you should be okay for this course so
I'm going to select this and it's going
to download it like any other
application once it's finished
downloading we're going to select that
and then select the file that we just
downloaded and then this is going to
take us through the python installation
process so we'll hit continue we'll hit
continue again
continue we'll hit agree and then
install and then it's going to prompt us
for a
password all right and so once you get
this popup it means that python was
successfully installed so we can then
close that out real
quick and we can move this to trash and
the next thing that we want to do is uh
go up to your search bar at the top and
I want you to search for the terminal
application right and it should find
that just double click on that so we can
open up a
terminal and with our terminal what we
want to do is we want to type in Python
3-- version and the reason we um specify
Python 3 is that you can actually have a
python 2 and a Python 3 version
simultaneously installed simultaneously
on your machine we want to make sure
that we got Python 3 successfully
installed so if we type this in it
should then print out the version that
we installed so we can see that we did
successfully install python 39.6 so we
should be set from a python perspective
and now that we have python installed
let's go ahead and install VSS code so
like I said vs code is going to act as
our text editor or our IDE and so what
we're going to do is just search for vs
code and this is going to take us to the
Microsoft page and then once again
Microsoft will automatically detect that
we're running a Mac and then we can just
go ahead and select download Mac
universal all right and once that's done
installing or downloading we can select
that and open it up and you'll get this
warning just go ahead and select
open and so this is going to open up our
vs code and what we need to do is uh VSS
code is just a very basic text editor
however it comes with extensions that we
can install that make
significantly more feature Rich so it'll
almost act like a traditional IDE and if
you select the extensions icon which is
this icon right here with the extra
blocks select that and I want you to
search for
Python and the first result should be
the one you want and it should be the
one um that's made by Microsoft so this
is going to provide things like linting
intellisense debugging and a few other
features that are going to come in handy
when it comes to writing python code
within vs code so go ahead and install
this all right so now that it's
installed what we want to do is Select
this icon to go back to our folder menu
and we want to select open folder so
what we're going to do is we're going to
create a folder to store all of our
project code so I'm going to select open
folder now we haven't created a folder
uh to actually store our application so
I'm going to go under U my traditional
users sanie and then I'm just going to
store this within my documents so I'm
going to make a new folder called um
I'll call this uh we'll just call this
fast
API so I'll create that and then we're
going to open up the fast API folder
that we just created
created and so this is going to open up
all of our project code right now we
have no files and that's to be expected
but what I want to do is I want to right
click here and select new file and we
want to do is type in
main.py and before we hit enter I want
you to look down here so when I hit
enter you'll see that something's
happening so it's activating the python
extension and it's automatically going
to select a python interpreter and so
like I said you can have multiple
different versions of python so
technically we could you know for any
one of our projects we could be running
39.6 or maybe we're running 2.7 if we
want to stick to python 2 we can
actually select which specific python
interpreter we want to run on a per a
project basis and if you ever want to
change this or for some reason it wasn't
able to find this correctly just go
ahead and select view command pallet and
then it automatically uh found the most
recently used ones but you would just
search for python select interpreter
select this and it shows the currently
selected interpreter but you can also
enter in the path to find a specific
interpreter so you would just find
wherever Python 2.7 was installed if you
wanted to use that or if it was unable
to find 39.6 go ahead and just uh find
where python 39.6 was installed on your
machine and point to that python.exe
file actually it's not called exe uh
within Mac I forget what it's called on
a Mac I actually use a Windows machine
for most of my things but that's all you
have to do uh and so at this point we've
got python set up and then we've got our
uh vs code set up so once again uh
anytime vs code closes you want to open
it back up and then um open up the
folder fast API in this
case in this video I'm going to walk you
through setting up python as well as vs
code on a Windows machine so the first
thing that we're going to do is within
your web browser just search for Python
and then we're going to select the first
result so this is going to take us to
the main python page and we want to go
to the download section and so here
python uh the website's going to offer
you up whatever the latest version of
python is in this case it happens to be
39.6 keep in mind if you're watching
this video in the future it's going to
show some other version and that's okay
go ahead and just download the latest
version as long as it's a later than 3.7
you should be okay so I'm going to just
hit download python
3.96 just going to download that once
it's finished downloading I'm going to
select that and it's going to open up
the installer now with this installer
open it's very important that you select
add python 3.9 to path do not forget to
do this or then you're going to run into
some issues so make make sure that's
selected and then hit install now if you
go through the installation process and
you realize you forgot to do this
technically there's a way to fix it
afterwards but um instead of me
explaining to do that the best thing to
do is just uninstall Python and
reinstall it so we'll hit install now
you'll get a popup just go ahead and hit
yes all right and once you see this
message where it says setup was
successful that means python was
installed and the next thing that we
want to do is just quickly verify that
Python's up and running and working so
what we're going to do is we're just
going to search for CMD so that's going
to open up our our Command Prompt or
terminal and then in here just type in
python-3 D-
version sorry we should actually type in
Python py- 3-- version all right and so
when you type this command in uh it's
going to tell us the specific version
that we installed so we can see that I
was successfully installed python 39.6
if you get any kind of error um or any
message saying that this command is not
available that means that python wasn't
installed successfully so just go ahead
and redo that process just in case now
the next thing that we want to do is
install VSS code so let's open up a new
tab just search for VSS
code and then we'll select this it's
going to take us to this page and you'll
see that vs code will automatically
detect what version you're running so
you can just select download for
Windows and then once it's finished in
uh downloading go ahead and open it
up hit the accept agreement hit next
next next and then you can leave
everything as
default and then go ahead and run
install all right and then go ahead and
finish it's going to automatically open
up a vs
code uh now there's a couple things I
want to do so uh VSS code at its core is
just a basic text editor however we can
install extensions that give it extra
functionality extra features that'll
make it operate a little bit more like a
full-blown IDE so go ahead and select
this icon right here this is for
extensions and then what we want to do
is we want to search for
Python and we usually just want to
select the first one it'll have a star
and it's going to be the one made by
Microsoft you'll see that there's other
ones made by other users but we want the
main Microsoft one hit install and so
this extension is going to give us
intellisense linting debugging and a few
other features that are going to make it
a little bit easier to start working
with python within vs code all right uh
and so now that it's done installing we
can just close this close this and then
select this one to get back to your main
file browser and and uh right now we
haven't opened up any folder so what we
want to do is we want to create a folder
to store all of our application code so
select open folder and then figure out
where you want to store your application
code so I'm just going to store this in
my documents you can store this wherever
you want I'm going to create a new file
or a new folder I'm just going to call
it fast API but you can name your
project whatever you want so just H
select
folder and so that's going to not only
create not only create the folder but
it's going to open it up within vs code
if you get this eror just select Trust
the author and just select yes and then
we can close out this welcome menu and
so now what we have is we've opened up
whoops uh we've opened up VSS code and
within VSS code we've opened up our uh
project code so right now there's no
code that's to be expected but I what I
want to do is I want to create a new
file real quick just uh for testing
purposes so I'm just going to right
click hit new file and I'm going to name
it Ma
main.py uh and so we want to name it py
because this is going to be a python
file and before I hit enter I want I
want you to focus your eyes right down
here and you'll notice something happens
down there so when I hit enter you'll
see activating extension so it's
activating the python extension and what
the python extension is going to do is
it's automatically going to uh select
the correct python interpreter or it may
not be corrected depending on what
happens on your machine for me it
automatically detected python 39.6 was
installed on this machine so let's
selected that one for me keep in mind if
you have multiple versions of python
installed it may select the wrong
interpreter so what you can do is if you
ever want to change The Interpreter or
specify a specific interpreter go to
view command pallet and what I want you
to do is search for
python interpreter and then look for
python select interpreter so right now
it's going to highlight where um the
current python interpreters which one
selected and what's the executable for
it but if you want to change that you
can select enter interpreter path and
then provide the path to the specific
version that you want so you can
obviously change it but usually it's
able to detect the latest version so you
should be good to go uh and so that's
all I wanted to do from a setup
perspective there's one more thing that
we'll cover uh later um but we'll get to
that in the next section um but right
now we've got python installed and we've
got vs code set up and we've got our
project directory set up so we should be
good to
go so now that we have Python and vs
code set up the next thing that we have
to do is set up our virtual environment
before we do that we have to actually
talk about what are virtual environments
and what problem do they try to address
so let me give you a little bit of an
example scenario of the issue that we
can run into when working with specific
package within python on your local
machine so let's say that we created a
project and this project is called
project one and what we need to do is we
need to install fast API version 1.2.1
so what do we do we install version
1.2.1 on our machine so that we can
actually use that version now let's say
later down the road we start a new
project called project 2 and let's say
this version uh requires us to run fast
API version 2.4.3 because we want to try
out some of the newer features well at
this point if we need to try out a newer
version we have to upgrade fast API to
version 2.4.3 on our local machine and
this may or may not be a problem it
really just depends on if version 2.4.3
is backwards compatible with version
1.2.1 uh because if version 2.4.3 has
breaking changes then ultimately that's
going to create issues with our project
one because that project expects us to
run version 1.2.1 and so if we can't
upgrade well we're in a little bit of a
pickle because one project needs one
version the other project needs another
version we can't have two different
versions installed on our machine so
what exactly do we do well this is where
virtual environments come into play so
with virtual environments let's say we
want to create a project so we create
project one and what we do is we create
a virtual environment call it whatever
you want and so this is a isolated
environment that will not affect any
other environments and within this
environment we can install any python
packages running whatever version we
want and it's completely isolated to
this project and so when we create a
second project what we can do is we can
create its very own virtual environment
as well we'll call it virtual
environment 2 and within this virtual
environment we can install any version
of any package that we want so then we
can install version 2.4.3 and so both of
these virtual environments are
completely separated completely isolated
with one another and so we can
essentially install multiple different
versions of a single package for each of
our projects and that way our projects
don't end up stepping on the toes of
other projects and so now that we have a
basic understanding of virtual
environments let's go ahead and figure
out how we can actually create our first
virtual environment and use it within
our
project in this video I'm going to walk
you through setting up a virtual
environment on a Windows machine now if
you already closed out your VSS code
window go ahead and open up a new one
and make sure you open up the specific
directory we created a couple lessons
ago now what we want to do is we want to
select a terminal and we want to select
new terminal and this is a awesome
feature with vs code it allows us to
have a integrated terminal within our or
VSS code window and this terminal is
fundamentally no different than a
regular terminal within windows it's
just built into vs code so that we don't
have to keep flipping between different
windows and if you actually take a look
at this right column we can have
multiple terminals open and we can even
use different terminals so the default
one on this machine happens to be
Powershell but you can also use command
prompt if that's what you prefer so if
you select command prompt it's going to
create a new terminal and you can see
that this is a traditional command
prompt so I'm going to use this one
because that's the one I normally use
however if you're more comfortable with
power feel free to use that now the
command to actually create a virtual
environment within Windows is
py
-3- M VNV so that stands for virtual
environment and then you want to give it
a name so give whatever name you want
for your virtual environment you can
name it after your project name or you
could just do what I do which is just
call it
VMV and what I like to do is for all of
my projects I give it the same exact
name and that's perfectly okay because
this virtual environment is going to be
isolated to this project directory and
so even though this project has a
virtual environment named VNV I can
create another virtual environment in
any other project with the same exact
name and they're all going to be
isolated to that specific project folder
so go ahead and hit
enter and take a look over here you'll
see that a folder was created called V
uh virtual environment or VNV and that's
going to be the name of this folder is
always going to refer to whatever name
you gave it so if I named this cookies
this would open up a new folder called
cookies and if you want you can take a
look at what's in here and if you go
under script specifically you'll notice
that we've got our python executable so
this is going to act as our new
interpreter uh and so what we want to do
is right now we are using our Global
interpreter and we want to change that
we don't want to use the global one we
want to use the specific one in our
virtual environment uh and that way we
can install packages that are exclusive
to just this specific virtual
environment and so to do that go ahead
and select view once again
and we want to go to command pallet and
then search for python select
interpreter as usual and then you'll see
the one we're currently using but we
want to pass in our newest one so select
enter interpreter path and then we want
to give it the path to our interpreter
which is the path from the root of our
project directory to this python.exe
file we're going to say dot which is our
current folder so this is going to be
the fast API folder and then within here
we want to go into uh Scripts
and then within scripts well sorry we
want to go into the virtual EnV folder
then
scripts and then python.exe go ahead and
hit enter and then if you look down here
you'll see that this gets updated so now
we're still using 39.6 but we're using
our virtual environment uh and so that's
all we need to do and it should remember
this every time we open up our project
however double check every time you open
up just to make sure you're using that
if it's for some reason moved back to
the default one just do the same
process now the second thing that we
need to do is we need to make sure our
terminal is also using the virtual
environment uh and so what we want to do
to do that is just type
in uh the path to this specific activate
dobat file this is going to activate
that virtual environment within our
command line as well so I'm going to
say uh virtual
NV and then we want to pass in our
scripts folder and then then activate
dobat hit enter and then notice what's
changed right so when you're using a
virtual environment right you're going
to see the name of the virtual
environment to the side of it so always
double check whenever you start up VSS
code and you start up your project that
this is enabled if you don't see this
then just run the same exact command and
that's going to reactivate the virtual
environment and so at this point we are
good to go with our virtual environment
and we can start coding out our
project in this video I'm going to walk
you through setting up a virtual
environment on a Mac machine now if
you've already closed out your vs code
window go ahead and open it back up and
open up the folder that we created a
couple lessons
ago now within here what we want to do
is we want to access our terminal so we
can access our terminal just by
selecting this and then this is our
terminal however vs code has a feature
where we can access the terminal
directly within our vs code window so if
we select terminal and the new terminal
that's going to create a new terminal
for us all right and so this is fun
fundamentally the same
thing uh as this terminal right here
it's no different but at least by having
it built into vsod we don't have to keep
flipping back and forth between the two
so you can use either one whichever your
preference is keep in mind that when you
open up the terminal within vs code it
automatically moves you to the um the
directory folder of your project so you
don't have to move there yourself uh you
can use whichever one you want now I'm
actually using I'm running Mac on a
virtual machine right now just because I
I natively use a Windows machine so I
don't actually own a Mac so this is is a
little bit buggy you know if you see me
type things you can see it vanish so for
demonstration purposes I'm just going to
use the regular terminal but I strongly
recommend you use the one built into vs
code so you don't have to keep flipping
back and
forth now to actually create a uh
virtual environment there's one command
that we have to run so you run python
3-m V NV for virtual environment and
then you have to give it a name so what
name do you want to give your virtual
environment you can technically give it
any name you want you can name it after
uh your project uh you can give it some
arbitrary name what I like to do is I
like to name all of my virtual
environments
venv and so for every project that I
create I just create uh the same exact
virtual environment name um venv and
that's not going to create an issue it's
perfectly okay to name all of your
virtual environments the same thing
because it's all going to be exclusive
to this specific project folder so no
other projects can access it so it's
okay if they all use the same name it's
just easier and so that way uh you know
if I ever create a get ignore file I can
automatically add V EnV and I can make
sure to just use the same exact GE
ignore template across all of my python
projects so I'm going to use VV and I
want to make sure that you pay attention
right here because after I run this
command take a look at what happens it
creates a folder called venv and that's
based off of the name of the virtual
environment and if we take a look at our
virtual environment you can see a couple
of different files uh you can see the um
the python file as well so if you go
under bin this is going to be the new
python file or the Python 3 file that
we're going to use for our interpreter
so down here at the bottom you'll see
that we are still using the global
interpreter we no longer want to use the
global one we want to use the one in our
virtual environment that way we don't
you know cause any issues with other
projects we want to use the virtual
environment so to do that what we want
to do is we want to select a
view command
pallet and then we want to do the python
select interpreter again so we'll select
that right and so right now it shows us
that um we are using the global one
however we're going to pass in the path
to our specific interpreter within our
virtual environment so we'll select
enter interpreter
path we'll say dot for current directory
and so that's going to mean uh the
current fast API directory then within
there we want to go into the virtual
environment folder and then within there
we want to go into
bin and then just say
Python and so we'll hit enter and then
take a look at what happened down here
right you notice that the uh version
still says 39.6 but our interpreter is
actually pointing to our local virtual
environment now because we changed The
Interpreter to use this specific python
file right here uh and so this is what's
going to allow us to install our own
specific fast API version as well as any
other version of any package that we
want so it doesn't actually install it
globally on our machine now we're almost
done but there's one other thing to note
if you look at our terminal our terminal
isn't using our virtual environment so
if I run pip install any package it's
not going to install it for a specific
virtual environment it's going to
install it globally so we have to enable
the virtual environment for the command
line as
well and to do that all you have to do
is type in
source and then we want to pass in uh
the path to this specific activate file
right here within bin so we do V EnV SL
bin SL activate you hit enter
and then notice how our command line
changes now it's prepended by the name
of our virtual environment so since we
named it V EnV you can see that it shows
it right before the terminal and so
that's all you have to do our virtual
environment is set up keep in mind if
you close out your
terminal and then reopen it you you'll
notice that your virtual environment is
gone so you have to run that same exact
command every time you open up your
terminal to ensure that you are in your
virtual environment and anytime you
close out vs code make sure that when
you reopen your project it still points
to the virtual environment if for some
reason it changes then just go back to
that command pallet by going to view
command pallet and then selecting The
Interpreter that you specifically want
um but that's all we have to do guys so
our virtual environment set up and so at
this point we can go ahead and get
started on coding out our
project so now that we got our
environment set up it's time to get
started coding out our project and what
I want you guys to do is first of all go
to the fast API documentation this is
really important what I want you guys to
do is really get a solid understanding
of how the documentation works so pull
up the fast API website and then head on
over to the tutorial section and then
select the intro part so this is going
to walk us through setting up our
project and what we will need to do is
first of all we need to install the fast
API package uh and so what we can do is
we can either do pip install fast API or
we can do pip install uh fast API all
when we do F uh pip install fast API all
it's going to install all of the
optional depend as well which we may or
may not need depending on what features
we want we're going to go ahead and use
the all option because we're going to
use a lot of them and there's no point
in having to go one by one and install
them so that's what we're going to do so
here uh in our command line and make
sure that we are in our virtual
environment and then just type in PIP
install fast API and then we'll pass in
all and we'll let that run now it's
moving fairly fast um but if you kind of
scroll through the history you'll notice
a lot packages and a lot of dependencies
that are getting installed so we'll take
a look at those once it's done just to
see what are the different dependencies
that were installed and so now that
that's done if we type in PIP freeze
this is going to show all of the
packages that were installed so it's not
going to be just fast API it's going to
include a lot of the optional
dependencies as well so if we take a
look um you can see that we've got uh
graphql installed if we want to use any
graphql uh we have bcrypt UV coin that's
going to be like our web server
websocket we want to work with websocket
so it already comes bundled with a lot
of things that we're going to use um and
I just wanted to make sure that you guys
understood what's happening when we pass
in that that all flag and if you want to
if you open up your virtual environment
folder and you go under lib you'll see
all of the uh the code associated with
those packages that we installed so
that's where all of them are going to
reside they're all going to reside
within the lib folder all right so now
that we've got uh fast API installed the
first thing that we have to do is we
have to import fast API and to import
fast API we just say
from Fast API which is the name of the
library we
import fast
API all right so we've now successfully
imported fast API let's create an
instance of fast API so we'll say app
equals fast API and then we'll call that
function uh keep in mind you can name
this anything you want but if you take a
look at the documentation and just
follow along uh you can see that it's
going to name an app so I think it's
best if we just kind of follow along
with that convention then what we're
going to do is we're going to just copy
this code right here so this is going to
be what's referred to as a path
operation and we'll go over what that
means in a bit and we'll just paste this
here I want you to save your code you'll
see if you get this uh warning or this
message saying format autop pep 8 is not
installed go ahead and hit yes and so
this is nice because it'll automatically
format our codes so if we ever put too
many spaces or things like that you'll
see that as soon as you save it it's
going to snap into place and make
everything look nice and pretty so let's
save this and so once we've got our code
let's actually start our web server up
so how do we actually start our web
server well once again let's go to our
documentation uh so we're going to make
use of the UV corn Library so because we
installed a fast API with the all flag
um it'll automatically install UV corn
if you didn't use the all flag then
you'll have to do pip install UV corn as
well but we already got it installed and
so let's go back here and let's run our
API so we do UV corn then what we have
to do is we have to uh reference the
name of our file so this is their entry
point into our application which is our
main file so here we're going to say
main keep in mind if this file was named
anything else you don't have to name it
main you can name it anything else you
would just want to pass the name of
whatever the file name is then you do
colon then you pass in the name of your
fast API instance so we named it app and
so we'll do
app and then we'll start that right and
so this is saying that we started our
server perfect and we could see the URL
that our server running on so it's going
to say
http/1 127.0.0.1 so if you guys don't
know what that address is that means um
it's this machine so whatever IP address
this machine runs on that's what this is
going to be uh so it's just saying hey
we want to refer to the Local Host and
it's going to run on Port 8,000 so if
you want to you can just copy this
URL go to your web browser paste it in
here and then see what happens and then
look at this I'm going to zoom in for
you it says message hello world and
that's coming from our
code right and that's coming from this
return statement right here uh so that
so this kind of verifies that everything
worked perfectly all right so now that
we've got everything up and running and
working and you can see that when we go
to our website uh we can see that we are
properly getting back our message uh
let's pause this video and in the next
video we'll take a look at exactly what
each line of this code actually
means all right guys so let's take a
look at the code that we added and
actually dis detect what each line means
so we've got these three lines of code
and if you take a look at the fast API
documentation that we were on it's going
to define those three lines of code as a
path operation so that's the terminology
is using it refers to this as a path
operation now the name itself doesn't
really matter uh you'll see that in
other web Frameworks uh especially in
other languages sometimes they refer to
this as a route um but they uh within
the documentation for fast API referred
to as a path operation so you'll see me
flip between those two terms but they
fundamentally mean the same thing so
let's actually take a look at this
specific path operation and we can
really see that it's made up of two
components the first component is going
to be the function and the second thing
is going to be the decorator so we'll
come back to The Decorator in a bit
let's take a look at this function so
this function is fundamentally no
different than any other python function
it's a plain old function uh you'll see
that there's this async keyword
technically this is optional this
keywords only needed if you're going to
be performing some sort of asynchronous
task so something that takes a certain
amount of time so things like uh you
know making an API call things like
talking to the database if you want to
do that asynchronously you do have to
pass in the async keyword but we're not
doing that right now so what we can do
is we can actually just remove that so
I'm going to delete that and just remove
that and so now it's just a regular
function and you'll see that the code
behaves exactly the same so we have a
function um we give the function a name
so the documentation just CHS an
arbitrary name of root keep in mind the
name itself doesn't matter so if I
wanted to name this you know uh get user
then that's going to be fine it's not
going to change anything it's an
arbitrary name however I do recommend
you name your functions your path
operation functions uh to be as
descriptive as possible so if you're
trying to log in a user uh then maybe
you should call this login user or just
log in so that it's as descriptive as
possible but keep in mind the name that
we put here does not matter so I'll
change this back to root for
now and then we have so then within this
function you can perform any kind of
logic so if this function is meant to
log in a user it's going to have all the
code for logging in a user whatever that
may be so maybe you know checking the
passwords in a database to make sure
that they match and to make sure that
the credentials are properly accurate uh
and then after that you know just like
any other function we can return
something so whatever we return here is
going to be the data that get sent back
to the user so if we go back to the
website go to our web server if you take
a look at this message hello world
that's exactly what we sent and if we
change this to be whatever we want it's
going to get returned back in the same
way so here we're just returning a
python uh dictionary I guess and what
happens is fast API will automatically
convert this to Json which is the main
universal language of uh apis right we
all talk to we use Json to send data
back and forth between an API so it
converts this to Json and it sends it
back to the user and that's why we see
that on the web
browser now the next thing that we have
is this decorator if you're not really
familiar with decorators in Python it's
okay you don't really actually need to
understand you know the core concept of
a decorator just understand that when
you apply a decorator to a function it's
going to perform a little magic to this
function because if I remove this
decorator if we just comment it out take
a look at this code this code has
nothing to do with fast API it's a plain
old function so how do we actually make
it you know act like an API well we have
to use this magical decorator this
decorator turns this into an actual path
operation so that someone who wants to
use her API can hit this end point uh
and so you just specify at the at symbol
that's what the that's how we clarify
that this is going to be a decorator
then we reference our fast API instance
and then we have a couple of different
options so what here we be pass in is
the HTTP method that the user should use
so this is a get method which means that
we have to send a get request to our API
and but we can use plenty of different
HTTP methods and I strongly recommend
you actually take a look at the
different HTTP methods if you do HTTP
methods
we can select this one this is the
Mozilla page you could see all of the
different HTTP methods so there's get
post put delete so those are the main
ones there's a couple of other ones that
uh are sometimes used but for the most
part those are the core
ones and so here once again just the
HTTP method and then finally we have the
path uh uh and so this is the root path
uh and so and so it's a little bit hard
to explain the path but it's basically
the path after the specific domain name
of your API so if you take a look at our
uh our URL our web server is hosted on
this specific uh URL if I go to this
page let's open up a new link and just
paste it in here so so the URL and the
path in this case is just slash so
that's the equivalent of just hitting
enter right here or putting a slash
which doesn't change anything right
right whether there slashes there or not
it's basically going to take you to the
same URL it's very similar to going to
you know
google.com right that's going to take us
to google.com but if you go to
google.com/ it's it's the same thing so
it's the root path so whatever um domain
name our API is hosted on whatever URL
it's just saying it's the root path you
know if I change this to um you know log
in right that means that this path
operation will only apply if the user
goes to our URL and then goes to slash
login so that decorator this path right
here just references the path that we
have to go to in the URL
and so if this is actually changed to um
how about posts and then you know like
vote so maybe this is a URL for voting
on a specific post then we would have to
go and do the same thing here so we'd
have to go to post SL vote so nothing
too complicated but those are the two
pieces that make up a simple path
operation you've got the function then
you've got this uh decorator where you
have to pass in the specific HTTP method
and then the URL you want it to go to
and I'm going to change this back to the
default
and now what I want to do is let's go
ahead and make a simple change so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to change
this I'm going to change the message to
be um welcome to my API we'll save
this go back to the root URL because we
changed it to the root
URL let's hit refresh notice how it
still says hello world nothing changed
so what gives right it you know our
code's changed I saved it why are we not
updating it so that it returns welcome
to my API well the problem is is that
anytime you make a change we have to
restart our server so to restart our
server you hit contrl C which is going
to stop it then you can just hit the up
Arrow key so that you can find that
command that you ran before and just run
it again and so now if I hit refresh we
can see that it updated and I'm sure
you're thinking well that's a little
Annoying every time I change my code I
have to do a contrl c and then an up
arrow and then hit enter just so that I
can you know make sure that the server
actually implements those changes and it
is a little annoying but there is a work
around so if we go to the documentation
you'll see that when they run UV corn
they pass in the D- reload flag and the
D- reload flag will actually take a look
at your code and monitor your code so
anytime that you change your code it'll
automatically restart your server for
you so let's try that out I'm going to
do a contrl C I'm going to hit the up
arrow and I'm going to pass in the D-
reload flag so we'll hit enter and now
what I want you to do is make some
changes so it doesn't really matter what
you change I'm just going to add a
couple exclamation points and then I'm
going to hit uh save
and I want you to focus what on What
Happens down here so if I hit save look
at that it automatically restarted the
server for me and so now if I go back to
my website uh or my API hit refresh you
can see that the exclamation points are
there so moving forward in a development
environment only when we're in a
development environment we're going to
pass in the D- reload flag when we go to
production we don't need that we're not
going to be setting it up because we're
not going to be changing our code in a
production environment and so I think
that's a good stopping point here uh in
the next video we'll just quickly review
exactly what is a path operation so that
we could just reinforce what we learned
in this
lecture all right guys so let's quickly
recap what we learned in the previous
lecture I want to make sure that you
guys have a solid understanding of the
different components of a path operation
because ultimately that's all your API
is it's just a bunch of path operations
so first things first we have our
decorator so our decorator has the
little at symbol uh and so that's what
signifies it as a decorator and then we
reference our fast AP instance which we
called app and then we have our HTTP
method so in this case this is going to
match only get methods and then we have
the specific path or the URL so this is
the root URL in this case and then below
that we've got our specific path
operation function so this function is
going to contain all the logic for
performing some kind of task and when
it's going to return some data and
that's the data that gets returned to
the user when they hit this specific
path operation so now that we have a ID
understanding of how path operations
work let's see if we can create a new
path operation and let's say this one
represents retrieving a bunch of social
media posts from our application so in
this case you know there's two things
that we need so the first thing is our
function our path operation function so
we'll say defa and then we'll give this
function any name I think since we're
going to be retrieving a bunch of posts
I think a good name is going to be uh
getor
posts um but keep in mind you can name
this anything you want like I said it
does not impact the behavior of anything
and then we want to see uh so here we
would pass in all of our Logic for
retrieving post but we don't actually
have an application so I'm just going to
say
return and then we'll just say
um maybe I don't know
data and this is going to be this is
your post but in reality we would
provide a list of
posts so let's save that and then
there's one last thing we have to pass
in our decorator like we did before to
actually make this turn into a special
path operation function so we'll say at
then we reference the instance uh the
fast API instance we'll do app Dot and
then we have to figure out what HTTP
method we want to use for this path
operation so when it comes to retrieving
data uh you usually use a get operation
and if you don't know which one to use
um you can just go back to this page
right here and it's going to explain uh
what each one's for if you select get
it's going to explain when you would use
a get uh if you want to use a post it's
going to explain when you should use
post but um I already know that for
retrieving data it's usually a get
operation so we're going to keep it as a
get method now for the URL I'm going to
say uh to retrieve uh post we want to go
to the slost
URL so let's save this and then let's
see um if we can retrieve that data so
um if I hit refresh here it's going to
say Hello World um but that's because if
you take a look at this we're at the
root path and that's going to match this
specific path operation uh and this path
operation on/ poost so if we go to SL
posts and then hit enter take a look at
that we have now got our data which is
our post so we've hit that second path
operation that we just created and it
really is as simple as that you just
Define a function you define the HTTP
method and then the URL now there's one
thing to note and that is that um you
know the way that fast API works is that
when anytime we send a request to our
API server uh it's going to actually go
down the list of all of our path
operations um and then it's going to
find the first match and as soon as it
finds the first match it's going to stop
running your code so uh if I actually
change this to just a SL URL just like
this one above what do you think is
going to happen right they both
referenced the uh get method and they
both reference the same URL so which one
do you think is going to win well let's
take a
look if I do just the slash again it
says hello world so it looks like the
first one one and the reason for that is
that once again fast API literally just
goes to the code and it looks for the
first match so there's really only two
criteria in this case what's the HTTP
method it's a get so anytime you go you
work in your browser your browser is
always going to send a get method by
default and then what's the URL so the
URL is a/ URL so it matches this one and
it does not continue past that so it
never runs this code so it sends that
back now if I took this copied it and
moved it at to the
top what do you think is going to happen
which one you think's going to run well
let's hit refresh look at that so that
one Ran So the first path operation that
matches is always going to be the one
that runs simple as that so the order
does in fact matter however if I change
this to
posts and and leave this at the
top right if I hit refresh we get hello
world so what happened was fast API went
on the list right and it received a
request that uh let me just put some
comments so the request reest comes in
uh sorry that's not the way to comment
in Python request comes in with a get
method and it comes in with the uh the
URL is going to be slash all right and
so these are the two things that it
looks for to match so it hits the first
path operation so this is a get so those
two match and then it looks at the URL
which is slash uh but that does not
match so it skips past this one and then
it goes to the next one you know does
and then it checks to see if that
matches so then get matches the URL
matches so then it returns hello world
and that's why it returned hello world
and the reason I wanted to highlight
this is that the order in fact does
matter so you have to keep that in mind
and it can impact the way uh your API
ultimately works so I'm going to just
take this move this to the bottom um but
in this case the order doesn't matter
because they're hitting two different uh
paths or two different
URLs till now we've been using our web
browser to generate h HTTP request to
test our
API and that's fine for now however once
we start getting into more complex um
path operations and routes so things
that involve um having to send a HTTP
put or patch uh or any of the other
methods and having to send data to our
API it gets very complicated because
there's no way to natively do that in
the browser without generating or
building out a complete full front-end
application and to test an API you
shouldn't have to build an entire
frontend application to do that that
would be you know unmanageable
unscalable and so there's a lot of
different tools that we have uh that we
can use to um test our API uh and so one
of these tools is called Postman so if
you go to post man.com downloads uh you
can download this app so go ahead and
just hit the download button it's going
to automatically detect what your um
operating system is but this is a very
simple tool it's just a tool that allows
us to construct our own HTTP requests so
we get to specify the individual uh
fields of an HTTP request so we could
specify you know what is the HTTP method
what's the URL uh what are the headers
that we're going to apply what's the
body what kind of data is that going to
carry is it going to have any
authorization headers so all of these
things we get to construct in a nice
gooey so that we can test our API so go
ahead and download this now I've already
got it downloaded but once you've got it
downloaded open up the uh desktop
application and you should see something
like this right everything should be
relatively empty and what we want to do
is if we want to create a new httv
request all we have to do is hit the
plus button and before I do that what
I'm going to do is um let's change this
to dark themes so themes I think this
looks a little bit better yeah that
looks a lot better and I'm also going to
zoom in for you
guys uh let's make it a little bit more
there you go hopefully that's nice and
easy for you guys to see now so what we
want to do is let's create a new HTTP
request so hit this plus button and you
can see that this provides us all of the
fields that we need to actually create
create an HTTP request so the first
thing that we need to do is specify
what's the HTTP method so if we go back
to our
code right we only have get requests so
whether we want to hit either one of
these path operations it's going to have
to be a get request so we're going to
leave it as get but you can see we have
all the other whoops we have all of the
other options then we have to specify
the URL so this is no different than the
URL that we went to in our browser we
just copy this URL
and we actually need the HTTP in there
as well probably so um if we actually go
back to our server and see where we
started it and actually the best way to
get the URL is just to stop it start it
and then that's going to give us the URL
so we just needed the HTTP
beforehand and then we just paste that
in
there okay and so if I leave this as the
um you know the root path whether I
include the slash it doesn't really
matter actually I can just hit
send and look at this this is the result
that we got back from our API server so
it says message hello world and once
again you guys already know where that
came from and that came from this
specific return statement and so you
could see that this is so much easier
than using a web browser well you guys
may not notice how easy it is at this
point but once we get to constructing
more complex path operations you'll see
that it's so much easier to use a tool
like this and keep in mind this isn't
the only tool that does this there are
plenty of other um applications that
also do this this is just the one that
I'm familiar with and the one that I use
but I don't want to you know Force any
specific application down your throat
you guys can use whichever one you want
so if you already Ed one that you prefer
feel free to stick with it but before we
wrap up this video Let's just test out
our other um specific path so this one's
going to reside on SL poost we're going
to try that we'll do SL poost we'll hit
send and look at that we got our data
that says this is your posts so now we
were successfully able to test both of
our path operations using Postman and
moving forward for the rest of this
course we're no longer going to use the
web browser we're going to use Postman
to test out our
API till now we've only been working
with get requests so all of the HTTP
requests we've sent to our API all have
been get requests and so now we're going
to learn about post requests and they're
a little bit different and I want to
kind of highlight what makes post
requests different than get requests now
we're going to compare the two right now
and I've drawn out a little diagram for
us so at the left side we've got our web
browser or it could be our mobile device
depending on whatever the front end is
and on the right side we've got our API
server so this is our fast API server
now with a get request what we do is we
just send an HTTP get requests and then
we send that to our API server and then
our API server sends back uh some kind
of data depending on what they're trying
to get so if they're trying to get a
whole bunch of posts we send back the
posts now with a post request it's going
to be similar except there's one minor
difference and that is that with a post
request we can send data to the API
server so in this case a lot of times
what you use a post request for is for
creating things so if I want to create a
post I would when I say post I mean like
a social media post not post as in post
request but if I wanted to create a a
social media post I would send an HTTP
post request and I would include all of
the data needed to create a post on my
API server so we'll send that data over
to the API server and the API server
will send back whatever data it thinks
it needs to to send and so in real life
if we were trying to create a post you
we would include whatever data we needed
for a post so in this case we would
include What's the title of the post
what's the content of the post what's
the user of the post we send that to the
API server the API can server can then
talk to whatever database to actually
create the post and then it can send
back some data you know something like
hey I've successfully created the post
um and then here's the final post after
I created it and then send that send
those details back to your web browser
or your mobile devices so think of it
like this a get request is basically
saying hey API server give me some data
whereas a post request is saying hey API
server here's some data do whatever you
need to do with it so it's like so it
really controls the direction uh of flow
of data uh between the frontend and the
API server so get requests are getting
data from the API server whereas a post
request is sending data to the API
server so now that we have a basic
understanding of how post requests work
let's go back to our codee and see if we
can create a path operation for a post
request so let's go below our last path
operation which was for getting posts
and let's create one for creating posts
so first things first let's uh let's
just actually create our decorator first
we'll do app Dot and instead of guest uh
sorry instead of get we're going to say
post so that's all it takes to convert a
traditional get request to a post
request you just say poost and then once
again we're going to say whatever
specific URL the user should go to to
actually create the post uh now I'm
going to do something a little bit bad
I'm going to say the path that we want
to go to is called create post and if
you've ever worked with apis this is
kind of going against best practice but
don't worry we'll correct this in the
next lesson um because there are certain
best practices it's not going to break
our application by any means uh we'll
say this and then we'll say defa and
then here we'll just name our function
I'll just say create post like I said
the name of the function never
matters and then here which all we're
going to do is we're going to
return uh we'll say message oops
message and then uh we'll say
successfully created
posts so let's save that and let's go to
our uh Postman and so we've got already
one request so I could just change this
to
post and then we have to change the url
in this case so we'll go back and see
it's at create post so it's going to be
at create post
and let's hit send and let's see what
happens look at that message
successfully created so we have
successfully sent a post request to our
API now one thing I like to do with
Postman is that you can create multiple
requests and then have them saved so um
I'm going to actually change this back
to just go to
post and then go to get and then we'll
keep that and what we can do is we can
just add another request and so I'm just
going to copy the URL here we're going
to paste this and then this is actually
going to be create posts and then this
going to be a post request and so now we
can hit a get request and then hit a
post request really quickly because
they're essentially uh we've got them in
two different
windows and let's just quickly double
check that still works that's good and
then let's double check it get post that
still works
perfect now that's cool and all however
the whole idea behind a post request is
to send some data to our API server so
how do we do that well let's go to our
post request and what we want to do is
um we want to send some data in the body
of the request and to do that within uh
Postman you would go to the body section
right here and then within body what we
want to do is go to raw and then select
the type and normally when you're
working with apis um you want to use
Json however you can use a XML and a few
others however most people use Json so
we'll select
Json and then we'll do and Jon looks
very it operates very similarly to a
python dictionary so it's uh you know
curly braces and then it's going to be a
whole bunch of key value pairs so here
I'll say What's the title of my post
well title of my post is going to be say
we'll say top beaches in
Florida and then the content of the post
is going to
say check out these awesome be beaches
all right and so now if we hit send
let's see what
happens great so it says successfully
create post so we successfully um hit
this end point but in our path operation
how do we actually extract the data that
we sent in the body how do we retrieve
that body data well what we can do is
within our path operation function I can
say uh I can just assign it some
variable so what variable do we want to
store all that body data you can pick
any name you want I'm just going to say
this represents payload out like it
could be something like body or anything
else so we'll say payload and then what
we want to do is call
in and then we want to say it's going to
be of a type
dict and we want to set this equal to
body and we want to import this so This
is actually something that comes from
the fast API Library so if you
do tab if you hit tab it's going to
automatically import it or you can
select it so you hit body and then
do that and then triple
dots and just to keep in mind right if
you see that from Fast API pams it
imported body so what this is going to
do is uh it's going to extract all of
the fields from the body it's going to
basically convert it to a python
dictionary and it's going to store it
inside a variable named payload pretty
simple and all we have to do is let's
say
print let's just print out payload
now if we hit that post request
again look at this right here we can see
that it converted into a python
dictionary and we extracted the title
field as well as the content field and
so that's how we extract the data from
the body of the payload all right and
just to quickly recap once again we
imported body from fast api. prams and
we let vs code do it automatically for
us I always recommend let vs code do it
for you so that you don't have to
memorize uh and remember you know where
in the fast API Library uh this uh this
property stored so we're taking this
taking the body and then we're
converting it into a dictionary and then
we're storing it inside a property
called payload but you can name this
whatever you
want and so what we can do is we can
take this data and then we can say um
let's say we're going to return back uh
new uh new post and then we're just
going to send the data so we'll say
title and we can actually change this to
a F
string and we'll say
title and then we can pass in payload uh
and you'll see that it's we can just
reference the title
property because it's just a regular
python dictionary and we'll say that the
content is going to
be
payload
content so let's save that and then now
let's hit
send now look at this we got our new
post and it s whoops it looks like I
made a mistake yeah no actually that's
correct title top beaches in Florida
content check out these awesome beaches
so that's pretty simple guys I showed
you guys how to not only send data in
the body within a postman request we're
also able to extract that data and send
it right back to the user now in a real
application we would take the data and
then we would normally store that data
inside our database so that we can
create a new post stored in the database
and then now anytime the user tries to
retrieve the post we can fetch that data
from the database we don't have a
database set up just yet so for now I'm
just showing you guys how to extract
that data and then send it back in the
request in the last lecture we learned
about how to work with post requests we
learned about how to send data in the
body using Postman as well as how to
extract that data within our path
operations so that we can perform some
logic and there's some issues that we're
running into at the moment uh based off
of the way we've kind of set up things
all right and the first thing is it's
kind of hard to get all of those values
from the body we have to you know
extract each one individ ually uh on top
of that the client can send whatever
data that it wants and this is a big
issue right I don't want the front end
to send arbitrary data if the user is
trying to create a post I want the title
I want the content nothing else right I
don't want them to send any extra data
right and on top of that the data itself
isn't getting validated right so how do
I ensure that the user is sending what I
want right what if the user sends a
blank title I can't have a post with a
blank title so how can we validate that
the data that the user sends is actually
valid right and ultimately what we want
to do is we want to force the user into
a schema that we can expect right that's
the term that we always use the apsa
schema where we want to Define exactly
what the data should look like so that
it's almost like a contract between the
front end and the back end saying hey
the back end sends a message to the
front end saying listen I expect my data
to look like this if you don't send me
the data that looks exactly like this
I'm going to give you an error and
that's the way you want to work with
apis you want to explicitly Define
what the data should look like so that
the front end can send you exactly what
you expect it so let's see how we can
Pro do that uh using fast API now what
we're going to do is we're going to make
use of a library called pantic now we've
already got this installed because we
use that all flag when we did pip
install fast API so if you actually go
back to your code and go to your lib
folder uh you should see pantic
somewhere in here and you can see that
pantic is already installed so we can
make use of pantic to Define what our
SCH should look like so let me quickly
show you how to work with pantic it's
really simple but keep in mind
technically pantic has nothing to do
with fast API it's its own complete and
separate library that you can use with
any of your python applications fast API
um just makes use of it so that uh we
can define a schema so let's import
pantic so we say from
pantic import base
model and so if we go down to our um you
know our create post um path operation
uh you know ultimately what we want to
do is we want to tell the front end what
a post or a new post should look like
what data do we expect so let's figure
out what data we want for a specific
post request uh so two things that we
want we want a title which is going to
have which is going to be you know a
string essentially and then we want uh
the content which is the content of the
post which is going to be you know some
sort of string all right and so we want
the we expect the user to send both of
those things and then we don't really
want anything else we don't want the
user to send any other piece of data we
just want these two things and we can
put in any other pieces of data we want
so if we want the user to pass in
something like uh you know what is the
category of the post we can include that
uh we can maybe include um uh maybe uh
the number of I mean I don't know you
can really think of anything maybe a
Boolean that kind of represents you know
is this a published post or do you want
this to be saved as a
so you can construct it however you want
but we're just going to stick to title
and content so the way that this works
is I'm going to remove this comment
right
here we're going to define a class we'll
call this class and then we'll give it
whatever name we want it's going to
represent what uh a post should look
like so I'm just going to call this
post and then this is going
to extend base model so this is what
makes it a special identic model we just
extend base model
and then here we pass in the different
properties for our post and like I said
we want a
title and we also want a the
content uh now what we pass here is
going to be what is this type of data so
if we go to this pantic Library uh
you'll see that there's the different
field types so we can set things to be a
Boolean we can set it to be an INT float
string so all of the common python types
list Tuple it's all available within
pantic so we know what a um ultimately
what a uh a title should look like so
what do you guys think should be the
field type for the title property well I
think it makes sense it should be a
string because this looks like a string
it's got some text it probably should be
a string so let's set this to be string
and the content should be the same thing
it should also be set to
string and now what we can do is let's
take this model
and go down to create posts and instead
of extracting the payload what I'm going
to do is I'm going
to
uh reference that
post identic model and then I'm going to
save this as a variable called post once
again they don't have to match um but
since this will represent the post I can
call this maybe uh newcore poost or
something like that and then uh and then
reference the post pantic model so
what's going to happen is because we
pass this into our path operation fast
API is automatically going to validate
the data that it receives from the
client based off of this model so it's
going to check hey does it have a title
if so is it a string if it if the title
doesn't exist or if it's not a string
and maybe we pass an integer then it's
going to throw an error it's also going
to check for us if content's available
if it is available it's going to make
sure that it's a string and if content
it's not available or if it's not a
string it's going to throw an error so
it's doing all of the validation for us
and it's defining the scheme of what it
should look like for the front end uh
what kind of the data should the front
end send to
us so we're going to remove all of this
nonsense I'm just going to for now just
say
data I don't know new post for
now and now what I'm going to do instead
of print payload we're going to say
print new _
poost so let's save this and then I'm
going to send a post request okay so
that updated fine but let's take a look
at what this printed out so take a look
at what it printed out look at that it
automatically extracted all of that data
for us so now we can access you know
post. tile and we can get the title of
the post and we can also access post.
content to get the content out of the
post and just to prove that to you guys
we'll say post
title so we'll save that we'll send a
request and now look at that look how
easy it is to extract that data because
it's already assigned to that new post
variable and we can just access each
property based off of what the model is
defined
as now that's great and all but let's
check to see if it's actually performing
all of that validation so if I go to my
um Postman and I remove title
let's see what happens I'll hit
send look at this look at this it's
saying that the inside the
body there's a title field and it's
saying a value error it's missing now we
didn't tell fast API just to send this
but it automatically does the validation
for us and sends back an error message
and then it sends back a status code so
this is the status code of the message
it sends a 422 we can change that later
don't worry about that but it's
automatically performing the validation
and that's what's awesome about this and
if we uh if I add the title
back uh what was it top beaches in
Florida and instead actually if I change
this to be um a one or something and I
need that comma let's see what happens
if I hit
send it looks like there's no
errors and that's because the number one
can actually be um converted into a
string so it's not going to throw an
error on that and that's perfectly fine
and
I'll and that's perfectly fine so that's
not a big deal um but let's change this
back like I said it's going to try to
convert whatever data we give it to a
string so as long as it's able to
convert it to a string it's okay and any
integer that we pass can be converted to
a string so I'm going to change this
back and I'll add top beaches in
Florida Florida let's see what happens
if we remove the content now
if I hit
send look at that now it's saying the
content is missing perfect so our
validation is working exactly how we
expect it
to and then I forget what what was it
something something beaches I can't
remember what it
was now let's say that we want to um uh
assign a
property uh that's optional right like
what if we wanted to make it so that the
front end can either choose to send some
piece of data or not send a piece of
data so let's say that we want the user
to be able to Define if a property uh if
a post should be published or not well
we can create a field called
published which is going to be Set uh
which is going to be a type of
Boolean and we can say um you know first
of all we can say if the user doesn't
provide us
a value we can give it a default value
so here I'll say true and so if the user
doesn't provide
published then it's going to default to
true if it does provide published then
whatever value you give it that's what
we're going to use it as and I'm going
to go down
here and we're going to change this to
we're going to grab the published
value and then down here we'll say
published whoops
it's going be set to
true so let's hit
send and we can see that it got set to
true that's good if we set this to
false it's
send we can see that it's false and then
if we remove this all
together move that comma as well hit
send look at that it defaults to true so
now we've created an App an optional
field for our schema so the user doesn't
have to provide this and it's going to
default to true in this
case now let's say we wanted to create
another field however instead of giving
it a default value if it's not sent we
want it to default To None So we want it
to be completely optional and we're not
going to store any value if the user
doesn't provide it what we can do is
let's say the field is a rating let's
say the user can give each post a rating
what we can say is optional
and we're going to have to import
optional uh from typing from the typing
Library so import
optional and then we have to pass in the
type so what is it going to be in this
case a rating I think an integer makes
sense and then we can say equals to
none so this is going to be a fully
optional field and if the user doesn't
provide it it's going to default to a
value of
none and so here I'm just going to get
the uh the value of our rating
and so if I hit send right now in our
body we don't have a rating field I hit
send you can see that it defaults to a
value of none because we set this to be
optional
none
however if I pass in a rating field I
need to give it a value some kind of
value so I'll say we give this maybe
like four stars or
something I hit send we can see that now
look the value of rating is set to
four and then finally the last thing I
want to note is because we set the type
to be an integer so even though it's
optional we still have to specify the
type if I give this a value of a string
so you know something like hello which
is not a valid rating take a look at
what happens look at that it says in the
body the rating field the value is not a
valid integer so it wasn't able to
convert whatever value we sent into
integer and so that's why it's throwing
there and saying like this does not
match up with the schema and it's
throwing an error and so that's what's
awesome about this is now we can ensure
that our front end is sending the exact
data that we expect by using these
pantic
models so moving forward in this course
we are going to really make use of
pantic mods to ensure that the schemas
not only receiving data from the front
end but also sending data back is all um
matching up with our organized schema
and actually there's one last thing I
want to to show you guys and that is
that when we actually um kind of extract
that data and save it into new post uh
it actually stores it as a pantic model
so it's a specific pantic model and each
pantic model has a method called dict so
if I do um if I print new post below
this what we can do is if you ever need
to convert your pantic model to a
dictionary all we have to do is write
the name of the variable
and we say
dot
dict so this is going to take that
pantic model and then it's going to
convert it to a dictionary so let's
print that
out let's save it let's hit
send whoops and I forgot to it's still
throwing a validation error but that's
to be expected so we'll say change that
to
four all right take a look at the two
different things so this is a pantic
model that's just printing out the
different uh properties of that of that
model whereas this is a regular python
dictionary so we can just send back a
dictionary if we want to so we do return
new
post and save that now if I hit send
we're just sending back a dictionary and
so now we send back the data with all of
the different properties and so you'll
see that this is actually a nice little
handy tool to be able to converted to a
dictionary uh which is something that
we'll be needing to do in some of the
future lectures so I wanted to make sure
we just cover our bases real quick on
that and also I don't like calling this
new post I'm just going to change this
to post for now because I think that's a
little bit better my opinion because it
is just a post we don't need to know
that it's a new post it clearly
is and let's just double check that
everything works let's hit send
perfect in this lesson we're going to
talk about what a crud application is as
well as what are standard conventions
when it comes to creating an API for a
crud based application
so crud is an acronym that represents
the four main functions of an
application so any application
regardless of what it is needs to be
able to create things so in our case
since we're building a you know a social
media type application we need to be
able to create posts make new posts we
need to be able to read posts uh and so
that includes you know retrieving all of
the pre-existing posts we need to be
able to update a post if we want to
implement that functionality so if we
decide to change what our post says we
would use the update functionality and
then finally we need to be able to
delete a post and so the c r u d that
represents the four main functions of
any cred based application so it's
nothing more than an acronym however I
created the slide so that you guys can
understand what our standard convention
when it comes to creating an API for a
cred based application because there are
certain bre best practices that we need
to follow and so when it comes to naming
the URL and the paths for each operation
there's a standard convention and the
first thing that I want to point out is
since we're working with posts it makes
sense to name all of the URLs all the
paths uh with/ posts and it's important
that you use the plural form of posts
you don't want to do SL poost you want
to do SL posts as in plural this is
standard convention for apis and if we
were working with users and we wanted to
be able to create read update and delete
users it wouldn't be SL user it would be
slash users so always use the plural
that's standard convention now when it
comes to creating a post right that
that's always going to be a post request
so we've got the create functionality
right here and we can see that we have
to send a post request standard
convention anytime you want to create an
entity it's going to be a post
request and the URL or the path for that
specific request is always going to be
slost in this case and if you want to
see what that looks like for The
Decorator and fast API it's pretty
simple you just do app. postpost so this
is something you guys already know now
when it comes to read functionality
which would be you know reading or
retrieving pre-existing posts there's
actually two different path operations
we're going to create so the first one
is going to be/ poost and this is going
to be for retrieving either all of the
posts or multiple posts depending on
what filter that we use and so when it
comes to retrieving information uh from
a database or anything like that
retrieving data it's always going to be
a get operation so you send a get
request to SL posts and if you want to
see what that face The Decorator on Fast
AP would look like it's just app.get
slost once again we already have this
set up up in our application so far
however there's also going to be another
path operation for reading right and
that's if you want to get one individual
post so if we want to get detailed
information about one specific post
we're going to send a get request to SL
posts slash and then we've got this ID
right here so anytime you create
something uh what's going to happen is
anytime you add something to a database
the database is going to give it that
specific item a unique identifier so
that we can uniquely identify that spef
specific entry and so if I want to get
detailed information about a specific
post I would just send a request to/
poost and then pass the ID of that
specific post I'm interested in so
that's what this ID represents and
within fast API if you want to see what
that actually looks like you would just
do app.get SL poost and then you do
curly braces and then ID and that'll
allow you to extract the ID from the
specific URL of the request and then we
can you know take that URL uh sorry take
that ID and then you know send it out to
our database so that we can retrieve the
information so there's always going to
be two specific path operations for read
functionality then we have
update uh so this would involve updating
uh a pre-existing post so maybe we you
know posted out something and then we
realize we said something offensive and
we want to update it before anyone takes
a screenshot of it now when it comes to
updating right there's two different
HTTP methods that we can use we can use
put or patch and it's really a matter of
user preference the only difference is
that I want to I don't want to spend too
much time on on it is that when we use
put that you the idea is that you pass
all of the information for updating it
so all of the fields have to be sent um
to the to the API server whereas a patch
we can just send just the specific field
that we want to change so put you want
to change the entire thing you have to
pass every every field even if it's
going to be the same and most Fields
don't change whereas a patch we would
just change the one specific field so as
an example uh as a you know if we're
working with users actually if we're
working with posts and let's say I
wanted to change the title all right I
want to update the title of a post if I
used a put request I'd have to give the
new title and I would have to give the
pre-existing content right because the
put uh the idea behind put is that you
have to provide all of the same
information so that we can on the back
end just take all the information and
then update the entity whereas a patch
operation I can just send the title and
then my backend should know how to just
update that one field we're going to
stick with put I believe uh in our
application but really at the end of the
day it doesn't really matter it's just a
matter of you preference but with update
just like when it comes to retrieving
one specific post we have to pass in the
ID so that we know which specific post
we want to
update and for The Decorator and fast
API the only thing that we change is
it's going to be app. put uh and then we
can pass in the ID like we did before
and then finally we have delete so if
you want to delete a post once again
you're going to send a delete request so
that's the HTTP verb is going to be
delete and then we have to pass in the
specific ID of the post as well and then
this is what the fast a API um decorator
is going to look like so it's actually
not that hard it's fairly simple and
you'll see that once you create one crud
API creating another one is almost a
matter of copying and pasting really uh
and so in the next video we're going to
make a few changes to our API so that we
can make sure that we follow uh this
naming convention because right now I
believe when it comes to creating a post
instead of just using SL poost we called
it SLC create post which once again is
not following best practice so we'll
update that in the next video all right
guys so in the last lesson we learned
about best practice and naming
conventions for an API so what I want to
do is quickly go into all the code that
we have and make changes so that we
follow best practices and so if you take
a look at our get requests you can see
we say send a get request to/ posts
that's perfect uh we don't need to
change anything to that however the
issue is is our uh create post
functionality so the path for creating
posts we can see that we send it to a
URL of SLC create post that is not going
and following best practi so what we do
just change this to be SL
posts and that's all we have to do uh
and so we'll save
this and um we'll we'll just double
check inside our um post man just to
make sure we update that as well so this
is going to be to SL poost and then
we'll just test this out to make sure we
didn't break anything and it looks like
it's still working just
fine all right guys so if we take a look
at our code you can see that for our
create post path function uh we're not
actually doing anything with the data
we're not actually saving the post
anywhere right now we just print it out
and then send it back to the user so
that's not exactly how a real
application would work and so what I
want to do is I want to start saving
these posts I want to start turning this
into a real fully functioning
application now ideally we're going to
save this uh within a database because
that's how any application works you
want to take a post you want to save it
in database so that you can persist that
data however we're not quite ready to
handle working with the database it's a
little complex we're going to get to it
in this course however I want to keep
things simple so what we're going to do
is we're going to save the posts in
memory and how do we do that easy I'm
just going to create a variable uh just
globally that's going to store all of
our posts so I'm going to say mycore
posts and this is just going to be an
array and so this array is going to
contain an uh whole bunch of posts
objects right and what each post is
going to be is it's going to be
essentially a dictionary and the
dictionary is going to look kind of like
this so we're going to have a couple
properties so we already know that our
post is going to have a title and then
that'll have you know whatever you know
title of post one or whatever and then
we're going to have the content of
course and I'll just say content of post
one this is just an example
post and then what we'll also do is like
I mentioned before anytime you save an
applica save a uh piece of information
within a database the database is going
to create a unique uh identifier an ID
uh now since we're not working with
databases there's no uh ID however it's
going to create issues because uh you
know if you remember when it when it
comes to working with um crud based apis
we need to be able to fetch data and
update data based off of the ID of the
specific post so we do need to still
have an ID so that we can uniquely
reference any single item uh within this
array so we're going to have another
field called
ID and then this is just going to have
you know be some random integer you know
1 2 3 4 5 it doesn't matter it's just
got to be unique that's all that matters
so this is what our post is going to
look like and we're going to just store
it in this array so we're going to have
multiple posts and I'm going to keep
this one hardcoded in here because every
time we change our code and hit save and
refresh guess what it's going to clear
this out because remember this is just
stored in memory so every time our
application restarts we're going to lose
that data so just to keep things simple
I'm going to hardcode another uh another
entry so for this post we'll say the
title
is uh favorite
foods and the content will
be I like pizza
and we'll just give this an ID of
two all right and so now that we
actually have someplace to store our
post we can actually test out our get
post functionality to see if it works so
I'm going to save this we're going to go
back to postman so find the one with the
get operation where we're retrieving the
posts and then we'll hit send let's see
well when we hit send nothing happens of
course because we actually have to
update the code to send that data so
let's let's go back to our code and
let's go to our get post so right now
we're just sending back this
information so let's update this so that
we return my posts and this should be
fairly straightforward what we can do is
we can just keep this property called
data and then we can just remove this
and just pass along mycore
posts and so what's going to happen is
fast API is great because if I pass in
an array like this it'll automatically
serialize it so it's going to convert it
into Json Json has something that's also
very similar to an array and it's going
to change that into a Json format so
that we can send it over our API so
that's all we have to do we just have to
pass in the array and it's going to send
that now if we try this look at that so
we get the data property and within here
we have an array so this is Json also
has a concept of arrays and then within
here you can see we've got our post one
and our post to so um that's really as
simple as how to work with our API how
to actually retrieve posts in the next
video we're going to update the um
create post path operation so that we
can figure out how to add a new post
into our my posts
array all right guys so let's update our
create post path operation function so
that we can uh retrieve the title and
the content uh from our front end and
then create a brand new post and store
it within our my posts array so how do
we do that well we already know that we
can retrieve retrieve our post by
referencing this post variable because
this will take our schema which remember
we defined with pantic it's going to do
all the validation and it's going to
store it within post and so this is
still going to be a a pantic model
however our um our array is going to be
an array of dictionaries so we have to
convert that to dictionaries and we
already know that we can convert any
pantic model to a dictionary by doing
dict uh and then that'll turn it into a
standard python dictionary and at that
point uh it's pretty simple this is just
standard python at this point we can
just do a myor posts.
append and then we can append post. dict
just like we did before we don't we can
remove these print statements they're
just cluttering things
up however there's one little issue like
I said we need to have an ID for every
entry uh and normally the database
handles that but since we are not
actually working with a real database
we're going to have to do this in
software so what I'm going to do is
we're just going to assign it a random
integer um not really that reliable but
if we pick a random number between 1 and
you know 10 million the odds of us
hitting the same number twice is almost
Next To None So what we're going to do
is we're going to use the random package
uh so we'll say from random
import Rand range and this is what we're
going to use to uh create a random
number or a random
integer and so so instead of doing this
I'm actually going to remove this for a
second and I spelled append wrong as
well what we're going to do is I'm going
to say postore dict which is going to be
the um post penic model converted to a
dictionary I'm going to set that equal
to post. dict okay so this is going to
be the dictionary and so now that we
have a regular python dictionary what we
can say is postore
addict and then I'm going to reference
the ID field that I'm creating and I'm
going to assign that to be a random
number so we're going to give it a range
of
0o two and then just pick some really
really really really large number so
this is going to ensure that pretty much
any entry for development purposes is
going to be
unique we will'll append that to the
array and then here's the thing when it
comes to how a usual API works is that
when a front end sends the data to
create a new post after we create the
post stored in our database we should
send back the newly created post
including the brand new new ID so let's
send that back so in this case I'm going
to send back postore dict cuz that's
going to be the brand new post that we
uh add to the specif add to our posts
array so let's try this
out uh let's go to our post request that
we
have and let's see all of our data so
we've got a couple things title content
rating I don't really care about the
rating um but I'll just leave it in
there for now it shouldn't matter
and then we'll just hit send and let's
see what happens and it looks like we
got an error so let's see what
happened all right it looks like there's
an and I already see what happened I
forgot to actually include postore dict
we actually have to pass in what we want
to append to the array let's save that
try this again hopefully no errors look
at that guys so it looks like we got
back the newly created entry and we can
see that it has an idea of whatever that
number is and if we do a get request now
to retrieve all of our posts we should
see that newly created entry so let's
take a look so we've got post one post
two and then we've got that brand new
post look at that guys so we are a
little bit less than halfway done with
creating our crud based
application now before moving any
further and writing any more code what I
want to do is I want to actually save
these requests because right now they're
just kind of stored in me if we close
out Postman it'll still remember it but
what we can do is we can create a
collection so here I'm going to select
create collection and I'm going to give
this a name so I'm just going to name
this after my project so I can call this
you know fast API course or you know
since this is a social media app we can
call it whatever we would call it I'm
just going to call it fast API course
we'll save
that and then what I want to do is I
want to save these two requests so that
I don't have to remember this in case
they accidentally get deleted so I'll
hit save save as
we'll save it and then um you can give
it any name so this is going to be um I
forget this is the get request so I'm
going to say I'm going to call this get
posts I'm going to store it inside this
collection right and so now within this
collection you can see this request is
stored in there and I'm going to do the
same thing for the Post request so this
is for creating post so we'll do save as
again I'm going to say uh create
post and then it's already remembers the
most recent uh collection but go ahead
and select the collection if it didn't
remember that and then we'll hit save
and so now they're both saved in here
and we can easily bring these up anytime
even if we close out all of our requests
so I closed everything out can bring
that right back up it's going to
remember everything and then same thing
with the post request if I go to the
body it even remembers the fields so
Postman one of my favorite tools when it
comes to working with apis and you know
as this course goes along you're going
to continue to learn more and more
things about
Postman okay guys let's continue
building out our crud application the
next function I want to implement is is
retrieving one individual post and so
let's define a function for that so here
I'll call this get post keep in mind
this is singular so I call this get post
whereas to retrieve all posts it's get
posts but like I said the name of these
functions don't actually matter it's
just more for for you more for
readability and The Decorator is going
to look like this and so this is based
off of that slide I already showed you
so it's going to be a get method and
then here the URL is going to be SL
posts
ID right because the user is going to
provide us the ID of the specific post
that they're interested in and so that's
going to get embedded in the URL so
they'll send a get request to slost
slash and then whatever ID so if they
want to see the information for uh post
one they'll pass in a value of one and
what this is actually referred to the
proper terminology for this is that this
is called a path parameter so this ID
field represents a path parameter and
this parameter happens to represent the
ID of a specific post the user is
interested in seeing and so what we can
do is fast API will automatically
extract this ID and then we can pass it
right into our function so now our
function has access to whatever value
was in that URL right there and so if we
want to I can do a quick print of ID and
then we'll just return some hardcoded
data so I'll just say data actually
we'll call this uh how about postore
detail I'll say this is the
post you're interested
in or even better what I can do is uh
we'll change this to an F string and
I'll just
say here is
post and then we can just pass an
ID so let's save that we'll go to
postman and what we want to do is we
want to create a new post but let's
create it in our collection so I'm going
to go in there select add request give
it whatever name you want I'll say get
one
post and then for the the URL just copy
the get posts
URL and then we want to pass in the ID
that we're interested so we just just do
slash and then in this case I'm going to
get the post with an ID of Two And the
reason why I'm doing that is because
we've hardcoded one of our posts S ID of
to so I know that's always going to be
there and then we can just try sending
this and see what happens so it says
post detail here is post and then post
number two so it looks like we were
successfully able to extract the ID uh
the path paramet that was passed into
the specific URL that the user sent a
request to so we now have access to that
at that point we can just find whichever
um entry in my post has that specific ID
now we have to implement the logic for
actually getting that post and so
there's many different ways of doing
this and I'm telling you right now this
is probably not the best way of doing
this I'm not really even a python expert
I'm sure there's much better ways of
grabbing this information however uh
keep in mind the codee's going to be
changed later on once we start working
with the database so this at this point
is just basic python logic uh and I do
want to keep I do want you guys to keep
in mind that this may not be best
practice for uh the best way of
retrieving an individual post but I'm
just going to create a simple function
and uh it's going to be called find post
so this is how you find a post by an ID
so the so we'll pass in an ID in this
function to retrieve the post and what
we'll do is we'll iterate over the my
post so we'll say 4 p in my
posts and we'll say if p so P represents
the specific post that we're iterating
over so if this specific post has an
ID which
equals the ID that was passed into the
function then we'll return P we'll
return that specific
post and then at this point we can call
this function so I'm going to remove
that print statement and say post equals
findor poost
ID and then for this we can just remove
this and just return
post let's save this let's go to back to
postman and let's try this
out and it looks like I got an error so
something happened and let's actually
take a look at our
code well guys I think I found the issue
so the reason why we keep getting none
right if I keep sending hting send it
says None and what I did was I just
printed out the post to see what we got
and it actually just prints out none so
it for some reason we're unable to find
post and I think I know exactly why and
so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
do a print of ID again and this is going
to teach us an important lesson so going
to send another
request and it prints out two however
what we're going to do is I'm actually
going to get the type of ID so I forget
how to do that I think it's the type
I think I could just do type in Python
so I'm going to figure out what is the
actual type of
ID and now if I send this request
again right you could see that the type
is actually a string and not an integer
and so when we pass this check in where
we say if p uh ID so if we get the ID
field and compare it to the ID that we
pass in it's never going to equal that
because one's an integer the other one's
a string they're never going to be equal
so the first thing that we actually have
to do is before we call this function we
have to convert it to an integer so I
can just say
int that's going to convert it to an
INT save that and then at this point if
I send this it should now work look at
that so keep in mind guys anytime we um
have a path parameter it's always going
to be returned as a string even if it
represents an integer or a number we
always have to manually convert it
ourselves so don't forget to do
that now there is one little issue with
what we're doing so everything's working
and if I actually change this to a one
we should get a different post so
everything's working great however what
happens if I type this well let's hit
send well we get an error right because
we're trying to convert this to an INT
and it's going to throw an error and
then instead of sending back a nice you
know built-in response we just get an
internal server error and the user has
no idea what exactly is wrong so we want
to provide it feedback so how can we
perform some kind of validation to
ensure that whatever data that's passed
into this path parameter can actually be
properly converted to an integer well we
can perform validation with fast API so
here for ID what we can do is we can say
I want this to be an integer so what
it's going to do is it's first of all
going to validate that it can be
converted to an integer and then it'll
automatically convert it to an integer
for us so we no longer have to convert
this ourselves so here I can just pass
an ID because this will make sure that
it's already converted and so now if I
save
this and I change this back to a number
first let's make sure that everything's
working so it automatically converted it
to an integer and now if I pass in you
know a
string it's now going to throw an error
it's going to say for a path parameter
of ID you can see that this value is not
a valid integer and so now the front end
has a good way of understanding what
they did wrong and you know this can be
anything right so if you wanted this to
rep to be a string right we can have
this automatically get validated as a
string and converted into a string so
that uh if they do actually send a
string no errors right and then if they
try to actually even if you put in a
number it's not going to throw an error
because any number can actually be
converted into a
string but we want an integer so I'm
going to change this back to an
integer and then we'll just hard code
this as two perfect make sure you save
your request and so now we've now
implemented our third function within
our Crow app so we've just got two more
we got a handle updating and deleting
posts but we've got all getting all
posts creating a post and then getting
an individual post and you'll see that U
for the last two it's pretty much the
same thing right we just have to Define
our specific decorator and then Define
the logic for actually creating and
deleting a post from that array or
updating uh a post as
well now before we move on I do want to
show you guys one potential issue that
you can run into if you don't quite
understand how these routes work and how
order matters within fast API so what
I'm going to do is I'm just going to
create a dummy route and you guys don't
need to follow along on this is just a
quick little demonstration and I'm just
going to make this another get request
uh or Handler for a get request and then
this one's going to be posts SL latest
so what this will do is when the user
sends a request a get request to this
specific path latest path we're going to
grab whatever the latest post
is and so here I'll just say uh
def get latest post
and so all I'm going to do is I'm going
to reference our my post list and I'll
say we'll get the length of my
post and then we'll just minus one so
this will grab the latest post and then
what we're going to do is just return
that here we'll say
detail and then we'll pass in and
actually let me store this in a variable
post equals and then we'll return
post we'll save this and I'm going to
show you what happen so let's create a
new
request I just copy the URL from the
previous one then here we're going to
change this to latest let's see what
happens interesting we get an error so
what exactly happened well let's take a
look at the error it's saying that um we
have a um p parameter called ID and it
looks like it's saying that this is not
a valid integer so I'm not even sure why
it's referencing this error because if
we take a look at our code right there's
there's no path parameter here so what
is exactly happening well let's take a
look right our request looks like this
so it's going to slost SL latest so when
we send this request what's going to
happen is that we're going to start all
the way at the top and fast API is going
to go through the list of all of our um
all of our paths and it's going to find
the first match so we have one at just
the root URL so it's not going to match
that we have one at/ posts it's once
again not going to match that this one
is for a post request so it's not going
to match that cuz we sent a get request
but then something interesting happens
here when we get to this get request
right so this handles a get request and
then it matches SL posts and then some
variable so technically that variable
could be latest you see the issue that
we're running into because there's no
way for fast API to know that that route
was meant for that that request was
meant for this specific path right
because it does technically match on
this and then what happens is since it
matches on this route it then tries to
perform validation on ID which is in
this case it's going to end up being
latest and then it's going to throw an
error because latest can't be converted
to an integer and so this is the example
of where order matters so you have to be
careful when you structure your API
especially with your with your paths and
your URLs you want to make sure that you
don't run into this type of ISS issue so
you know one thing in this case you
could do is just move this up that would
fix the issue because now if you save
this and then run this right it works
and if you uh try to reference a
specific ID that's going to work as
well well in that case let's try one yep
and so that works as well because uh SL
poost SL1 will never match this one
it'll only match this
one uh so be very careful when it comes
to your it always works top down so
anytime you're working with path
parameters it could potentially result
in you guys accidentally matching other
routes by accident so you know there's
different ways to get around this like I
said you can just move this up or if you
wanted to change the url Al together so
that this is like a SL poost slash
um I don't know you know just put in
another keyword something like a a
recent or something recent latest or
something well actually even then that
would yeah and so just keep and so I
just want to make sure you keep that in
mind when you're structuring your API
because anytime you have a path
parameter it could result in you um
accidentally matching requests that were
meant for a different uh for a different
route so I'm just going to delete this
this was merely just for a demonstration
purposes and I just want to make sure
that you guys understand that fast API
uh just looks at all of your paths and
just works its way down the list till it
finds the first
match for our get post path operation
specifically the one where we retrieve
one specific post we do run into a
little bit of an issue so if we go to
our Postman real quick and uh send a
request to get one post but in this case
instead of doing one or two uh what I
want to do is I want you to put in the
ID uh put in an ID uh that doesn't exist
so we only have right now um posts with
an ID of one and two what happens if we
send it with a ID of five you can see
what we get back it says null right and
I don't like that because it doesn't
really give the front end any feedback
as to what exactly is happening uh so
they don't actually know you know they
don't know if some kind of error
occurred or if we were unable to
retrieve this information properly or if
there's a server error or if this item
doesn't ultimately exist and so we need
a way to accurately tell the front end
that hey the ID that you're searching
for does not actually exist in our
database and the best way to do that is
through a method that I'm sure you guys
are already a little bit familiar with
so right here I've got my GitHub page uh
for our course
and you can see it's just GitHub my
username and then the name of the repo
but if I search for if I put in a whole
bunch of letters afterward what's going
to happen is GitHub is going to look for
a repo with this name that doesn't exist
and let's see what happens it gets a 404
and I'm sure you guys have seen a 404
error at least once before in your life
so that's a specific HTTP status code
that represents that this item was not
found that does not exist and HTTP
status codes are important we haven't
really talked about it in this course
that at this point but there's a lot of
different status codes and uh if you
actually just search for HTTP status
code you could just grab one of the top
links I'm going to go take a look at the
Mozilla one and you'll see all of the
different HTTP status codes and you'll
see when to use them now most of the
time you're going to see that we get a
200 response back that's the default one
the fast API sends that usually means
that everything's good everything worked
that's why it says okay however we do
have other ones that we do also commonly
use so anytime you create something so
within your crud application for create
anytime you send a post request usually
after you create that entity you send a
2011 back instead of a traditional 200
so there's a lot of HTTP status codes
and we're going to cover all of those in
future lectures but the ones we're
interested in is for when we have an
error so if we scroll down 400 usually
means there's some kind of bad error
something happened and most importantly
we want the 404 not found so the server
cannot find the requested resource so
that's the exactly what we're looking
for uh keep in mind there's also 500
status codes which means you know some
kind of server area server error or
server failure so what we're going to do
is I'm going to go back to our
code and what we need to do is we need
to manipulate the response because right
now we're getting a 200 back we're
getting a status code of 200 if I send
it it says null and then it just sends
200 so that doesn't really give us a
good idea as to what's happening so how
do we manipulate the response well we
have to first of all import the response
from Fast AP I and then what we're going
to do is we're just going to pass it in
as a parameter into our path operation
function so I'll just call this I'll
store it in a variable called
response and so once you get access to
the response object we can tweak it
however we want so what I'm going to do
is um after we search for post if we
didn't find a post I'm just going to do
a quick check I'm going to say if
not
post right that means if we didn't find
a post what we're going to do is we're
going to set the response and then we're
going to grab a property off of response
called status code so here we can tweak
the status code of the response and I'm
going to say hey I want this to be a
404 all right now let's save
it now if I hit send it still says post
detail none but take a look at the
status code it's now updated to 404 and
if I change this to an ID that does
exist right we get the post properly and
the status code changes to 200 which
means everything is good so that's one
way of doing it however there's a
slightly better way of doing it uh same
concept um but instead of hardcoding the
value or trying to remember it what we
can do is we can
import
um from the fast API Library something
called
status and so now instead of having to
remember what to use we can just type in
status and then it's going to show you
all of the different HTTP codes H and so
now you can just quickly just look
through which one over one sounds the
most accurate so we'll grab the 404
and now you don't need to worry about
putting hard coding in a number we can
just reference um you know I guess it's
an it's probably an enumerator but I'm
not really sure so it doesn't really
matter um and then that's all you have
to do so let's test this out
again so 200 good change this to five
perfect um but the next thing I want to
do is I don't want to return null that
looks ugly so instead I'd like to
actually throw an error so in this case
uh in this if statement I'm just going
to call a return that only is going to
ever run if uh post doesn't exist and
we'll just say uh in this
case detail or we'll say message I'll
just say
message FST string and we'll say post
with
ID and we'll pass in what was the ID and
we'll say uh was not
found all right and and now if we try
this look at that we get our air post
with ID was not found and that matches
up with the ID that we gave it and we
got our 404 now this was uh this is one
solution however I think this is a
little bit sloppy and there's a better
way of doing it uh instead what we can
do is we can raage raise an HTTP
exception so this is a built-in
exception into fast API that'll
automatically um you know you can pass
in what the specific error code you want
as well as the message and so that way
you don't have to hardcode all of this
and it just makes everything look a lot
simpler so we'll go to the fast API up
here and we're going to import something
called HTTP
exception and now we can delete all of
this nonsense code actually I'm just
going to comment it for now just so I
can reference it in a second and all we
have to say is we'll raise an exception
so we raise HTTP
exception and then we have to pass in
two things so first is the status code
so we'll set the status code to be
status
and then same thing right so far
nothing's really
changed and then here we'll just pass in
the value for detail which is going to
be the message that uh fast API
automatically responds back with and I'm
going to pass in the same exact F
string and so now we've basically
replaced this with just this one line
right here this HTTP exception I think
this looks a little bit nicer I don't
like having to do the set the response
and then having to pass in but I don't
like having to pass in the response into
the path operation function having to
set a property and then having to return
my message we can remove all of this
nonsense and I can get rid of all of
these comments and I think this is just
a little bit cleaner and moving forward
we're going to be using these HTTP
exceptions a lot because all we have to
do is just pass in what's the HTTP
status code and then the message we want
to send back to the user and then that's
what's going to be sent to them so now
once again we're going to try this
out and look at that right so we got the
404 and got the message uh the detailed
message right a lot cleaner a lot
simpler now before we move any further
and before we wrap up this video I did
mention that anytime we create something
we should send back a 2011 so if we go
back to our create
post and then we'll just create a new
post again we can just send this we
created a new post look at the status
code that gets sent back it's got it
gets sent back at 200 and that is wrong
remember anytime we create an entity
based off of that documentation we
should send a 2011 so how exactly do we
send how do we change what the default
status code is for a specific path
operation well what we can do is we'll
go back to our code and let's find our
uh create post and if you want to change
the default status code uh what we do is
inside the inside The Decorator we'll
pass in another option so we'll say
status code here and then we set this to
be status and then what whatever our
specific status code is so I want 2011
and then that's all you have to do so
now by default anytime someone uh sends
a request to create posts we're going to
send a 2011 created so we'll save that
we'll give it another shot if I try this
again now we get a 2011 perfect so at
this point I think you guys will have a
solid understanding of how to change
status codes whether it's because we're
trying to throw an exception or if we
want to just change the default status
code of a specific path
operation all right guys so now it's
time to move on to uh deleting a post so
to delete a post remember we're going to
start off with our decorator and it's
going to request or it's going to
require a delete uh HTTP
request right and then the URL is going
to be the same so it's going to be posts
and then we're going to need the ID so
we can figure out which post to actually
delete right then let's define our
function so I'm just going to call this
delete post
and so here we have to implement the
logic for deleting post so what are we
going to do well uh for me there's many
different ways you know deleting a post
is just a matter of trying to figure out
um which
specific uh dictionary within this array
has a specific ID of whatever ID we give
it and then we just remove it from the
array so how however you want to do it
go ahead and do it I'm going to just
show you the first way that I thought of
uh like I said this doesn't actually
have anything to do with fast API this
is more of just simply working with
python so I'm telling you right up front
this may not be the most efficient way
to do it but like I said we're
eventually going to implement a real
database so it doesn't really matter how
you do it as long as it
works and so the first thing that we're
going to do is I'm going to look to find
uh the
index uh in the array that has
as required ID we're going to look for
what we're going to try to get the index
of that specific item and then all we're
going to do is we'll do a um
myor posts. poop and then just pass in
the index and so that's how we remove it
from that array pretty simple and what
I'm going to do is I'm going to actually
just Define a function out here just to
keep things simple so this is going to
be called find
uncore index poost and then we're going
to pass in the ID that we're interested
in and then we're going to iterate over
the array but we're also going to grab
the specific index as we iterate over it
and so you do that by using
enumerate so this is going to iterate
over it we'll get the access to the
individual post that we're iterating
over as well as the index and so we'll
say if P if the ID equals equals
ID and I forgot the in keyword
here we'll just return I so this is
going to give us the index uh of the
dictionary with that specific
ID so here we can just call that
function and we'll set it equal to the
index so index equals find _ index of
post pass in ID so we now have the index
and at this point I can just do a my
posts. pop and then just pass in index
and then we'll try to do a return and
then here I'm just going to pass
in uh we'll say
message we'll say
post was successfully deleted but let's
give this a shot so first of all let's
get all the
posts right if I do a get all posts
you'll see that we have two posts and
then I'm going to create a new
request and this will be called delete
post
just going to copy that URL pass it in
there and so here I'm going to try and
delete with a uh post of a value of
one and I realized I still left it as
get so we're going to change it to
delete right and so now it throws an
error so what exactly happened well if
we go back to here and then go back to
our console it says it says nontype
object can cannot be interpreted as an
integer and uh and I realized I forgot
to actually pass in ID into our function
so that's why it was giving us that
error so now let's try this
again and we see that we get the message
says post was successfully deleted
that's good however um you'll see that
the status code is 200 and so if we
actually go back to our status codes
you'll see that there's a uh specific
status code that we should be using for
when we delete something and that status
code is a 204 and like I said you know
you can read the documentation but this
is something that just you know comes
with time of working with API so you'll
know that anytime you want to delete
something uh you want to use a a 204 but
before we actually do that let's verify
that it actually deleted it so we'll go
to get posts and I'll send a request and
we can see that there's only one post so
it clearly did work um but let's update
the status code so do you guys remember
how to update the status code uh the
default status code of a specific path
operation we just pass in status code
into The Decorator and then we'll do
status and then we'll just get our
204 now let's try to uh delete something
again we'll try to delete uh where's my
delete we'll try to delete post one
again let's see what happens so you'll
see here that we get the 204 so
everything looks good we didn't get any
data back and if we go back to our
application you'll see that we got a an
eror which says too much data for
declared content length and what's
Happening Here is I actually have to
look up this error and that's because
anytime you send back a 204 the idea is
that since we delete anything we
shouldn't really be sending any data
back and so when we try to send this
message back fast API essentially throws
in there saying like listen you're
sending a 204 we should not be sending
anything back so that's how they kind of
implemented fast API uh and so the what
you should be doing is if you want to do
if you what we should do is actually
just delete delete this we should grab
the
response and then just pass in status
code
status HTTP 204 right so basically we
don't want to actually send any data
back anytime someone deletes something
we just want to send a 204 and then one
of the requirements for that to work is
that we don't send any data back I know
it's a little confusing uh if you
actually just Google this error uh
you'll probably get better explanation
um but 204 when you delete something
don't want to send any data back that's
kind of the expected result so let's try
this
again let's send
a all right so we got the 204 no data
comes back and no errors so that's all
we have to do so this is just something
special that you have to do for delete
uh within fast API just keep that in
mind it's more of just a copy a cut and
paste type scenario however before we
wrap up this uh delete video uh we are
still running into one tiny issue
if I try to grab a uh an ID that doesn't
exist let's see what happens well now we
get a 500 error and we get an error
because well non type object cannot be
interpreted as an integer so uh since we
tried to grab the index from this uh
find index post it's going to return
nothing because there's no post uh that
has an IDE of five so we get nothing and
then we try to pop with an index of none
that creates an error so we need to put
in a simple if statement to actually
catch that scenario so we'll say if
index equals equals none so it'll return
none if it doesn't exist what are we
going to do well we're going to
raise an exception again so we can use
that raise HTTP exception and we'll just
say status code equals uh in this case
uh we want to send a 404 like we
normally do so we'll say status.
HTTP
404 and then we can send a detailed
message so in this case uh you know
we'll do once again another F
string and we'll say post with
ID pass the ID does not
exist let's try this
out perfect 404 post with ID does not
exist let's just make sure we didn't
break the original functionality we
delete it perfect and let's just double
check there's no errors there we go so
everything looks good to go guys uh so
we'll wrap up this video and then in the
next video we'll take a look at how we
can update
posts all right guys we're almost done
with all of our cred operations the
final one is update so let's create a
new request we're going to call this a
update
post and I'm just going to grab the URL
from the delete post because it's going
to follow the same exact structure so
we're going to pass the ID of the uh
post that we want to
update now since we are updating it we
need our front end or in this case
Postman to actually send the data uh
that we want to update with so since we
are working with posts and we take a
look at our uh structure of our posts
it's very simple we just have title
content uh and then you know published
as well if you want to add that in
ratings as well and I'm actually going
to remove that so I don't actually want
to have that I'll actually we'll keep it
in for now but we'll definitely remove
that a little bit later
on and so if I go back to postman we can
go to our body and then provide all of
those fields so we'll go to raw and then
Json so this is just like when we were
trying to create a post we just pass
that data
in and so here we'll get the
title and we'll give it a new title so
updated title so this uh this uh this
update request is going just going to
update the title now we are going to use
uh the put method so with put method we
have to actually pass in uh the data for
all of the fields right we want to pass
in what the final post will look like
after we update it we don't just want to
pass in the fields that we want to
update so if I go to let's say um you
know post one right we have the title
and then we have the content so if I
wanted to update just the title right I
would make sure that I pass the content
as well so I'm just going to copy this
since we're not updating it I'm just
going to send back the same exact
content right and then this is going to
be a put
operation all and so this is what the
request is going to look like now let's
go to our code and let's actually create
our path operation for
that so here we're going to do app.
put it's going to go to post ID
and then we'll Define our function I'm
going to call this update
post we're going to get the ID and I'm
going to convert that to an INT um and
then one other thing right because we
are receiving data from the the front
end uh just like we did for creating a
post we want to make sure that it
adheres to a very strict structure so we
have to use so I want to use our schema
again so that the the front end can't
just send whatever it wants to now I can
create a new model called uh class you
know update
post and then we can pass in all the
fields that we expect however it's going
to be the same thing as the post because
we expect a title content uh and then um
any of the other fields uh depending on
what we want ultimately but it's going
to be a post so it doesn't make sense to
create a new schema we can just use the
pre-existing
schema and so here I'm just going to
pass in post and make this type of post
so that it's going to make sure that the
request comes in with the right
schema and then for now I'm just going
to hard code the return to be uh a
message and I'll just say updated post
and then here I'm going to do a print
let's just see what the post looks
like all right so we were able to
extract all of that data so
perfect uh and then what we're going to
do now is uh there's a couple things so
first things first I I need to find the
index uh that of the post with this
specific ID so just like we did with
delete I'm just going to copy this
actually we can copy all of this right
here because if that ID doesn't exist we
want to send a 404 so we can reuse all
of that
logic but if we did find an index that
means we do need to update it so what
I'm going to do is uh we're going to
grab postore
dict which equals post. dict so that's
going to take the data we receive from
our front end which is stored in post
and it's going to convert it to a
dictionary that's all it's
doing and then what I want to do is I
want to set postore dick of
ID to be equal to ID so we're going to
set the ID uh inside this new dictionary
to be that ID and then we're going to
say myor
poost and we're going to pass in the
index uh of the specific post we want to
update and set that equal to postore
dict and then lastly we're going to
return I'll say data and then we're
going to return our new post which is
going to be postore dict now let's just
quickly recap what's happening so first
of
all uh the user is going to send a put
request to the specific ID of the uh
post he wants to update and we're going
to just do a quick check so we're going
to see if we can find what is the index
of that specific post within my Mo my
posts
aray if it doesn't exist then we're just
going to throw a four four if it does
exist whoops if if it doesn't exist
we're going to throw a four4 if it does
exist well first thing we're going to
take all the data we received from the
front end which is stored in post we're
going to convert it to a regular python
dictionary and then we're going to add
the ID so that this final dictionary has
the ID built in and then we're going to
say for the Post within index we're
going to just replace it with our new
postore dict so that's how we update
that specific spot in the
array and so let's give this a shot so
if I do uh get all
posts right we can see we have post one
and then the title is title of post one
and then let's go to our update and we
can see that we're going to change the
title to be updated title and let's see
if that works okay so it looks like it
worked uh we got back the new post so
let's do a get all posts again and let's
see if it actually did update and we can
see that it did in fact
update now just to just to make sure
everything else is good let's also
change the uh the content so let's say
this is the new
content let's send an
update and then we're going to run this
again and we can see that the content is
updated so now we're able to
successfully update each and every post
and that's going to wrap up all of our
crud operations so you could see that
building out an API building out your
crud functionality is fairly
straightforward within fast API uh we've
got one more lesson where we're just
going to restructure our code a little
bit just to make things a little bit
cleaner and then we're going to start
getting to the fun stuff which is
working with databases so I'm going to
show you guys how we can actually uh get
a postgress database installed on our
machines and running and then we'll
actually start saving data into an
actual
database in this lesson we're going to
talk about one of my favorite features
of fast API and that is the built-in
support for documentation so normally
when you build an API you're going to
want to create documentation so that
users know how to use it and one of the
challenges with that is that it's not
exactly a simple process and anytime you
make changes to your API you have to
make sure that you update your
documentation and it's very easy to
forget to do that with fast API fast API
automatically generates the
documentation based off of the path
operations that you've defined so it
does it all for you and you don't have
to write a single piece of code to
actually get the documentation in place
and so to actually see the documentation
you just go to the normal URL but you
just do SL docs and so this is going to
show you the built-in documentation
powered by Swagger UI and so what's
really nice is and if you've ever looked
at the documentation for um some other
apis you may have noticed something that
looks similar to this and that usually
means that they used Swagger UI as well
so fast API has built-in Swagger UI
support and it automatically generates
all of the routes and the documentation
for all of your paths and so if you take
a look at all of our operations our path
operations we've got the one for getting
all posts we've got the one for creating
posts we've got the one for getting an
individual post we've got the one for
updating an individual post as well as
deleting a post and what's really cool
about this is if we do the hit the drop
down right it's going to show you how to
use this specific path uh or how to use
this specific API endpoint so if you
want to actually try it out you can do
that so you could say try it out and
then you can just hit
execute right and so now it actually ran
the query against our API server and it
shows us what the output is so these are
the two documents that we have uh or the
two posts that we've created and we can
do this with all of the uh uh API
endpoints so if we want to create a new
post uh it's going to give you example
of the data that we can pass in so we
can try try it out and then it's going
to give us all the fields that we have
to pass in and then we can just
customize this so if I want to say
creating new post with
documents and then I'll just for Content
I'll say this is really
cool we'll give it a random rating we
hit
execute right it actually runs that it's
going to show you how to um perform the
same actions using curl as well and then
it's going to show you the data that we
got back from our API server and we can
see that we got a 2011 Response
Code and so I want you guys to just kind
of play around with this um get familiar
with it so there's going to be times
where you may not even have to use a
tool like Postman you could just test
things out uh using swagger UI in the
built-in
documentation and what's even nicer
about this is that uh we have built-in
support for two different types of
documentation so this is using swagger
UI but if you use
redock sorry there shouldn't be an S at
the end it's just redock right you could
see a different format of the
documentation using a tool called redock
uh so it's going to fundamentally do the
same thing it's just a different
documentation tool so it's going to look
a little different uh feel free to use
whichever one you ultimately prefer but
uh by having it automatically get
generated by fast API you don't ever
have to worry about updating anything so
if you take a look at like create post
right we've defined the pieces of data
that we need and in the future if we
decide that the user needs to pass in
another field maybe like the date that
they wanted to get published it'll
automatically update this you don't have
to tell it you don't have to manually go
in and update it
yourself all right guys so we're going
to make one slight change to how we
structure a code and what I want to do
is instead of just having my main file
with uh within my base project directory
I want to actually create a folder
called app so that's going to store all
of our application specific code and
then put that Main in there so it's a
very small change but we do have to
change a couple of things to make sure
that it doesn't actually break anything
so I'm going to create a new
folder and I'm going to call this
app and so this in Python if you aren't
too familiar with how python Works uh
python has a concept of packages and a
package is nothing more than a fancy
name for a folder however for something
to properly act as a package python
requires you to create a dummy file and
this file is called uncore uncore
init.py
all right and so that's going to turn
this into a proper python package just
know that you have to add this file you
don't have to put anything in the file
but anytime you create a new folder just
make sure you create a file with this
exact name and that's going to ensure
that uh it is in fact a python package
so now that this is an actual python
package we can just drag this main file
into our app folder
right and then now we're going to get an
error and that's perfectly okay so we're
going to cancel out of
this and I want you to take a look at
the command that we run to start our
application so the command to start our
application was we do UV corn we do the
name of the main file which is just Main
and then in within main if you take a
look at what's the name of our uh fast
API instance it's called app however now
when we run this command line uh this
command it's going to look for a file
named Main however there's no file named
main within our base project directory
cuz it's now been moved into app so to
actually reference the main file that's
inside of a python package it's pretty
simple you just put the name of the
package beforehand so you do app and
then dot so it's going to tell UV Corin
to look inside the app directory for a
file named main so then we go in there
we see the main file and then within our
main file we look for the app instance
which is our fast API instance right
here so let's give this a shot let's see
if we broke anything it looks like
everything started up fine I'm just
going to do a couple of requests so this
is going to be just get an individual
post looks like everything's good I just
want to make sure that there's no errors
and yep everything looks good so I think
this is just a little bit better of a
way to structure our application we're
going to put all of our app code moving
forward inside of this app directory so
that we can keep everything else
separate I think at this point we have a
basic understanding of how to work with
fast API and how to set up basic routes
and work with path operations and until
now we've been storing all of our posts
in memory and I think we've made it to a
point where we are ready to now start
working with databases and so if you
don't know what a database is a database
is a collection of organized data that
can be easily accessed and managed uh
and so when it comes to any kind of
application related data so things like
users that have registered posts that
have been created all of these pieces of
information are going to be stored
within a database so it's going to be
stored on disk so that we can retrieve
this information at a later point in
time now when it comes to databases we
never actually interact with the
databases directly instead what we have
is a database management system that's
going to sit in the middle so when we
want to perform an operation on a
database we're going to send that
request to a database management system
that management system is then going to
actually perform that operation and then
it's going to send the result back to us
so we never talk to the databases
directly instead we have a piece of
software that sits in the middle and uh
acts as the brains behind the database
now there's two major branches of
databases there's relational and nosql
databases relational databases are
usually sql-based databases and we're
going to cover that in the next slide or
so but these are just some of the more
popular relational and nosql databases
that you guys have probably heard of in
this course we're going to uh work
exclusively with relational databases
and more specifically we're going to
work with postgress now if you
ultimately want to learn how to work
with mySQL or Oracle or SQL server or
any of the other databases keep in mind
that at the core uh they are
fundamentally no different than
postgress you know 90 I would say 97% of
the things that we cover when it comes
to postgress is going to be almost
identical in all of these other
databases because they all at the end of
the day use SQL however SQL there is a
little bit of slight uh nuances when it
comes to each database each of them will
implement it in a slightly different way
so you'll see that certain um SQL
commands aren't available in others but
for the most part all of the core things
that we cover from a SQL perspective is
going to be applicable to any the other
relational based
databases uh and so let's talk about SQL
now so SQL or structured query language
is a language that's used to communicate
with the database management system uh
and so you know when we want to perform
an operation we're going to send a
specific SQL statement to the database
management system it's going to then
take that statement and then perform the
operation on the database and then it's
going to send that result back to us so
SQL is the language that we use to
communicate with the database management
system
now in the next video what we're going
to do is we're going to install
postgress on both Windows and Mac
depending on what you're using and
there's an important thing to note when
it comes to installing postgress or
really any database when you install an
instance of postgress uh what we can
actually do is we can carve out multiple
separate databases right and this is
kind of confusing at first because
you're thinking well we installed
postris we have a database yes but what
we can do is we can actually create two
different databases that are completely
isolate isolated and have nothing to do
with one another and that way if I have
application one we can create a database
just for app one and then if I have a
second application that I create this
application can have a separate database
as well and there these two databases
are going to be completely separate and
completely isolated so that they don't
step on each other's toes so it's pretty
cool and it's a pretty awesome feature
to be able to kind of carve out your
postp instance to multiple
databases and keep in mind that you
don't necessarily always create uh a
separate database in database instance
for each application right there are
scenarios where you might actually
create an app that's going to make use
of more than uh one database instance
within
postgress however those are very
specific situations maybe if you want
some sort of multi- tendency or things
like that however we're just going to
create one individual database instance
for our application that's going to
handle everything that we need now when
we install postrest what's going to
happen is that uh the installation
process is going to create a database uh
within the postgress instance called
postgress little confusing right it's
postgress within postgress um but it's
actually going to create this database
named postgress and the reason we need
to do this is that if you ever want to
connect to a postgress instance uh what
you have to do is you have to specify a
database that you want to connect to so
some kind of default database that you
want to connect to you can't just
connect to postris you have to specify a
database and so that's why the
installation process creates one
database for you so that you can have
something to connect
to however we won't necessarily need
that instance once we create our own
however I usually just keep it in by
default because it's not going to hurt
anyone in this video we'll take a look
at how we can install postgress on a
Windows machine so let's go ahead and
just search for
postgress and it's almost always going
to be the first instance so just go to
postgress ql.com
you'll see all of the downloads options
so right now the latest version is 13.4
so I'm going to just download that one
you may see a newer version feel free to
download that nothing's going to really
change between each
version once that's downloaded start the
installer if you see this pop up just
select yes right with the installer open
select next uh you can leave the default
installation directory no one usually
messes with that now here you can select
the different components that you want
to install with your postr instance so
for the first thing that you have is the
postgress SQL Server that's obviously
what you want to download the next one
is PG admin so this is a guey that can
be used to manage your postgress
instance we're going to be using that to
actually manage postgress so you want to
make sure that you've got that
downloaded stack Builder this is a um an
extra feature that can be used to
install extensions and extra features
within postgress we're not going to be
installing any of those extension so
there's no need to have stack Builder
however it's not going to break anything
if you do leave it checked and then uh
we'll we you won't be using any command
line tools to manage postgress however
go ahead and just leave that check just
in case you know down the road you
actually do want to use
it all right and then once again leave
the default data directory uh then you
have to pass in the password for the
super user so U make sure you remember
this
password then you got to specify the
port that you want your database to be
listening on uh the default postgress
Port is going to be 5432 you can change
it if you want but you have to make sure
that you update uh everything else uh
when it comes to creating our code uh to
update that port number I'm going to
leave it as default as do most people
and then just hit next on this window
and then next here next and then it's
going to start the installation
process and once that's complete just
hit finish and then like I said we're
going to be using the PG admin guey
software to manage our postgress
instance so if you just search for PG
admin you'll see that it's right there
just select that and open it up and then
at that point in the next video we'll
we'll start taking a look at how we can
use that to not only uh create
individual database instances but also
create tables and things like
that in this video we'll take a look at
how we can install postgress on a Mac
machine so let's search for postgress in
Google and the first result should be
the one that we're looking for and
within the postgress website just select
the downloads button and this is going
to show you the different platforms that
support so we're going to install this
for
mac and then select download the
dollar and then here we can see all of
the versions that we can download we're
going to download whatever the latest
version is so in my case it's 13.4 if
you're watching this video in the future
it's probably going to be some other
version but it should all be relatively
the same so we'll just download under
Mac all right and once it's finished
downloading just go ahead and select the
DMG file that you downloaded and then
we'll set up the in installer and if you
get this popup just select
open and then specify your
password with the installer window open
select next uh leave the default
installation directory uh now within
here uh by default it's going to install
four different components I'm going to
walk you through what each of these
components does the first one is the
postgress uh server so this is the
actual postr database so we definitely
want to install that below that is PG
admin this is a goey that can be used to
manage your post databases we're
definitely going to install that because
that's what we're going to use in this
course to actually manage our
database stack Builder is an extra um
almost like an extra installer that's
used to uh install extra extensions that
give postris some extra functionality
we're not going to use any of those
extensions so go ahead and uncheck stack
Builder and the last one is command line
tools so we can manage postgress through
the goey as well as the command line uh
in this course we're going to stick
exclusively to the guey however I would
still recommend downloading the command
line tools just in case you ever do want
to use
them and then specify the default data
directory that's fine then you want to
give uh the password to your postgress
instance so this is kind of like the
root user
equivalent here we specify what port we
want our postgress instance run this is
the default postgress Port uh if you
want to change it you can do it uh but
just make sure that you know whenever we
get to actually coding out our uh API
and specifying what port we connect to
the postgress database make sure you
update those accordingly however I
recommend just keeping it as the default
and then everything else just keep
hitting next and then it'll start the
installation all right and once that's
complete just like finish it's going to
be uh at that point postest has been
successfully installed then what you
want to do is just hit the little search
icon I want you to search for PG
admin all right and so if you want to
open up pgp admin which we'll cover in
the either the next lecture or the
lecture after that just search for it
select it and that's going to open up
the gooey tool used to manage your
database before we get started with
configuring our postgress database there
are a few things that we need to cover
and one of those things is the concept
of tables and this is a very important
concept when it comes to working with
relational databases so a table
represents a subject or event in an
application uh and so what exactly does
that mean let's use a example let's say
we're building out a e-commerce
application right you're going to have a
table that represents each part of your
application so you're going to have a
table for all of the users that have
registered you're going to have a table
for all of the different products that
you plan to sell on your website and
then you can have a table for things
like purchases and reviews so each table
represents a different subject or event
in an application and what's amazing
about these tables is that all of these
tables are going to form some sort of
relationship that's why it's referred to
as a relational database and if you
think about it the tables that we have
listed right here they're all going to
have a very basic and obvious
relationship right purchases right when
a user purchases something that
automatically implies a relationship
because every purchase order has to be
associated with the user account that
actually filed that purchase order and a
purchase order is going to have a list
of products that the user wants to buy
so we can see right there all of the
tables that we have already form some
sort of relationship and it's really
important that when you design your
database that you figure out what are
these relationships beforehand so that
you can design a very efficient database
right just like if we're building a
social media application right we are
you we know we're going to have a table
for users we're going to have a table
for posts as well and we already know
that there's going to be a relationship
between the two because every post has
to be associated with a user because
users create posts so you can see that
you know all data has some sort of
relationship with one another now when
it comes to tables we have columns and
we have rows a column represents a
different attribute uh and so if we're
building out a table for users we would
create a column for for the name so this
column represents the name of the user
we might create a column for their age
their gender you might create another
column for the email that they Ed to
sign up you might have a column for uh
their billing or shipping address right
it's up to you to figure out what are
the different attributes we need to
model a specific user then we have rows
rows are very simple right each row
represents a different entry in the
table so if we have a user's table then
each row represents a unique user so Row
one this is the user uh Vanessa row two
is going to be the user Carl so each row
just represents a different entry within
the
table now databases have data types just
like any programming language and the
reason why this is important is that
when you create a column within a table
you need to specify what kind of data
type you want to use and that decision
is going to be ultimately based off of
what attribute this column represents uh
and so we have data types uh just like
any other programming language like
Python and so if we were building out a
table for you know social media posts
one of the things that we might have is
a column for what are the total number
of likes or retweets and so for
something like that you would want some
sort of data type that's numeric you
know a data type that models numbers and
in Python you know we have two main data
types we have integers and we have
floats integers being whole numbers
floats giving you decimals well
postgress has the same thing right it's
going to have integers it's going to
have decimals and a few others keep in
mind that uh you don't need to worry too
much about that just understand that
there are numeric data types within
postgis that are just like python so
when it comes to the number of likes of
post gifts you know maybe we would use
something like an integer because we're
not going to have a half a likee or
anything like that then if you're trying
to model uh you know someone's name or
email or address right we would use some
form of text and within python or any
programming language you have strings
that allow you to represent text within
postgress we have the same thing it's
just called something different we have
uh varar which is just short for varying
character which is once again just a
string fundamentally and then we have
text right they're both going to do the
same thing don't worry too much about
the differences just understand that
postest does allow you to work with text
just like any other programming language
it's just called something
different uh and then uh for booleans
postgress and python they both support
booleans they're going to work the same
way way it's either true or false very
simple uh and then within python we have
lists so anytime you want to model uh
you know multiple instances so a list of
something uh we have arrays within
postgis and you'll see that when you
work with relational databases you'll
see that arrays aren't used very uh very
much because a lot of times if you're
using an array it may be better to take
that column and just convert it into its
own table um but like like I said you
know don't worry too much about that
we'll go over that in some upcoming uh
upcoming
lectures when we create a table we have
to specify something called a primary
key and a primary key is a column or a
group of columns that uniquely
identifies each row in a table so what
exactly does that mean well we need to
tell postgress essentially how can we
uniquely identify each entry in our
table each row uh and so we have to give
it a special column that ensures that
every entry uh for that specific column
is unique and keep in mind that we can
only have one primary key per table you
can't have more than one however a
primary key can span multiple columns
however let's keep things simple for now
and just assume that primary keys are
really just one column and so a lot of
times when you create a table what we
have is a column for a unique identifier
so anytime you create a new user usually
you're going to have an ID associated
with that account and that ID is going
to be unique uh and so the ID associated
with John is going to be
77498 and that's how we uniquely
identify each user based off of that ID
and so it makes sense to select that as
the primary key because we already know
that each ID is going to be unique so it
fits the perfect definition of what a
primary key is right and so the only
requirement for something to be a
primary key is each entry must be unique
no duplicates we can't have the same ID
for another user and so you're probably
thinking at this point that hey we're
going to create an ID column for every
table and then make that the primary key
I'm going to tell you that that's not
quite
correct the primary key doesn't have to
be the ID column always in fact your
table doesn't even have to have an ID
column right it's up to you to decide if
you actually want to have that there are
certain instances where you may not want
an ID column and so if you don't want to
use the ID column or if you don't have
an ID column you need to ensure that you
have some column that's able to uniquely
identify each and every entry and so one
good example of that when sticking to
the users table example is that
generally in an application a user can
only sign up with an email once so we
know that an email is always going to be
associated uniquely with one account
right we can't have two users with the
same exact email that's not going to
work that's usually not allowed so we
could definitely use our email column as
a primary
key but there's plenty of other examples
right phone numbers right generally I
can't sign up with the same phone number
uh for two different accounts so we know
phone numbers are going to be unique uh
for the guys that are in the United
States you know what a social security
number is two people can't have the same
exact social security number uh and so
there's a lot of different things that
you can use to choose for the primary
key uh just keep in mind it's not always
the ID so that's the main thing I wanted
to focus on in this slide now as we go
through creating our table uh and
creating each of the individual columns
that represent a certain attribute for
that table uh we can add in extra
constraints for each column so we can
put in extra little conditions and and
so we already talked about the column
that's going to be the primary key and
we know that the primary key has to be
unique for each and every row but what
happens if we have another column that
isn't the primary key but we want to
ensure that each and every entry has a
unique value for that specific column
right so take a look at the name column
in this case let's say that we we won't
allow two users to share the same exact
name is there any way we can tell
postgress to perform that check for us
well we can add in what's called a
unique constraint so we can when we
create the table say that I want to make
this column unique by adding the unique
constraint and so that way anytime I add
in a new user it's going to check the
name and it's going to check to make
sure that there's no other users with
the same exact name and if there is it's
going to throw an error and we can do
this with any column uh you can do it
with all your columns if you wanted to
uh that's not necessarily something
you're going to do but I just want to
make sure you guys understand that you
know we can perform extra checks for
each entry um by adding in a constraint
the first constraint that we covered is
the unique constraint but there are
plenty more now the next constraint is
called the null constraint and when it
comes to creating columns uh by default
postris allows you to leave a column
blank essentially so I can add in a new
user and I can say that um I can leave
the name column blank so instead of
having Vanessa for the first one I could
just leave it blank and not put any data
in and so what postgress will do is
it'll put in a value of null because we
didn't provide it and I could do the
same thing for age I don't have to pass
in an age by default and I don't have to
pass in a gender by default as well and
it will put in a null value for each and
every one of those but let's say we want
to tell post to perform a check and say
hey I don't want you to be able to
create a user that doesn't have an age
so what we can do is we can put in a
constraint and this constraint is called
a not null that means we are not going
to allow it to be null right we are not
going to allow postris to use a null
value so if we try to add in a new user
called Carl and we don't give it an age
well postris sees that this column is
not allowed to be null and it's going to
throw an error because it's not null so
that's the second constraint and I think
these are the two main things that I
want to focus on and I think at this
point we have a good enough
understanding of the different things
that we can do with tables columns and
rows that we can go ahead and start
playing around with postgress and really
digging deep into how tables are created
and how they
work in this video we'll start taking a
look at PG admin which is the guey that
we use to manage our postgress instance
we'll take a look at how we can Define
our tables for postgress we'll take a
look at how we can create entries in our
database as well as how to modify and
delete them as well so go ahead and
search in your under your applications
for PG
admin and you'll see that once it pops
up for the first time it's going to ask
you to set the master password for PG
admin and it's important to understand
that this password is for the PG admin
GUI it has nothing to do with the
password that you created during the
postgress installation this is strictly
for PG admin itself and the reason it
ask for a password is that ultimately we
can store our passwords for connecting
to our different postgress instances
within Peg admin so that we don't have
to enter it every time we want to
connect to our database and so that's
why we have to create a master password
so that we could store all of the
individual passwords for all of our
postgress instances so I'm just going to
create a random password in this case
and keep in mind it does not have to
match the password that was created for
your postgress instance these two have
nothing to do with one
another now the first thing that we want
to do is specify the connection details
for connecting to our post instance and
what's nice about PG admin is that we
can it'll remember all of the servers
that we've ever connected to so that we
don't have to manually input this
information every time we log in now PG
admin has done a little bit of the work
for us automatically so if you see under
the server section this is where we
Define our individual postgress
instances just hit the little uh drop-
down arrow and you'll see that there was
a server called postgress ql 13 already
created for us so by default when you
install postgress we know that we're
going to have a local Post postgress
instance running on our local machine so
it's going to automatically set up the
connection details for that instance the
only thing you have to provide is the
password for connecting to that instance
and so now we want to pass in the
password for the postgress user for the
postgress instance and this password
isn't the password that we just created
a few seconds ago this password is the
password for postest itself so this is
the one we created during the
installation process so go ahead and put
that in
there and then you can choose to save
this password so that you don't have to
reenter it I'm just going to skip that
for
now and so now it's taken that password
and it's now connected to our local
postgress instance and so you'll see a
little bit of information uh
about uh things like you know what's the
sessions what are the transactions per
second so you'll see not a lot of nice
little pretty charts however I want to
make sure that you guys actually
understand how to define a new server
instance so what we're going to do is
we're actually going to create this from
scratch so I'm just going to select this
we're going to select remove
server and we're going to do this
straight from SC scratch so I'll do
create
server let's give this a name I'm going
to call this um my local postest
instance because that's what it is local
postgress then we have to specify the
connection details so here we give the
IP address uh that the postgress
instance uh runs on um because this is
running on our local machine we can just
say Local Host however if this was
running uh within AWS or some cloud
provider uh that cloud provider would
have would provide you a password sorry
an IP address or even a domain name to
connect to and that's what you would
specify here in this case but since
we're connecting to our local machine we
just say Local Host then here we give
the postrest
password uh right when we did the
installation for postgress we use the
default Port so that's why we could just
leave this as
5432 uh and then as I mentioned when we
connect to postest we always have to
give it a the name of a database to
connect to we always have to provide the
name of a database to connect to since
this is a fresh installation the only
database that's going to be there is
going to be uh database named postgress
so it's going to connect to that by
default uh then we have to give the
username and password uh and we haven't
created a user yet so there's always one
default user this is a super user and
the username for that user is always
postgress little confusing because the
database name is postgress the name of
the actual dbms is postgress and then
our username is also post so try not to
get all three of those things um uh
confused uh then we here we could save
in our password so this is where we put
in our post
password and then if you want to save
this for a future so that you don't have
to enter in every time you can go ahead
and do that at that point hit save and
then you can see that once again we
created this from scratch now within PG
admin there's going to be a lot of menus
a lot of things that you see and you may
be a little overwhelmed but I want you
to keep in mind that a majority of the
stuff we won't really even care about
right so when you focus on just the
things that we care about you'll see
that there aren't many things involved
when it comes to PG admin and so like I
said within a postest installation right
we're going to have uh individual
databases right so we can create a
separate database for for each of our
applications so under our server right
you'll see a section called databases so
this looks a little interesting let's
click this right and then if we drop
this down or expand this you'll see that
we have our one default postgress
instance that was created for us during
the installation process uh now we're
not going to touch this we're just going
to leave this there but let's create our
own postgress instance so right click on
databases it create and then database
and then here we just want to give the
database a name I'm going to call this
uh I usually just name it after my
application name so since this project
is called Fast API I'm just going to
call this my fast API
database and you'll see that there's a
couple of other windows uh we won't
touch any of these however go to the
last section right here where it says
SQL right and as I mentioned before SQL
is the language that we use to actually
talk to
postgress and you know since this guey
is here to manage postgress it's going
to make our life a little bit easier but
at the end of the day uh it's just
passing in SQL statements and so because
we created a database through the GUI um
it's kind of abstracting a lot of the
SQL away from us however what's nice
about PG admin is it's going to give you
the underlying SQL uh that's used to
actually create this database so we can
see that it's just a command that says
create database and then the name of the
database we gave it uh here it's just
specifying the owner the encoding and
the connection limit uh technically we
could remove all of these lines and just
take the the semicolon and just put it
right here uh and then we can just do
create database fast API and that's how
you do it through the command line um I
think it's just nice and helpful uh that
it provides this for us however
ultimately we won't need to do that
because we do have PG admin so we can do
it all through the goey and uh you know
if you guys are worried that we're not
going to cover SQL believe me we will
but I just want to make sure we start
off um by you know taking a look at the
guey learning it the easy way then we'll
learn how to do it the harder and proper
way um but once we got this set up go
ahead and hit
save and you'll see that we have our new
database right now there's an X but if
as soon as you click on it it's going to
turn yellow which means that we have now
successfully connected to this
database and then under this database
you're going to see a lot of different
options and like I said we're not going
to touch most of these instead the only
thing that we want to focus on is under
schemas so under schemas and then under
public and I'm going to move this over
for you guys uh you'll see that there's
one important section called tables so
this is where we actually create and
Define our tables so right click this
and actually if we do it if we hit the
drop down you can see there's no tables
but that's to be expected because this
is a brand new
database and let's go ahead and create
our first table so we'll do right click
create and then
table and then let's give this our table
a name so let's say we're sticking with
the whole e-commerce example so we're
going to create a table called products
so this table represents the different
products that we're going to
sell don't worry about any of these
other fields uh it says the owner's
postris because we're logged in as the
postrest user however uh you know if we
log in as a separate user that then
you'd see the owner get updated
accordingly if we go into the column
section this is where we Define our
column so this is where we're defining
what is referred to as the schema of the
database so to add a new column just hit
the plus
icon uh and so now the first thing that
we need to do is let's figure out what
attributes does a product need and uh
you know a product is going to need a
name so let's give it a
name uh and so we'll call this column
name because it represents the name of a
product all right then we have to give
it the data type as I mentioned there's
going to be different data types that
closely resemble or match the data types
of a programming language so a name is
going to be you know a certain amount of
text right so we need whatever data tape
represents text and so we've got a
couple right we do have text uh and then
we also have varing character or
character varying this is the one I'm
going to ultimately use so we're going
to select character varying and if you
actually want to see the difference
between these I recommend you go uh
online search search for
postgress data
types right and then just it's usually
chapter eight of the documentation you
can select this and then this is going
to give you a breakdown of the different
data types and it's going to break it
down based off of you know numeric types
we've got a date time booleans
enumeration enumerated we've got uh you
know if you want to represent IP
addresses we've got a data type for that
so there's a ton of different data types
I definitely take a quick read over all
of these however we're just going to
stick to the basics so uh if you don't
want to go through all of that then
we'll we'll stick to just the core
fundamentals for now anytime we're
working with text we're going to use
character
varying and then as I mentioned we've
got a couple of uh options so uh we've
got the not null uh and so right now
it's set to no which means that
technically we can uh leave this entry
blank so we can create a brand new
product with no name at all and postest
is going to put in a value of null if we
do that but if we think about our
application right would we really want
uh to be able to create a product
without a name doesn't really make sense
so I think we should set this to be yes
so that it actually throws an error if
we try to do that and you'll see a flag
for a primary key so we get to specify
which column is ultimately our primary
key I don't think the name of a product
should be a good primary key we need the
primary key to be a column that really
emphasizes what makes each entry unique
and I don't think the name actually does
that so we're going to leave that set to
no for now and we're going to add in a
new column all right and this time we'll
add in uh let's say the
price and so now we have to specify a
data type so for numeric data types we
have an integer which is going to be
whole numbers which probably isn't a
good data type for prices because we
need decimals um we do have
uh numeric uh and there's a couple of
other ones so if we go back to our
documentation hit um numeric types right
we've got numeric so this allows us to
specify also decimals as well versus
integers and then we also have floating
Point types as well either one of these
can be used they operate a little bit
differently but both of them will work
but since we since I want to keep things
simple and I don't want to confuse you
guys too much I'm just going to use an
integer to define a price and I know
technically there's no application they
would ever use an integer to represent
price but you know I want to keep this
simple and I actually want to show you
guys something unique uh so you see that
there's a couple of different types of
integers we have first of all a plain
old integer we've got a small in and
then we've got a big endt so what is the
difference between all of those well
it's the number of bits that we have so
a small int has the fewest number of
bits which means that the maximum number
we can go to is going to be a lot
smaller versus a traditional integer and
then if we need to go up to a really
high value we're going to use big int U
which is going to have the most number
of bits right and if you want a good
explanation just search for what is the
difference between big
int verse
int right and so we can see here the
difference between them is you can see
the minimum value and you can see the
maximum value and so I think that's what
minus 2 billion to two billion so we get
it in the negative and the positive
direction versus a big in which is N9
negative 9 to 9 billion so you got to
figure out what's the best fit for you
if you don't if you don't think you'll
even hit uh two billion then there's no
reason to go to a big in
so I'm just going to leave this as a
plain integer we could definitely get
away with the small integer but let's
not worry about that I don't think we're
ever going to have a product that's
going to be 2 billion but that's
fine all right and then once again um we
have the not null option so it doesn't
make sense to create a product that
doesn't have a price so let's make sure
that's not
nullable uh and then the length and the
Precision this is for um floating points
so you can say like how many decimals do
you want to support it for um for an
integer though it it shouldn't matter
and it looks like I didn't properly
select this we'll do
integer all right and then the last
thing that we need is um each product
should have a unique ID U right and like
I said a lot of our tables are going to
have an ID column so here we're going to
create a column called ID and so what
kind of data type should we use for this
well I think what makes sense is an
integer right and an ID is just going to
be some random number so we could use
int big int or small int uh and so let's
just say we'll use a
integer I'm going to search for
integer however I don't actually want to
leave it like this um I did mention in
one of the previous lectures that U most
databases support the ability to
automatically generate a ID for you so I
don't want to have to be a be the one
responsible for creating an ID and then
putting that information into postgress
I want to just provide the name and the
price and I want postgress to generate a
unique and random ID for that product so
how do we do that that well it's pretty
easy there's a uh there's a data type
called
serial uh and so a Serial is just a
regular integer however it automatically
creates
a random number and it's actually not a
random number what it does is it the
first product we create will get a value
of
one the second one will get a value of
two and it'll just increment by one for
each product we had so it's going to
ensure that every single product we
create gets a unique integer value for
the ID column and like I said you know
we do have uh you know small inss big
inss and regular integers this is the
same thing but it's just Auto
incrementing uh for those three kinds so
I'm just going to say it's going to be a
regular integer that increments by One
automatically and then this is going to
be what's going to be the primary key
right we know that the ID has to be
unique I think that makes sense to make
it the primary key and I think for now
this is a good enough starting point um
to learn about SQL and postgress in
general so let's save this
and we have then successfully created
our first table and so under tables
you'll now see our products table so
let's start playing with this products
table let's create entries let's delete
entries let's really start to have fun
with it uh so right click on
it and select view edit data and then
you can really select any one of these
if you select all rows what it's going
to do is it's going to fetch every
single entry that we have in the
database and show it to you we don't
have anything in the database so doesn't
really matter uh if you select first 100
rows it's going to grabb the first 100
rows in the database and if you select
last 100 rows it's going to grab the
last 100 now if this was a production
server or something like that we might
have millions of entries so you may not
want to do all rows and then just get
flooded with all of this data so you may
want to select one of these or filter
out the rows based off of some criteria
but we have no actual data on it so I'm
just going to select all
rows and you'll see that within um PG
admin we have these different tabs so it
opened up a new tab and you see that
there's like a little up window so if
you can pause it and Rewind it says that
it actually ran a query uh and so what
it did is it ran a query to retrieve all
the all the rows because that's what I
selected right I select I selected you
know get me all of the all of the rows
by selecting all
rows and if you look at this query
editor right here this is the actual
underlying SQL that it ran so it ran
select star from my products table order
by ID in an ascending fashion so it's
going to grab the first product with the
lowest ID number and the next product
with the second lowest ID number and
it's going to keep incrementing up we've
got nothing in our database so it didn't
return anything but I think it's cool
that it does show us the underlying SQL
now like I said we don't have anything
in our database at the moment so let's
go ahead and create our first entry uh
so I'm going to create select this
column and I'm just going to give it a
name so this is going to be a let's say
a
TV and let's give it a price I'll say
this is um
$200 and then the ID this is going to be
automatically generated so we don't need
to provide a value uh and so at this
point you may be thinking well looks
like we created an entry right we have
our TV price of 200 well not exactly to
actually store this data in the database
right now we're just proposing changes
we have to select this button right here
so if you hover over this this says save
data changes so when you select this
this is actually going to push this data
into the database so let's do that you
can see that the data was saved
successfully and now it's actually in
here uh in the database so let's create
a new entry I'll say this is a DVD
player I don't know if anyone uses these
anymore and then let's give this a price
I'll say this is uh
$80 and then we can we can just keep
adding as many as we want so let's add
in a uh
remote is going to be 10
bucks right and you'll see that uh
anything that's kind of bolded so you
notice how TV isn't as bolded as DVD and
remote so bolded means we haven't
actually pushed it out to the database
it's just proposed changes so we can
push out both of these at the same time
by pressing this again so we push that
and then you can see that they got
pushed out and take a look at the ID
column right the first item got an ID of
one the second one got an ID of two and
then three and it just keeps it's just
going to keep
incrementing now let's have a little fun
let's create a new item this time let's
create let's make it a microphone or
something and let's leave this price
column blank and let's see what happens
what so now if I press this take a look
at this Arrow
null value in column price so we left
this value empty so post Christ
interpreted as null but we set the
column to be not null so we we told
posters to do a check and say Hey listen
if we ever don't provide a value we want
you to throw an error so this is forcing
us to provide a value for this because
creating a
product uh without a price just doesn't
seem to make sense so let's give this a
price save that and so now that worked
and then this time let's try creating a
product with a
price um but no name this time right so
what do you expect to happen well since
we set the column to be not null it's
going to throw an error or it should
hopefully and look at that null value
and column name so once again it's not
going to be supported it's going to
throw an error so let's just give it a
name let's say this is a car the world's
cheapest car hit okay save that that's
been successfully
added all right so now that we've kind
of played around with it a little bit
let's make this a little bit more
interesting and let's add in a brand new
column to our products table so right
click on the products table right here
and select properties then under columns
we're going to add in a brand new column
so we're just going to follow the same
steps and this column is going to
represent If an item is on sale so I'm
going to call this isore bull sorry not
isore bull it's going to be isore sale
and it's going to be a simple Boolean as
the data type because the are going to
be set to True which means the items on
sale or false that the item is not on
sale so we'll do
Boolean uh and then everything else
we're just going to leave uh by default
so for not null we're going to leave
this to be no so we are going to allow
the user to input a value of null in
this case however what we're going to do
is we're going to add in uh an extra
constraint I guess uh actually we're not
we're going to set a default value so uh
if the user does not provide a value for
isore sale we're going to give it a
default value and say that by default if
a product doesn't receive a property for
a sale it's going to be set to false so
it's not going to be on
sale so let's hit
save all right and then um right now you
don't see a new column but that's
because you don't see the new is on sale
column but that's just because we need
to refresh this page so let's go under
object I think we could do it here I
think it should be a
refresh I didn't do anything so I think
we're just going to to do the same thing
as we did before uh there should be a
way to refresh this but it looks like if
I just press it here it doesn't do
anything so uh instead I'm just going to
do a view edit data all rows again it's
going to open up a brand new
tab and now we can see the isore sale
column here and what's awesome about
this is that because I provided a
default value it went to all of the
other items in my database that didn't
that were created before this column was
created and it provided a value of false
because I said listen if if the value is
null or if we didn't provide that data
go ahead and put in the default value of
false and so now if I create a brand new
item and I'll say this is for uh
pencil and the pencil is probably only
$2 now since this uh can be set to null
I'm going to just leave that blank and
now if I save this take a look at this
it gets the default value that we
provided so uh you'll see that for a lot
of your columns you're going to want to
provide default values if you expect it
to be frequently uh inputed without a
value and you wanted to receive a
default value and now once again I'm
going to actually create a brand new
column once more and then we'll go to
properties we'll go to
columns and then we'll add a
column and we'll call this column
inventory so this is how many of the
items that we have in stock uh and so
here I'm this is going to be an
integer and uh I think it makes sense
for in our application to have a a value
for our inventory we shouldn't leave it
now so I'm going to set it to yes and I
want you guys to see um what happens
when we hit save because the big issue
is right this column doesn't exist at
the moment and so all of these items
were created before there was an
inventory column that was created
however this column has a not null value
but it doesn't have a default value
right we gave is sale a default value so
post Chris was smart enough to go into
all of these pre-existing items and give
it a value of false well what's going to
happen with the inventory I didn't give
it a default value so let's see what
happens if I hit save it throws an error
it says column inventory of relation
products contains null value so it's
basically saying all of these products
that you had before don't have a value
for
inventory so at this point um you know
you have a couple of different options
uh you could delete your all of the the
previous products if you wanted to um
and since this is a development
environment that's not a big deal if
you're in a production environment that
could lead to issues obviously you don't
want to delete your uction data um so we
could just give it a default value like
we did before uh and so I can just go
back into con whoops not there we want
to select this little button go into
constraints and we'll say the default
value
is um let's say there's going to be zero
item so let's hit
save and once again I'm just going to
open this up I still don't know how to
refresh it I know there has to be a way
uh I can't find it so it's okay we could
just open up this again and then we can
just delete these I don't want too many
of
these and I don't know why it got
squished up like
that but because we provided a default
value uh it all it got all values of
zero and so now if I create a brand new
item and I'll call this this will be a
pencil
sharpener we'll give a price of
$4 is sale I'll set to be true
that's true uh and then if we don't
provide an
inventory right it's going to get that
default value of zero all right so I
think we've almost wrapped up our schema
for our products table however I want to
add one more thing and this is uh
something that's pretty common uh
anytime you create an entry within
almost any other table you usually want
some sort of time stamp right so what
when did we add this product when did
this user uh create his account when did
this user
uh create this post right so anything
that we add into our database or in our
application it is generally best
practice to store uh when that item was
created because you never know when you
need to know that information so let's
create another column and let's see how
we can work with timestamps so I'm going
to right click on products as usual go
to properties and then under columns
we're going to add in a new
column and we'll call this column
created
at uh and then here we have to select
something that represents time so what I
recommend you guys do is just go to the
documentation and then um look at date
time types so there's a couple of
different ones but we're going to do is
a time stamp with time zone so we got
time stamp without time zone and then
time stamp with time zone we've got just
the date and then we've got just the
time but I want the date time and the
time zone so that's the most
detailed so I'm just going to search for
timestamp and we want timestamp with
time zone
all right and we obviously want this
field always filled in um however I
don't want to have fast API API be
responsible for creating the time stamp
I want postgress to automatically create
the Tim stamp for when the entry was
created so I want to be able to just
create a product and then as soon as it
gets added to our database postris will
just fill it in with whatever that
current time is so how do we do that
well we can go into this right here so
let's configure this add a
constraint and then here all we have to
do is for the default value I want you
to just write now so what this is going
to do is uh the default value for any
product that gets added uh it's going to
run this specific command on the CLI so
this command just grabs what is the
current time pretty simple right now uh
I think it's pretty straightforward what
is what time is it now right uh and so
this will set the default value so if I
hit save at this point all right since
we had all of these other items that
were created previously before there's a
time stamp what it's going to do is it's
going to set the created time to
whatever time it is now um which
technically that's not accurate cuz
that's not when they were added but
these were created before we were smart
enough to actually have a time stamp so
uh if we refresh this so I'm just going
to do a view edit all rows
again right you can see that they've all
been given the same Tim stamp of
whatever that current time was and now
if we add in a new item and I'll add in
how about a
keyboard we'll give this a price of 28
is sale we can just leave that empty how
many in our inventory we'll give it uh
50 and then we'll leave this blank and
so let's see if that if it automatically
fills in what is the current time and it
should be later than this time obviously
so we'll hit save and so if we just
double check yep we can see that this is
uh about a minute later and so now we've
successfully added the created at
timestamp in this lesson we'll run our
first SQL command however before we do
that what I want you guys to do is
create a few more entries within your
database uh and so you could see that
off camera I added about you know six or
seven more entries and you want to make
sure that you provide enough um varying
data to your database so make sure you
know the price is all different make
sure that the isale bullion is you know
a good mix of true or false make sure
that the inventory numbers vary enough
and then try to create them at different
times as well if you can do that uh that
way when we actually go to make queries
we can see a variety of different output
and that won't happen if you only have
three to four entries
but once you do that we should be ready
to start our first query and what we
want to do is right click on your
database so my database is called Fast
API and then select query tool so that's
going to open up a brand new tab and
what we can do is we can run our query
from here so here we type out our query
and then we just hit the play button and
that's going to run our query so how do
we make a query within a SQL database so
first of all let's start off with the
most basic query I'm going to type it
out and then after we type it out and
run it I'm going to to explain to you
exactly what each part of the command
actually
does so here we'll do select star
from
products colon then once we've tighted
this out what we can do is just hit the
play button and let's see what happens
so this is going to run the query we got
the same output here saying that it
successfully ran and it says 13 rows
affected uh and so what we can see here
is it just printed out every single
entry within our uh products table now
we only have one table so it's
essentially just dumping out the entire
database but if we had more tables uh
you would see that this would only print
out whatever was in our products table
so this Command right here does one
simple thing and that is it's going to
give us every single row within the
products database so let's actually
break this down so first of all we start
this command with select so we're
basically saying Hey I want to select
these rows uh ignore this for now we're
going to come back to this and then what
we do is we run from and then products
uh and so you say what table you
ultimately want to run this command for
so you say from and then the table name
and then it's going to run that query
against that table if we had a table
called users and we wanted to get every
user we could do select star from users
no different right so it's just a matter
of providing your specific table name so
every query is going to be with regards
to some table and the thing about SQL is
every single command is going to end
with a semicolon so if I don't put the
semicolon it's not going to do anything
well in this case it actually ended up
working but that's just because we're
using PG admin if you did this in the
command line it wouldn't have worked so
remember semicolon at the end of every
command now let's talk about what this
uh star or asterisk actually does and so
you can see by default we get every row
and that's coming from this part of the
command um but what does this do well uh
if you see here we we get every single
column back from our table right and
that's because we use the star here
however uh in an actual database your
tables could have 50 columns maybe more
they could have a ton of columns and if
you're running a simple query to get you
know some specific information you may
not want to get all of that data back
you may not care about most of the
columns you may only want one or two
columns and so we can filter out what
columns we want returned back for each
row so the star means I want every
single column so we got every single
column that we defined for the table but
if I wanted to run a query against the
products table but I only wanted a list
of the different names of each product I
can specify just name and so what this
is going to do is this is going to grab
just the name column uh from my products
table so if I run this again you can see
we got the same exact data we got all 13
entries but it only returned just the
name
column and then we can add in as many
columns we want so if I wanted uh the ID
column as well and the
price I can hit run and so now we got
the ID and the price and what's really
nice is it's going to line up with the
order that that I write them here so if
I want the ID first and then the name
and then the price I could change this
to ID name price and so now it's going
to order it in that in that exact order
so we got ID name and price but if you
do a star it's just going to return
every single
column now before we dig any deeper into
SQL and how to structure SQL uh commands
I want to talk about capitalization uh
and so you'll notice that when I ran
this command uh the word select and the
word from is capitalized uh and I want
to make this very clear capitalization
doesn't matter so if I make this
lowercase and I make this lowercase as
well and then hit run you'll see that
everything works just fine as it did
when it was capitalize so capitalization
doesn't matter however with a any SQL
statement we have uh two types of words
we've got SQL specific keywords which is
part of the SQL syntax and then we have
our user provided information uh and so
let's quickly talk about what those two
things are so the user provided
information is keywords that I'm
inputting in so I'm asking sequel or my
postr database I want the information
from my products table so I'm passing in
this data and so that one you just you
have to make sure you just match this up
with whatever it's called within our
table but all of the SQL specific uh
words that I don't create that don't
match up with anything in our database
right those can be either capitalized or
lowercase it doesn't matter it's not
going to impact your SQL statement but
you will see that best practice is to
capitalize it so we'll do Capital select
and then capital from and the reason we
do that is that we can much easier tell
which parts of our SQL statement is user
provided information and what parts of
our SQL statement is just basic SQL
keywords so this just makes it a little
bit easier to read you may not notice
the benefit of it now but you'll see
that these SQL commands can get really
long they can span multiple lines and so
having those keywords capitalized it
makes it a little bit easier to
understand but keep in mind it doesn't
actually impact how the command how the
SQL statement actually runs so it
doesn't matter but if you want to follow
along with what I do I like to
capitalize
them now with SQL uh what we can do is
when we perform a query we can rename
any of these columns so if we find that
this name is a little inconvenient and
maybe uh you know renaming it makes it a
little bit easy on our backend code to
better interpret the data we can pick
any column we want and rename it so
let's say we're trying to fetch the ID
column I'm just going to run this we can
see we grabb the ID column and it's
named ID but let's say uh this confuses
our back end because we're retrieving uh
maybe data from another database that
also uh you know for users or something
and then we also have an ID field and we
don't want them to get mixed up I can
rename this column and we can rename it
by using the as keyword so I say ID as
and then specify the new name so I can
name this products ID but now if I run
this we can see that the column is Now
Products ID instead of just ID and I can
do this for any and as many columns as I
want so if I wanted to rename the is
sale uh column I can save it as on
sale and so there you go guys it's
really as simple as that um keep in mind
I kind of continued with my normal SQL
uh format uh of capitalizing the SQL
specific keywords just because it makes
it a little bit easier to
read all right so let's clean this up a
bit I'm just going to change this back
to St so that we can retrieve uh every
single column I'm just going to run that
just to make sure nothing's broken and
so till now we've been retrieving every
single entry in the table and that's
because we've provided no filter
criteria no filter conditions so let's
figure out how we can filter the
specific rows that we want based off a
certain criteria so let's say I want to
match all entries that have a specific
ID of something right and we know
there's only going to be one entry that
has a specific ID because the ID field
is a primary key so we know that two
different items can't have uh the same
exact ID but you'll see one of the more
common tasks when it comes to working
with databases is uh retrieving a a row
based off of a specific ID so you know a
lot of times our backend will be like
hey I want you to retrieve the product
with an ID of 10 so how do we do that
easy we add the keyword where then we
specify the column that we're interested
in uh that we want to match on so we're
going to use the ID column
and then we say ID equals and then we
pass in the value it's really is that
simple so if I want the ID of and so if
I want to get the product with an ID of
10 I just pass in
10 and remember to make sure you have
the semicolon at the end hit run and
look at that we've now got our product
um that has the ID of 10 and then keep
in mind just like we did before we can
filter Down based off of just the fields
we want so if we want just the ID and
the name we can do that and it should
work just fine we'll change this back
and run that and so we got that uh if we
want to grab the ID of
product with an ID of 3 run that and so
now we get the product with an ID of
three but what's nice about this is that
we can choose any column to match on so
uh let's say that uh I first dump
everything so I can just see what I've
got and let's say I want to match on uh
any product that has an inventory of
zero so that's basically saying like
which products do we not have inventory
of so that maybe we can place an order
well we can just say where and once
again I'm capitalizing the SQL keywords
and I can say where inventory equals
zero and so now we've got we've got a
list of products where we need to place
an orders really is as simple as that
now working with numbers you just place
the number so any column that uses
integers or Floats or anything like that
you could just say equals that however
if you want want to match based off of
name uh the name column it's going to be
a little bit different because the name
column uses you know varying characters
or text or you know what would be a
string in Python and so for those what
we have to do is first of all we'll use
the column
name equals but we have to wrap it in
quotes single quotes to be specific so
if I want to get the uh product with the
uh with the name of TV I have to put in
single quotes search for it and then now
we get that so keep that in mind because
if you remove the quotes I believe you
should get an error yep and you do get
an error so just make sure when it comes
to working with varying characters or
any kind of text you want to wrap it in
quotes now just like with most
programming languages we do have
operators and so till now we've just
been working with the equals operator so
if I need to get um you know any product
that has a price of you know 20 I would
just say where price equals 20 and I
don't look it looks like I don't
actually have any items with the price
of 20 so I'm just going to do 200
because I see that the TV is 200
if we run that it works just fine
however What If instead of doing this I
want to retrieve all of the items that
have a price uh of greater than 50 how
do I do that well it really is
fundamentally no different than how we
do it in Python so I could say where and
I'll say price is and then we have
greater than 50 so this is going to grab
any item that's basically 51 or
higher and it's non-inclusive so it
doesn't include 50 and so now look it
looks like it grabbed all of the items
that cost more than 50
bucks um but if I wanted to say greater
than or equal to 50 I can
say just greater than or equal to 50 if
I run this we can see once again it
works just fine but I don't have any
products that are priced at 50 so I'll
try this again with just 80 so we'll say
greater than
80 it should not return this one because
80 is not greater than 80 so we can see
the 80 is gone but then if I do greater
than or equal to we can see the 80 is
back and we get the same thing with the
less than and less than equal to so I
could say less
than
80 and I could say less than or equal to
80 as
well and then last operator that I want
to discuss is the not operator so if I
wanted to grab any product that does not
have a uh inventory of zero I can say
where
inventory and we have two different ways
of doing this I can say not equals so
this is kind of the similar syntax that
you see in some other programming
languages not python but um other
programming languages I could say not
equals and then zero this is going to
give me every product that we do have
adequate stock for and so now we see we
get no columns or sorry no rows with an
inventory of zero but we can also
use this syntax so the greater than
sorry the less than and then the greater
than we run that we should get the same
exact result all right so let's move
move on to uh performing multiple
operators so let's say I want to grab
any
item that we have inventory of so any
any item that has an inventory greater
than zero that also costs more than $10
how would we do that and I'm sure you
guys can probably take a guess at this
but we'll do
inventory greater than zero and then how
do we add that next statement where we
say greater than I forgot what I said
greater than 20 so we could just say
and simple as that we do and and then we
pass in the next criteria we'll say and
price is greater than
20 let's try that out and I realized I
forgot the wear keyword here so that's
why it's throwing an
error all right and so now we got every
single product that has a inventory
greater than zero and a price of greater
than
20 and just like with an and operator we
also have an or
operator uh and so if I want to see any
product that is either
greater than $100 or less than 20 I can
say where where price is greater than
or price is less than 20 and so now we
can use two criterias and as long as it
matches one one or both of the criterias
it's going to return that result all
right let's clean this up a bit and
let's say I want to retrieve uh products
with an ID of one two and three how
would I do that well I can do uh where
where ID equals 1 and then we'd have to
do an or statement and then we'd say ID
equals
2 or ID equals three if we run this it
should grab just those three items now
there's another way to perform this kind
of operation uh and instead of using all
of these ID equals 1 iD equals 2 and
then just combining them with or
statements we can use the in operator so
let me explain how the in operator
Works what we can do is we can say ID in
and then we can provide a list of values
so I can say one two and three and once
again I forgot the wear
keyword and so you if you run this you
can see that we got the three items and
you can see that that's way more
readable instead of having to type out
that entire command and let me show you
the previous command I shouldn't have
deleted it so I'm going to use this
scratch Pad just to show you guys and so
before we did where
ID equal
1 or ID equal 2 or ID equals 3 so which
one do you think is more readable so
both of them do the same exact thing
however one's a little bit easier to
read and it cuts down on the number of
keywords that you have to
type now we before we proceed any
further I'm just going to retrieve all
my databases sorry all my entries once
again and what I'm going to going to do
is I'm going to add a few
items and so all of these items are
going to be named uh very specifically
so I've got a TV items uh and so I'm
going to call I'm going to create one
called TV
blue and then let me give this a
price and then everything else I can
leave default and then I'm going to
create a TV
red and then a TV
yellow and then I'm going to save these
to our datab base and uh I forgot to
give it a price we'll just say all of
them cost actually let's give them
different prices so this one will be 200
yellow no one likes anything that's
yellow so I'll give it a value of
50 and we'll save to our database all
right so that's in our database now and
we know how to filter based off of items
uh and we can use the wear keyword and
we can do it for even columns that are
based off of characters like the name
column so let's say that I want to
retrieve everything uh all of my TVs so
this TV this TV this TV this TV how
would we do that well we can't exactly
use the wear statement because I can say
where name and then I mean we have
equals we have greater than we have less
than but none of those really do what we
want to do uh so how can we match just
on all of our
TVs well we can use our like operator so
we could say
where name
like and then what we can do is we can
pass in something very specific so um we
pass in the text that we want but then
we can start using things that are kind
of like regular Expressions uh like we
have in Python so I could say TV and
then percent sign and what this is
saying is that I want to grab every row
that has a name that starts with TV and
then the percent sign means any random
characters afterwards so this is just
saying I want any product that has a
name that's start with TV so if I run
this you can see that we were able to
grab all the TV so it's very similar to
regular expressions and if I remove this
and instead just uh you know add in the
letter A this is going to return all of
my products that start with the letter a
and I don't have anything but if I
change this I know I have one product
that starts with an R so if I try that
you can see that we get the remote and
we can also flip this so I can
say you know percent sign and then pass
in some letters at the end so if I want
to grab anything that ends in the letter
N I can run that looks like I've got
nothing that ends in the letter N maybe
e right and so now we get all of the
items that end in an e right and then we
also have the ability to do the opposite
so this matches anything that ends in an
e but if I want to get every line that
doesn't end in an E I can say not but
that's just going to give me the
opposite so that's going to give me
every row except for those two rows and
what we can also do is if I want to get
any line that has the letter en n
somewhere in the name I can do the
percent sign before and after and so we
just look for these two characters
anywhere in the name so if I run this
and it looks like I got an error and I'm
not sure what happened there but I
changed this I I just deleted and
retyped it and so now it no longer gives
me an error so I'm not really sure why
that happened um could be a bug of some
kind or maybe there's a typo I didn't
see but this is going to grab any text
uh that has the letters e n and then it
can have any characters before any
characters after and then since we have
the not operator then it's going to um
do the exact opposite but then I can
also remove this so I can grab any lines
that match just
this and then it looks like once again I
get the same exact
error okay there we
go now when we make a query to our
postcrush database we can also specify
how we want to order the results now by
default it looks like it's just going
based off of uh the ID but it's not
necessarily going to be like that and so
it's better to actually tell postris how
you want to order the products so in
this case I've got no filter criteria
I'm just returning everything and let's
say I want to filter or order the um the
products that are returned based off of
price so if I say
order buy I can then specify the price
column so let's see what happens when I
run this right we can see that it looks
like it starts at the lowest price and
then Works its way up so by default when
you specify the order by um keyword and
then specify the column it does it in an
ascending order uh and so you could
specify the order at which you want to
go uh the direction I guess by saying
ASC so this means ascending so this
shouldn't change anything because
postgress by default is going to always
do it um in an ascending order so if I
run this nothing changes however if I
want to do this in a descending order I
can say DC for descending so now it's
going to start at the most expensive
price and then work its way down now
let's change this and let's say we want
to order by inventory and I want to see
which products we have the most of so
I'll say inventory and then descending
because we want to start at the highest
value and work our way down so I'll run
this and then we can see it starts at
the highest one and then Works its way
down but we've got a whole bunch of
zeros uh and let's say that between
these guys I also want to uh specify a
tie breaker of some kind we can also uh
specify the order uh using a second
column for these tie Breakers so I can
pass in another column and so let's say
that anytime there's a tie I wanted to
then order by uh let's say price so I'll
say
price and then we'll say uh the cheapest
price uh so ascending now ascending is
always the default so we can just delete
that keyword and so let's run this now
and I forgot to put a comma so after
each uh column that you want to sort by
you have to do a Comm and so now we got
all of our data and so let's take a look
and see if this actually worked so we
can see we're sorting based off of
inventory then we get down to zero
so these are all tied so we take a look
at the second column that we pass in
this case we're looking at the cheapest
price and so if we see the first one
looks like the cheapest price is two
then it goes up to 4 10 30 40 50 80 100
200 and you can pass in as many columns
as you want uh for your uh sorting
criteria you don't have to just stick
with two and it's really just a matter
of doing a comma and then passing in the
next column and then whatever the
criteria is and you'll see that one of
the common things to do is let's say we
want to get um the most recent products
well I think it makes sense to just sort
based off create so that's a time stamp
for when the product was created so
let's see what was the most recent
products that were put into our database
we can just say created _ at and what
order do you think we need do we need
ascending or descending if you don't
know think about it and if you still
don't know test it out that's the
easiest way to find out so we can see
that the first one is remember this is
always going to default to ascending so
when it's ascending we can see that
there's a one at 820 it created 820 and
then the bottom ones are created at 821
so it looks like this starts off with
the oldest one and then Works its way up
to the most recent one because that has
a later date you can think of the later
date as a higher value so if we want the
you know the most recent products first
we would do
descending and so now we've got the most
recent products
and with this order uh with the Sorting
property remember we can just chain this
on to any SQL statement so if I also
wanted to uh you know uh get all of the
products that have uh a price of greater
than 20 and then sort it by something I
can just specify my wear keyword and say
wear price is greater than 20 and then
for all of those results I want to order
by uh who was most recently created
we'll search that and so there you go
and so that's the great part about SQL
is you'll just keep chaining these
different SQL keywords to uh filter out
the exact data in the exact order that
you want now in an actual production
environment our tables could have
millions tens of millions hundreds of
millions of rows and so it would never
make sense to just perform a query like
this where we just dump everything
because then all of a sudden we're
asking our database to send back 100
million rows and that's just
unacceptable and our software that we're
using to even send the query may not
even be able to handle that and so
usually you want to provide a limit of
some kind so you may want to say hey I
want to grab uh you know the first 10
rows that match this criteria well we
can do that by using the limit keyword
so we say limit and then pass in the
number of rows that you want so if I run
that you can see that we get 10 rows if
I lower this to five we can get this uh
we can get five rows and you can chain
this on to any SQL expression so let's
say I wanted to grab all of the products
that have a price of greater than
10 if I search that you can see I get 10
results and let's say I want to limit
this to only the first two results so if
I hit that you can see that now I get
two results so uh all the keywords that
we're covering including the order bu
and any of the filter Expressions we can
just keep chaining on to our SQL
statement to further specify exactly the
data that we
want now with limit there's another
keyword that I want to cover uh and so
let's say that I want to grab all
products and I want to order
by
ID all right so this going to return it
like it normally does and it's ordered
by
ID and let's say I want to set the limit
to be five so now we get um products
with an ID of 1 two 3 five and
seven do I not have a ID of six I'm just
curious actually so let me cut this out
for a second I just want to see if
there's an ID of six there isn't okay so
that's that's expected so let me add
that back so we'll
say so I'll do order
by ID and then we'll limit to
five so we have the first five now let's
say that we want to skip a certain
number of rows because every time we
search this we're going to get the same
result and let's say that we don't
actually care about the first two
results and I want to skip past them we
can provide an offset so I'll do offset
two and so what that's going to do is
it's going to skip past these two first
two results and then give us the next
five so we should see the first result
be remote then microphone then car and
then the two after that come after that
so if I search this we can see that that
first one is a remote and the last one
is the pencil sharpener and then if I do
an offset of um you know five it's going
to skip the first original five and so
then we get pencil pencil sharpener and
keyboard so you're going to see that you
know when it comes to limit and offset
these are going to come in handy when we
start implementing pagination in our API
we're going to definitely make use of
the limit and offset keywords till now
we've been using PG admin to create new
entries in our database by just going
into the little gooey here and then just
adding new values however when you're
actually working with the post Christ
database you're never actually going to
do this this is more for administrative
purposes but a real application is going
to use SQL just like we use SQL for
making queries we're going to use SQL
for adding new entries so let's take a
look at what the command looks like for
adding a brand new entry into our
database the command starts with an
insert because we're going to insert a
brand new row and then we say into and
then we're going to specify the table
that we want to add a new entry to now
in our database we only have one table
so it's going to be products but here
you would provide whatever table you'd
like to add a new entry into right then
we have to do uh what we have to do is
provide a list of columns that we want
to provide data for uh and so I'm going
to leave this blank for now we're going
to come back to that and then we specify
values
and then here we're going to actually
provide the values for each column and
so if we take a look at our products
database uh we know that the name is
required we know the price is required
uh and then that's about it all right we
can choose to provide an sale but it's
going to default the false and then we
can choose to provide an inventory if we
want to if we don't though it's going to
default to zero so we have to provide a
name and a price and it's ultimately up
to us to decide what we want to pass in
so we know we need a
name and we know we need a price now
let's say we're going to let postgress
automatically give us the default is
sale value to be false so we're going to
leave that out because we're not going
to pass in any data so this column is
just for all the columns we want to pass
in data but let's say we want to give it
a custom inventory value instead of just
defaulting to zero here we would put
inventory and then in the values column
these are going to be the values that
you want to actually provide for the
name the price and the
inventory so let's go ahead and provide
that so let's create a brand new item so
let's give it a name uh and the order in
which you pass things has to match up
with the order that we pass in here so
the First Column that we're going to
provide a value for is name because it's
the first one here so what name should
we give it and keep in mind since it's
text uh or varying character we're going
to have to put this in
quotations and let's add in a
tortilla so now we're a grocery
store right then the next one is going
to be the price so how much is our
tortilla going to cost uh we'll say it's
$4 and then finally we have to provide
an inventory value so let's say we're
going to have a th000 tortillas
and then as usual you want
a
semicolon all right and so at this point
this is all we have to do to create a
brand new entry so let's hit run and
let's see what happens so query returned
successfully uh and so we see this
insert
01 and so at this point it says insert
01 and then query return successfully so
did we actually successfully insert that
something into our database and more
importantly what exactly does this mean
so if you see insert 01 that means
everything worked perfectly there was no
errors what this means is that first of
all ignore the zero so this means uh
that we're using the default postrest
configuration so this represents the oid
but I believe postrest by default
doesn't use that unless you specify it
to so it's going to give a value of zero
and don't worry too much about that
that's kind of outside of the scope of
this course we're not going to mess with
that but instead what we want to focus
on is that second column so this means
that we inserted one row so that means
our insert worked perfectly so let's
take this and what we're going to do is
first of all I'm going to copy
this cut it out actually P paste it into
my scratch pad for now and then we're
going to say select star from
rows sorry select star from
products and we're going to run that and
so if we go to our bottom we should see
our brand new tortilla and so we
provided the tortilla value we provided
the price and we did not provide an
isale so it defaulted false and then we
provided an inventory
now if I copy this again and paste it
back into here right and if I move the
name
column right after the price well now
SQL is expecting me to provide the value
for Price first then name then inventory
so then I would have to take the price
move that over to the First Column and
then move that move that into the first
entry and then we have the name and then
the inventory and so keep in mind the
order here has to match the order
here so once again I'm going to go ahead
and just add this again because why not
uh and so now oops it looks like we have
an error what happened here all right
there we go I guess we just needed that
space and so now it's in there and
you'll notice that once again we get the
zero one so that means everything was
inserted properly so now we should have
two items in our database with the name
of tortillas and when you're working
with with post Chris uh and especially
with an API where we want to create a
new post like in our application the
general convention in an API is once we
create the new post we want to return
that data back to whoever sent that
request to the API so we want to get
that brand new brand newly created post
with the new Fields like the created ad
field and all the default values and
send it back to the client or the front
end so how do we get postest to
automatically return it because right
now it doesn't seem to do that and we
could you know just provide two
statements right I can add in a second
statement that says select star you know
from
products uh this is going to dump
everything we could potentially you know
filter on you know where
name equals you know tortilla or
something like that and then at that
point we should have three entries but
uh that's one way of getting back the
result however there's a much easier way
within postgress so first of all I'm
going to change the name I'm going to
add a new item and say this is a car and
I'm going to give it a price of10
,000 and what we can do is we can pass
in a keyword called returning so this is
going to return the newly created item
or items if you want to insert more than
one item and then here we have to
specify the columns that we want for the
newly returned items so if I do star
that's going to return every single
column if I do ID this is just going to
give me the ID of the brandly brand new
created uh item I'm going to return
every single column so if I try this now
look at that so it creates the new entry
we you can see that has an ID of 26 and
it gives back the entire row now if you
want to insert more than one row at a
time what we can do is we just do a
comma here after values and then just
provide the data for the next row so
we'll do um we'll create a new item that
had cost
$50 and this is going to be a
laptop and then we'll say there's going
to be an inventory of 25 of them and
then if we wanted to add another one
then we could just do another
comma and then add some more values in
so we'll give this a price of
60 this is going to be a
monitor and then we'll say we have four
of
those and so here we can then go ahead
and run you can see that it added three
items and then it returned all three
because we have the returning keyword
and if you wanted to we could just say I
want the ID we can just say I want the
ID
and the created at
field maybe the name as
well I run this we can see it created
another three new items and then
returned just those three
fields and so that's pretty much all I
wanted to cover when it comes to
creating new entries in the database and
inserting new rows into a table all
right so in the last lesson we learned
how to insert new entries into a
database let's now figure out how to
delete entries so let's clear out this
query real quick and the command to
delete a entry from a database is going
to be delete who would have thought
right delete then you say from and then
you provide the table that you want to
delete a row from so we'll say products
and then we want to specify condition so
what is our match criteria what rows do
we actually want to delete so we have to
tell SQL I I want you to delete this
specific row so what do we usually match
on well if you take a look at our API uh
or specifically our delete endpoint uh
the user provides the ID of the product
they they like to delete or I guess in
our application it would be uh the ID of
the post we' like to delete but we're
working with products so we'll say you
know just like with a regular select
query you say where and we can say ID
equals and then the ID of the product we
want to delete so let's take a look at
one of these products I'll grab a
product
10 and then let's run this and then
afterwards let's actually do a select
star from products so we can see all of
the products afterwards just to verify
that the ID of 10 or the product with an
ID of 10 got deleted so you can pass in
as many uh um SQL commands as you want
here so we'll run that and so it ran and
then we can see that we um the product
with an ID of 10 was deleted now I'm
going to change this to 11 because
there's no longer a product with an ID
of 10 so I'm going to delete this
product um but what we can do is we can
tell postr to actually give us back the
specific entry before was deleting so we
can see what that looked like so we can
just pass in the returning keyword just
like we used uh with the insert
statement and then we specify the
columns we want so I'm going to say all
of the columns and then if we run this
we can see that it deleted uh the
product with an ID of 11 and we can see
what that product looked
like and keep in mind if I don't pass
any of this data and I just run this
right you'll see that it says a delete
of one so this is just telling you how
many total rows are deleted now let's
say that we want to delete multiple
products based off of a criteria so
let's say
uh we want to delete any product that
has an inventory of zero how do you do
that same exact command we just have to
match on any product with an inventory
of zero so let's say
delete from products table where and
then we'll just say
inventory equals z so they should delete
every single product with an inventory
of zero we run
this we can see it deleted eight rows
let's just do a selection
star from
products and you can see we no longer
have any products with an inventory of
zero all right so we saw how we can
insert new data into our table and we
saw how we can delete entries from our
table I think the next logical step is
to figure out how to update a
pre-existing row so the command for
updating is going to be as you guessed
update and then we have to specify the
table that we would like to update uh
and so in this case it's going to be the
products table and there's going to be
two things that we have to pass in so
first of all we need to specify which
entry we want to update we can update
more than one entry at a time but you
know just like when it comes to deleting
if you take a look at our API that we've
built so far the user provides the ID of
the specific post they want to update so
normally we're going to update based off
of the ID column so we'll say where you
know just like uh the select statement
or the delete statement we can say where
ID equals and then the specific product
of the ID and the specific ID of the
product that we want to delete so let's
say we want to delete one of the
tortillas so an ID of 25 sorry not
delete but update so we'll say
25 then we want to pass in all the
columns that we want to update so we
pass in the name of the column and then
what the new field should be so let's
say the name column I want to rename
this to
be uh flower
tortilla and then let's say I also want
to update the so I could say the
price equals and then 40 so right now
the price is four and the name is
tortilla it's going to now be flower
tortilla and 40 if I run
this and don't forget the semicolon at
the
end and I realized I forgot one keyword
so before you pass in all of the new
values we have to use the keyword set so
it's update products then we want to set
these columns then I run this and we can
see that we updated one field and I'm
going to copy this put it in my scratch
pad for now and just do a select star
from
products and so if we take a look at our
tortilla so now it's called flower
tortilla you can see the ID is still the
same because we didn't change that and
the price got changed however all the
other fields have all remained the same
so that's good um but just like when it
comes to inserting new data uh we gener
generally want to return the newly
updated product to the user so how do we
do that we can just use the returning
keyword I'm going to copy this
again and let's update a different
product so I'm going to update the car
which is a ID of
30 and let's just say I want to update
one field I I'll remove all these and
I'll just say I'm going to update the
isore sale
field to be to set it to true cuz right
now it's set to
false we'll set that to true
and then we can say
returning
star if we update this we can see that
we now got the car we can see that the
is sale set to true and it returned that
data and it was successfully able to
update
that now let's say we want to update
multiple
rows and let's say I want to update uh
we'll just let's just update everything
right so if I don't pass in a specific
condition I can update every column or I
can specify condition uh and then update
just those columns so let's let's say um
I want to match any any product with an
ID
of uh 15 or greater so an ID of greater
than
15 and I want to set the is sale to be
true so if I run
this we can see all of the entries that
it was that it updated so now all of
these entries which all have an ID of
greater than 15 have all all have the is
sale column set to true and so that's
how we update entries within a postgress
database at this point I think we have a
good enough Foundation when it comes to
working with postgress we're able to
successfully query a database insert new
rows delete rows and update rows so I
think it's time we finally started uh to
go back to our code and figure out how
we can actually work with a database
within a python or a fast API
application but before we do that I want
to do a little bit of cleanup so uh with
our database we no longer need our
products table so what you can do is you
can go ahead and delete it so you can
just right click and then hit uh Delete
or drop uh technically if you don't want
to delete this and you want to keep it
uh for now just for reference you don't
have to delete your table it's not going
to impact anything else so you can keep
it but I'm going to go ahead and delete
it because we don't actually need it
anymore so we'll just do that hit yes
and then it's going to delete that and
we should no longer have tables and I'm
also going to move over to another
machine so uh when we go to the other
machine you will see a whole bunch of
other databases but those are all
databases from my other project make
sure you just focus on the fast API
database all right I'm back over to my
new machine you'll see that if I uh take
a look at my database there's going to
be a whole bunch of other databases but
I've got my main fast API database so
that's what we're going to be working on
don't look at any of these other ones
and within here it's going to be pretty
much empty I've got no tables and so
we're going to go ahead and create our
table for our uh social media
application so uh you know we've been
working with posts so I think it makes
sense to create a table for posts and
before we do that we have to figure out
exactly what are the columns for our
specific table and to do that I think
it's best to actually take a look at
what our application looks like at the
moment and so if we actually take a look
at a structure of a post we know that
it's going to have a title we know it's
going to have a Content we're we know it
should have a um attribute called
publish to determine if it's published
or not we're going to get rid of this
rating that was just for demonstration
purposes so I'm going to remove that for
now so it should have a title content
published and like any other item uh
when it comes to a database uh we're
going to have ID column as well so that
we we can uniquely identify each entry
and then we're also going to have a
created ad field to see uh to track when
the specific post was added to the
database so we've got essentially five
columns and then once we have that we
can go ahead and just do what we did
before we can go to tables we can hit
create table and then we're going to
call this table post because it
represents our social media post and
then we'll go to the column section and
start defining our columns the first
one's going to be our ID column and so
with our ID we want to do series
so this is going to cause it to be an
integer that automatically increments
for us and then that's going to be our
primary key as it was
before we'll add in another column for
title this is going to be a varying
character or character varying not null
is going to be said to true we can't we
don't want to be able to create a post
without a
title uh then we're going to have a
column called
content I believe that's what we called
it here content yep
uh once again this is going to be uh
character
varying and once again this is going to
be not null uh then we're going to have
a published
column and this is going to be a
Boolean uh this is also going to be not
null however I'm going to provide a
default value so if I do leave it blank
it's going to default to true
and then finally we're going to create
the created at column and this is going
to be a time stamp with time zone this
is also going to be not null and then
just like we did before with our
products we're going to add a constraint
so that it's going to be uh now so it's
going to grab the current time whenever
we add this entry and it's going to
automatically add it to that
column and so at this point we've got
our tables defined we can go ahead and
hit
save if we right click on post and then
go to view and edit data we should have
essentially what is an empty database
and for now uh we know how to insert
data we can do it either through SQL or
we can just do it to here I'm just going
to do it through here just because it's
a little bit quicker for now so I'm just
going to say this is my first
post and the content is uh we'll say
some interesting stuff so just go ahead
and just create a couple of
posts and then I'm going to add my
second post
all right and then we can just hit save
and so now we have two posts in our
database so we can start working with
that when it comes to working with a
postgress database within a python
application we're going to need a
postgress driver uh and so there's going
to be a couple of different libraries
that going to do that that can do that
we're going to use this Library uh right
here uh and I believe in a couple months
a version three is coming up but right
now this is the latest version so head
on over to the documentation and it's
going to show you how to just quickly
set this up and so if we go to basic mod
module usage this shows us how to uh set
up a connection to our database and so
we're going to import the
library uh and then we're going to set
up a connection and hopefully this is
big enough for you guys so you just say
connection and then here we pass in all
of the data um for our postgress
instance so you know what's the IP
address of the postgress database what's
the postgress database that we want to
connect to what's the port number things
like that and then we set up a cursor so
this cursor is what we use to actually
execute SQL commands and so you can just
do cursor execute and then here we just
say you know create table well you guys
aren't familiar with that command yet um
but you can do you know insert into you
can do select star from test uh and then
at that point we can then do fetch one
fetch all and then if you ever want to
make changes to a database you just do
commit so it's a it's fairly
straightforward so uh let's go to our
code and set this
up and so the first thing that we want
to do is we want to install that Library
so we'll do pip
install and I'll just copy that name
all right and now it's successfully
installed so let's set up our
connection and so a connection to a
database can fail right maybe the
database is unreachable maybe the
database is down uh there's a lot of
things that could cause issues with us
being able to connect to we could put in
wrong passwords or something like that
so anytime you have some kind of code
within python that could potentially
fail we're going to use the try
statement so I'm going to say try and
then we're going to say connection
equals and then I realized first thing
that we have to do is we actually have
to import the library so let's just copy
this line right
here and then I'm going to say Psy cop
G2 I don't know if there's a specific
way to actually pronounce that that's
why I'm not trying to pronounce it and
then we call the connect method and so
here we have to pass in a few properties
so the first property is going to be the
host uh so that's basically the IP
address uh we also have to pass in the
the specific database we want to connect
to we also need to pass in the username
that we want to connect as as well as
the
password and for now we'll just keep
that as such so let's fill in these
fields so what's the host so since this
host is just our local machine uh for
the IP address you can just say Local
Host that means our own IP address I
spelled I misspelled
database and I'm going to set this to be
post postris cuz that's what's sorry
it's not going to be postris it's going
to be fast API all right so that
database is just going to match up with
the name of our database right
here username we've been using the
default postris username and then
password I'm guessing you guys could
have guessed what my password is it is
password
123 all right and then finally there's
one extra thing that we have to pass in
uh and so this library is a little bit
weird so when you actually make a query
to retrieve a bunch of rows from the
database it doesn't include the column
names it just gives you the values of
the columns which uh you know it's like
I don't know what you know what value
maps to what column so you actually have
to pass in an extra field to get the
column names which kind of seems dumb
but that's way the that's the way the
library works and so what we're going to
do up here is we're going to import
something else we're going to do
import same
Library
extras import and then
real redict cursor
and this should be
from and then the last property we're
going to pass in here the last argument
is going to
be cursor Factory equals real dick
cursor so like I said all this does is
it's also going to give you the column
name um uh it's going to give you the
column name as well as the value so you
know which value map to what column or
then it's just trying to figure the
order and then mapping it to comms gets
a little complicated so this will just
make it a nice python dictionary when it
returns
it all right and just like it had in the
um the documentation we'll say cursor
equals con. cursor so it's just calling
the cursor method and then saving it in
a variable named cursor and so all this
is going to do is this is what we're
going to use to actually execute uh SQL
state
statements and if it's successfully able
to connect we're going to say print and
then we're just going to print out
something like a database connection was
successful however if we weren't able to
connect to it and we get an exception
we'll say accept exception as
error so we're going to get the error uh
it's stored in a variable called error
and then we can just say
print connecting to database
failed and then after that just for our
knowledge we can say the error
was there we'll just print out the
error so let's save this
okay and you can see that we were
successfully able to connect to our
database so it looks like everything
worked well um but just as a quick test
I'm going to change uh my password here
I'm going to put it as an incorrect
value so let's save this and let's see
what
happens right we can see that uh the
password failed and so at this point
what the code does is it failed it
printed out the error and then it just
keeps going through the rest of our code
so then it starts up our fast API server
but at this point you know our
application's not going to work because
the postgress database connection failed
so really our application our API our
web server can't do anything until we
get a connection to our database so just
having it fail and then kind of
gracefully handling that error doesn't
do anything we need to wait for that
connection to actually go through before
we do anything else or then at that
point there's really no point in having
our server up and running if we can't
access our database so what I like to do
is we're going to set up a while loop
and I'm just going to say while and I
want this Loop to just continuously run
until we successfully get a connection
so we'll say while true which means
we're just going to keep doing this over
and over and over again until we break
out of
it and I'm going to tab everything over
and put everything in that while
loop all right and so while this true uh
if we successfully are able to connect
to the the database I'm just going to
break out of the while
loop
however uh if we fail then it's just
going to go right back into that
Loop and so now um one other thing is
it's going to do this really quickly and
I would like for after an error I would
like it to kind of wait two to 3 seconds
before it tries to reconnect so what we
can do is we can import the time module
so I'll say import time
and here I'll just say time.
sleep and I'll sleep for two seconds use
whatever time you want and so now if I
hit save check out what happens so it
failed to connect because of wrong
password and then it's just going to
keep retrying every two seconds now for
a failed password it's never going to
connect however if it's an issue with
your internet if it's an issue with the
database hasn't having not fully
initialized then having it just kind of
redo this until the database fully comes
up is a nice way of kind of handling so
if I change this now back to the correct
password we see that we're now
successfully able to connect so this is
our code for actually connecting to our
database uh and at this point we can
start working on actually um writing our
SQL code and then you know being able to
manipulate our database from our fast
API and I do want to point out one thing
uh generally when you're working with
your code what we did right here is very
bad we hardcoded all of our database
information right into our code this
creates a problem because first of all
when we check this into get now our
database password is stored in there and
then we run into some extra issues
because this is the connection for our
development environment or our
development postgress server our
production postest server is not going
to be running on a local host maybe um
the database might be called something
else the username and the password are
for sure going to be different so if we
hardcode it in we won't actually be able
to change it in the future we we need a
dynamic way to kind of have our code
change based off of if it's in our
development environment or our
production environment so later on in
this course we'll figure out how to do
that however for now we're just going to
work on keeping things simple and just
learning how to interact with the
database before we start moving into
things like environment
variables all right so the first thing
that we're going to work on is
retrieving all of our posts from our
post table and so what we're going to do
is we'll go to our specific path
operation for that which is the app.get
poost right here and let's figure out
how to do this so if we go back to up to
our connection right you'll see that we
have access to this object right here
which is cursor so we're going to use
that to actually make a query so we'll
say cursor.
execute and then this is where we are
going to P paste in our SQL
statements so I'm just going to put in
three quotes right here and then we just
put in our SQL statement uh so in this
case right to retrieve all posts we just
do select star from
posts okay and let's save this as a
variable so I'll just say these are my
posts and then let's just do a print
post to see what we
get and so I'm just going to go to my uh
Postman and we'll just find my get posts
request we'll send it all right and
let's see what happens right we could
see that it printed out none so this
doesn't actually do anything
right this is just passing in our SQL
statement however to actually run it we
have to
do
uh
cursor Dot and then we have a couple of
options we can do fetch all fetch many
fetch one so uh when it comes to
retrieving multiple posts we're going to
always use fetch all don't worry about
fetch many I don't think we're ever
going to use that uh and then if we ever
want to find one individual post uh you
know like a finding a post by an ID or
something then we can use fetch one cuz
I believe if you want to fetch a post by
an ID and you do fetch all it'll
technically get it but it'll just keep
searching through uh the database for
another post with that ID however we
know that only one post can have that
exact ID so it's inefficient to kind of
search through the entire database when
we know there's only ever going to be
one result so for those it's always
better to use fetch one but since we're
retrieving multiple posts we're going to
use fetch
all and at this point you know we don't
actually need to save this in a variable
because it's never going to return
anything we we can save the output of
this to be um posts so now if we save
this run this
again and I realized I forgot to
actually call it let's try that
again right you can see that we got all
of our posts from here and so now
instead of returning my post which is
our old array which um we're not going
to use we're going to return what we
just fetched so we're going to return
posts
and we'll go r r that print statement
it's not needed anymore and hopefully
this works so let's hit send all right
and so now you can see we've got our two
posts from our
database and it's got uh all the extra
field so it's got the published which is
the default value and then it's got the
created at timestamp which post added so
now we've actually successfully been
able to retrieve posts from our postest
database and you can see how easy it is
to actually work with that in fact it
was actually a little bit easier to do
this than to actually work with a uh
just an array stored in memory it really
just comes down to understanding SQL and
since we spent you know the last half an
hour or so really drilling into how SQL
Works uh you'll see that sql's pretty
easy and then once you know SQL you know
fetching you know retrieving updating
deleting posts from a SQL database even
within your python code is dead
simple okay so let's now move on to
creating a brand new post and so if we
just quickly take a look at the code
that we have right here uh you can see
that we have our schema we're going to
save that in our pantic model and so
we'll be able to access the properties
from the body within this post object so
I'm going to clear this out and just
delete all of that code for
now and for now I'm just going to
hardcode some value I'll just say
created
post and so let's work on uh inserting a
new post into our database
so once again we're going to uh access
the cursor object so we're going to do
cursor. execute and then once again
we're going to use the three
quotes and we're going to use typical
SQL so to insert something into our
database we do insert and then we say
insert into what table do we want to
insert it into we'll say the post table
right and then here we have to pass in
the columns uh of all the fields that we
want to uh enter in so if we go look at
our database uh that we have to pass in
a title and a
content and then everything else is
optional so we can also provide
published as well and then the database
creates the created ad and the ID so
it's really just these three columns
that we're going to uh pass into
here and so it's going to be
title content and then
published
yep and then we have to pass in the
values for for those columns and this is
where things get
interesting you never want to do any
kind of string interpolation and then
pass in the values of post directly into
this instead what we want to do is uh
we're going to
parameterize um or sanitize all the data
that we put into this SQL statement so
what you should do is do percent s uh
and so this kind of represents a
variable and we're going to do percent s
and then percent s
and so this variable is going to be the
value that gets passed in title this
Vari variable is going to be the one
that gets passed into content and this
variable is the one that gets passed
into the published column and what we
want to set these as uh we're going to
actually use a second item that we pass
into the execute command uh the execute
method and so here we pass in the actual
values so this first percent s what do
we want that to be that's going to be
post. tile so we're grabbing the title
from the body
then we want to pass in post.
content and then we want to pass in
post.
published all right and this may seem a
little confusing and let me correct that
um because I'm sure a lot of you thought
we could just do cursor. execute and
then here we pass in just an a an F
string and then I can just copy all of
this and then pass in
here oops and the values we can just do
you know post.
title and then um you know post. content
and so on and this would technically
work however this makes you vulnerable
to SQL injection so if the user for the
title uh decided to you know if we go to
the create post and for the title he
decided to pass in some kind of weird
squl statement like uh
insert
into blah blah blah right he puts in SQL
instead of a valid title this is what is
a SQL injection uh attack and he could
potentially uh manipulate data within
our SQL database that's why it's never
good to do it to pass that data in
directly into here instead all of these
um you know SQL libraries like uh uh
like our postris library here uh they
actually can sanitize the inputs so when
we do this percent s method and then
pass it in as the uh second field into
the execute statement it'll actually
make sure that there's no you know weird
SQL commands in there and it's going to
make sure that we're not vulnerable to
SQL injection so that's why we never do
it like
this and we always do it like this and
just keep in mind right these are just
variables or placeholders and then the
values we want to pass into that will be
passed
into um these parentheses right here as
the second parameter into the execute
method so post. tile since it's the
first one in this list is going to go to
the first percent s and then post.
content is going to go to the second
percent s and then post. published will
go to the third percent s so the order
matters they match up with whichever
percent Des comes first so if I took um
you know post out published right and
then moved it all the way to the
front well now post out published would
go to the first percent s post out title
would go to the second one that would
cause issues because it doesn't line up
with that so that's why we want to make
sure that the the order really does in
fact
matter and just like we had before uh
anytime we create something in our
database we want return uh the created
result so we can use the returning
keyword and we'll return
everything uh and so you're probably
thinking you know we we can just save
newor poost equals that and then since
we're returning it it's going to get
stored into that variable and that's not
exactly correct uh instead what we have
to do is to get that returned value we
have to do a new uncore poost and then
we do
cursor. fetch one
so that'll get whatever we return from
here and then what we're going to do is
we're going to say newor poost it's
going to get returned to the user let's
save that and let's see what happens so
go to our create post and then I'm going
to clear that out and just say hey hey
this is my new
post and let's hit send so it looks like
everything worked right 21 created you
can see it's got all of these values
let's go back to our SQL database I'm
going to just do a quick uh query so
I'll just say query
tool and I'll just say select star from
Posts let's run it and if we take a look
at the values and the title should be
hey this is my new post with an ID of
three you could see it's not in there uh
and so you might be wondering well uh
you know the output of our our API looks
perfect it sent it all back well when
you're working with uh postgress or any
of these
libraries you have to actually do one
last thing you actually have to commit
the changes uh just like when it comes
to working in our database you know if I
create something here pass in some data
into the content it's not saved in there
I actually have to finally save it so to
save that data we have to reference uh
instead of the cursor we're going to
reference the connection and then we
have to do a
commit so if we go down here we just say
con which is my connection to my
database and just say commit so that's
actually going to push those changes out
so we'll save that now I'll try this
again all right and so now we got it
looks like it has an IDE of four if I go
to my postgress database I'm going to do
another
search sure it's okay if it deletes it
uh and so now we can see idea 4 hey this
is my new post so now it worked so keep
in mind anytime you want to insert data
uh into your code make sure you do a
connection. commit to actually save it
into the postest database because these
are all staged changes so we're stage
staging it we can see the result of the
stage but we have to commit it to the
database to actually finalize those
changes all right so now let's move on
to fetching an individual post by an ID
um I want you guys to take a crack at
this C if you can try to figure it out
it's going to be relatively similar to
the two other previous ones we've done
so we'll start out by referencing the
cursor object as usual and then we'll
execute and then here we're going to
pass in our SQL
statement and so we're do is Select star
from post that's going to grab every
post but we want to grab just one post
based off of the ID and so you guys
already know how to do that we can say
where ID equals and then whatever ID
that you want uh and so let's take a
look at our database I have uh an ID a
post with an ID of one so right now I'm
just going to hard code it I'm going to
say post with an ID of
one and at this point this is not going
to return anything to actually return
something we'll say uh cursor do Fetch
and then we're going to use not fetch
all but fetch one because there's only
ever going to be a post with an IDE of
one just and so this is going to make it
a little bit more efficient and then I'm
going to save that as
post I'll just say test post not to get
confused with the other post and then
we're going to print that out just to
see if it
worked so let's get one
post and it doesn't really matter what
we send it as
if I take a look at this print statement
you can see that we were able to get
just that one single post so it looks
like that worked so now let's clear out
all of this other code I'm going to
remove the print statement um actually
before we do that first of all let's not
hard code the value anymore instead we
want to use the ID that we passed in uh
From the Path parameter so how do we do
that remember this we want to always
make sure that we're not vulnerable to
SQL injection attack so we'll do percent
s that's going to be the placeholder for
the value and then the second thing that
we pass into the execute method this is
going to be the ID so we take the ID and
then that's going to get pushed into
this value so it's essentially doing the
same exact thing so let's see what
happens uh when we try to run this again
and I'm going to try to grab a post of
one and let's see what happens all right
so it looks like we got an error so
let's take a
look and it says that int object does
not support indexing so it's not very
helpful however I'll tell you EX exactly
what's
happening because this is a string we
need ID to be a string as well right now
it's an integer because we validated it
as an integer and we converted it to an
integer but we need this to be a string
or then it's not going to work so we
have to convert it to a string it's
pretty simple you just do
string and that's all and at that point
that should fix the issue and I'm sure
you guys are a little bit confused
because uh when when it comes in as a uh
path parameter it's going to come in as
a string we then convert it to an INT to
then only convert it back into a string
uh and so you might think well maybe we
should just change this to a string but
if you change that to a string then it
could potentially open up it to us to
issues where the user could type in
something like this which isn't a valid
ID so we do have to validate it as a
number uh convert it to an INT and then
convert it back to a string once
again let's save this
this our error should go away and let's
try
this all right no error so it looks like
everything's good and so now it's just a
matter of cleaning up our code and
getting rid of all of the other
code so I'm going to rename this so this
is just going to be post so we can keep
everything else the same so if we didn't
find a post right which means uh you
know the database return nothing it's
going to be set to none and then we can
raise the usual exception but if we did
find a post we're just going to return
it
but now if I get a post of one you can
see that we've got that post which is
clearly from the post database because
it has the created at field and then if
I try to grab a post of an if I try to
grab the ID of a post that doesn't exist
try five we can see that post with the
ID of 5 was not found and let's just
double check to make sure that there is
no post with an ID of five and there
isn't a
perfect and you know guys one
interesting thing uh later down in some
of the next PATH operations that we we
work on um I did run into a weird issue
where if I didn't have a comma right
after this even though there's nothing
that comes after it led to an issue I'm
not sure why it did that um but keep in
mind if you do run into some weird
issues just put in this extra comma for
some reason or another it potentially
fixes some issues okay so just keep that
in mind I don't have an explanation for
it you know maybe it's listed somewhere
uh within stock over flow I'm sure
someone eventually or occasionally asked
this question and I just couldn't find
it
all right so now let's work on deleting
a post I'm going to remove these
comments to clear up some space we're
going to do cursor. execute you guys
should already know the exact SQL
statement that we need so it's going to
be
select sorry not select
delete from post table and then we're
going to delete by ID so we'll say where
ID equals and then remember we don't
want to pass in the um the user input
directly we want to do that placeholder
again and then we also want to we want
to do a returning so we'll see what that
post was before it was
deleted and then we'll pass in the value
of the post so this is going to be ID um
but we want to convert it to a string so
we don't hit that error
again and then I'm going to do that
empty Comma just to avoid any potential
issues and then we have to do a cursor.
fetch one to get the deleted
post and I'm going to save this as a
variable so I'll say um deleted _ poost
equals
that we can remove this and then for
this exception when we try to grab a the
ID uh of a post that doesn't exist we
can just say if deleted undor poost
which is the post that we batched wasn't
found we're going to throw an
error we can delete this and remember
there's one last thing right anytime we
want to make a change to a database we
have to connect uh commit to it so we'll
do connection.
commit and then everything else we can
keep our code exactly the
same and then I'm just going to run this
just to get so we have a post with an
idea of 1 two and four so let's go ahead
and delete one of those so if I delete
uh the post with an IDE of four what do
we get oh sorry we're still under the
get let's go to our delete this is our
delete and then we're going to delete
with an ID of four 204 no cont content
so that's good and let's double check
our postgress database to see if it got
deleted we can see that it's now gone
and then let's try to now grab the with
the same one let's try to delete the
same post which no longer exists we
should get a 404 post with ID of 4 does
not exist
perfect and last but not least the final
path operation we need to update is the
update post path
operation we'll grab the cursor object
and we'll execute our SQL statement
again
and so here we'll do
update
posts and then here we want to set the
title and what do we want to set our
title to well that's going to be passed
in from the user so any kind of data we
get from the user you know we have no
idea if they put in you know very
suspicious SQL uh data so we always want
to put the
placeholders uh and so all the fields
that they can update are going to be the
title the content and published so then
the next one's going to be
content and the last one's going to be
published and then we'll pass in those
values and that's going to come from our
post object so we'll do post. tile post.
content and finally post.
published and uh just like we had with
inserts and delete we can do a returning
so we can actually get the returned we
can actually return the updated object
do returning star so we can get all the
columns and then to actually fetch that
updated post we have to do cursor. fetch
one and then we'll save that in a
variable called updated
post and then we can remove this this is
our previous code and then for the
little check to make sure that we
actually got and updated a post we can
get updated post if we didn't if it
returned none then we're going to send a
404 because a post with that ID didn't
exist and then we can delete all of this
nonsense and then what we return back is
going to be updated
post up make sure you get updated with a
D or then if you just do update post it
tries to call it this own function which
doesn't
work and I'm just going to see what I
have in my database so I've got a post
uh with an ID of one so we're going to
update him you can see currently the
title is first post so if I go to my
update
post I'm going to send it with the ID of
one we're going to update that post and
then it's going to have an updated title
so if we see that get updated then we
know it worked so we'll set and do a
send we can see what we got back and so
it looks like it updated but let's
actually double check with our
database and it did not update and I'm
sure you guys can take a guess as to
exactly what went wrong remember any any
time you want to make changes to a
database we need to do the connection.
commit so let's try this again all right
so we got the same result let's take a
look at our database run this and then
we've got updated title it look like it
updated
both and uh that looks like a bug so
what did we do wrong well if you look at
our code we're updating every single
post because I didn't provide a wear
condition what post do I need to update
so that's a mistake on my end so we have
to do where and then we'll say ID equals
and that ID is going to come from this
value so we're going to put another
placeholder
there and then that last value is going
to
be the ID converted to a string just
like we did before so simple
mistake going save that and before I do
that I'm just going to change this back
to first post
and I'm going to change this back to
Second
post and then just going to have some
random
text and then we'll save
that then let's update
this all right so we updated our code
and then let's take a look at our
database we'll run this
again and we can see that it was updated
and you'll notice how that first post
then moved down the list because it was
most recently updated but we updated
just one post this time and then last
but not least let's try to update a post
that doesn't exist so I'm going to
search for an ID of 23 try to update
that and then if I do that uh we can see
that we get a little bit of an error so
what happened here we got data equals
null uh and so it looks like
this didn't work and it looks like uh it
got it changed back to update post so
make sure uh you reference this variable
so I need that D now let's try try
that and now we get the correct
404 when it comes to working with a
database within a python application or
really any application across any
language there's a couple of different
ways of interacting with the database uh
and so we saw how we can use the default
postgress driver uh to talk to a
postgress database by sending SQL
commands and this is my preferred method
of working with databases because I'm
fairly comfortable with SQL and so it
just makes sense to use raw SQL and send
that directly to postgress using
whatever the default postgress driver is
for your specific programming language
however there are other methods uh and
so you'll see that one of the popular
ways of you know really working with
databases is using what's referred to as
a object relational mapper or an or and
so an orm is a layer abstraction that
sits between the database and our fast
API application uh and so we never
actually talk directly to a database
anymore instead we talk to the omm and
then the orm will actually talk to our
database uh and so some of the benefits
are is that we don't actually have to
work with SQL anymore so instead of
using raw SQL what we'll do is we'll
actually use standard python code uh
calling various functions and methods
that ultimately translate into SQL
themselves so let's see what that
actually looks
like uh and so with our traditional
application which is what we have now
we've got our fast API server and it's
going to talk to our database by sending
SQL using the default postrest database
driver however with an omm what we can
do is fast API no longer has to talk SQL
instead fast API will actually use
regular python code uh to send you know
specific commands to an orm and then the
orm will take that python code convert
it into regular SQL and then using the
same database driver that we're using
for it'll actually talk to the database
uh and then it'll eventually send that
result back to us because the databases
they can only talk SQL however by doing
like this we can kind of abstract away
that SQL complexity and make use of uh
very common python uh objects and
various other python features to
actually generate and build queries as
well as to create and Define tables so
let's take a look at what an Orum
ultimately allows us to do so one of the
first things is instead of us going into
you know PG admin and creating the
tables and all the columns ourselves
what we can do is we can Define our
tables as python models and so if you
take a look at the code down here what
we can do is we can actually Define what
our tables and post scripts are going to
look like and so you can see here we
give it the table a name and then we
could specify each of the columns you'll
see a lot of the common fields that we
already worked with so the type so this
is an integer this is a string we can
also see if a field is nullable we can
see that the ID is set to be a primary
key so we're using standard python
classes to Define our table so that we
don't need to do it ourselves using PG
admin and on top of that queries can be
made using regular python code so we can
actually chain on different methods to
construct various python uh to construct
various SQL queries and so if you take a
look at one of the queries down here
below that I provide as an example you
can see we just do query we provide the
specific table that we want to uh query
and that's going to be based off of the
specific models and then we can just
pass in whatever filter commands and
then grab the first entry so you can see
that there's no SQL anymore it's just
standard python code uh and so that
makes it a little bit easier for some
people who may not be as strong on SQL
uh and so they don't have to worry about
writing these complex SQL commands they
can just chain on uh specific methods to
a to a DB query to generate their final
SQL commands and so the you know there's
a couple of different ORS I'd say the
most popular one within the python world
is SQL Alchemy and one of the things to
keep in mind is that this is a om that's
a standalone library right so this has
this library has nothing to do with fast
API we're going to use it in our fast
API application but I want you guys to
understand that it actually has no
relationship with fast API it's not part
of fast API it's its own library and you
can use SQL Alchemy with any web
development framework you can use it
with any python application even if it's
not a web application as well so in the
next video we'll start taking a look at
how to work with cql Alchemy and how to
set up a database connection using SQL
Alchemy instead of using the default
postgress
driver okay so in this lesson we're
going to start taking a look at SQL
Alchemy and get that set up in our
project and so there's a couple of
things that I want you guys to take a
look at so the first thing is I want you
to go to the SQL page so if you just
search for SQL uh you'll get to the main
page and then if you want to go to
library and then references and then
version 1.4 which is the one we're going
to use however I believe they're going
to come out with a version 2.0 which is
going to be pretty different so uh if
you are watching this video in the
future you definitely want to install
version 1.4 so that you can follow along
with this course so you can click on
that uh and so there's a nice little
tutorial you can follow uh and then
there's also some reference
documentation when it comes to setting
up the omm so if you click on sess
session usage this will show you how to
set up a session um however if you go to
the fast API documentation as well uh
fast API they've got great documentation
so if you go to the documentation and
then select SQL relational databases
this is going to show you how to set it
up with SQL Alchemy okay so first things
first let's go ahead and do a pip
install for SQL Alchemy so we'll do pip
install and then SQL Alchemy
now guys I want you to remember that um
well first of all I'm running 1.4.2 3
but the thing is SQL Alchemy doesn't
know how to talk to a database right it
has all the code for us to write python
uh Define all the models and things like
that but it doesn't actually know how to
talk to a database it actually needs a
database driver and so if you take a
look at all of the packages that we
already installed by doing a pip
freeze right we in the last video or in
the the last section we installed our
postgress database driver so whatever
database you guys plan to use so if you
want to use a mySQL database with um uh
with SQL Alchemy you have to make sure
that you install the underlying driver
as well because ultimately that's what's
used to talk to the database since we're
using postgress we need to install this
as well but since we were using it
originally in the previous sections we
had we already have it installed so we
don't need to worry about doing that but
keep that in mind right SQL has no way
to talk to a database it still needs the
underlying driver to communicate with it
and that's usually how all orm's work
but now that we have that on inside our
app folder I'm going to create a new
file and I'm going to call this
database. py so this is going to handle
our uh database
connection and from here um what I'm
essentially going to do is um just
really follow this documentation so if
you take a look at it right here uh we
can just copy all of this code right
here when it comes to importing
statements so this is just going to
import all of this SQL Alchemy code that
we
want all right and then we have to
specify a our connection string so where
is our postrest database located and so
if you take a look at how we had this
set up before using the default postris
database driver right we passed it into
this connect function however a lot of
times when it comes to working with
databases there's a a unique URL that
you create to connect to any kind of
database and there's a a specific format
for that and the format for that is
actually pretty simple so go to database
py and then I'm going to create a
variable called uh
SQL
Alchemy undor database _ URL so this is
going to be a regular string uh and the
structure of the URL for postgress
database it's going to be postgressql
because that's the type of database
colon SL slash then we have the username
that you have to put in
colon then we have the
password and then we do at and then this
is going to be the IP
address I'll say ip- address slash host
name whichever one you're
using in our case that's going to be
Local
Host and then you have to provide the
database name that you want connect to
so that's the format of a uh connection
string that we have to pass into SQL
Alchemy and then what we do is we say we
have to create a engine so the engine is
what's responsible uh for SQL Alchemy to
connect to a postgress database so you
do engine equals and then we're going to
reference this create
engine and then we pass in our
connection string so let say SQL Alchemy
database URL however this is not filled
in yet so we're going to fill in this
data so go ahead and put in your
username so if you haven't created a
custom user going to default to
postgress put in your password so we'll
do password 1 2 3 for me the IP address
/host name this is going to be Local
Host and then the database name this is
going to be fast API or whatever you
created your database
as so that's your connection string and
like I mentioned before it's never good
to hardcode this value somewhere in your
code because now you've got your
password stored in your code and it's
going to get checked into GitHub and
then anyone can see it so this is bad
practice however we will change this in
the future all right so like I said the
engine is responsible for um
establishing that connection however
when you actually want to talk to the
SQL database we have to make use of a
session so we do um session
local equals session maker
and then we just pass in a couple values
so autoc commit
false autof flush equals
false and then bind equals
engine all right and all of these values
these are just some default values now
keep in mind when you're creating the uh
when you use when you use the uh create
engine function uh if you are using a
SQL light database you have to pass in
this option
uh as the second parameter so you do the
database URL and then you do connection
args equals check same throut equals
false this is something that's exclusive
to the SQL light because it's I guess
it's just running in memory you don't
need to do this for postgress you don't
need to do it for any other SQL based
database and then you can see in the
documentation this is what the uh
connection string will look like so it's
just confirming what I already showed
you guys and so we can just kind of keep
scrolling down and we don't really need
anything else uh except for this last
line right here so we here we have to
Define our base class uh and so all of
the models that we Define to actually
create our tables in postrest they're
going to be extending this Base Class so
we can just copy
this and then paste it into here and
when I was first doing all of this you
know it was a little confusing and
overwhelming just think about that just
for now I want you to assume that it's
more of just a cut and paste job it's
just a copy and paste the only thing
that really matters that you're going to
be changing is going to be that
postgress URL but everything else for
pretty much every project you can just
copy and paste to this entire code and
now within our database. py file that's
all we have to do the next thing that we
want to do is Define our tables like I
said with an OM we no longer have to
create tables within PG admin or any CLI
utility we can Define it as a
python model so what we're going to do
is we're going to create a new file and
this is going to store all of our models
we'll and we'll call this models.py so
every model represents a table in our
database and what we're actually going
to do is um let's take a look at our
database and let's see how we can Define
this as a model within
python so the first things first we got
to import a few
things and the main thing that we got to
import is from our database file we have
to import
base so let's do
import.
database sorry that should be from
database import base and then we can go
ahead and Define our model so uh right
now we've been dealing with only working
with posts so we're going to create a
model for posts and like I said this is
going to actually create the table
within postgress so what we're actually
going to do is I'm going to delete this
table eventually and then we're going to
have uh Python and cql and my fast API
application in SQL Alchemy created for
us on the fly but I'm going to keep this
for now just so we can take a look at
all the fields that we
have so here I'm just going to call this
post and keep in mind when it comes to
classes in Python you always want to
make sure that they're capitalized and
then this has to extend base so this is
that base model from SQL Alchemy and we
just have to extend
it and there's a couple things that we
have to pass in the first thing is what
do we want to call this table within
postgress because we have this class
name which only python knows but uh we
can specify a specific name within
postgress now our table name right now
is called post so I think we should just
keep it at that so we could
saycore table
name underscore uncore equals and then
the name of the table you want so here
we're going to name it
posts and then now we have to Define all
of the columns right so just like we
went within PG admin and went column by
column creating it specifying all of
their constraints and things like that
we're going to do this
within uh within uh our python code so
we'll say the first thing is we want an
ID so we'll say ID
equals and then how do we actually
create a column well we have to import
something from SQL Alchemy so we'll say
from SQL Alchemy import column so now I
can create a
column and then there's a couple of
different fields that we have to pass in
so the first thing is what type of
column is it and so if you go back to
our post table and go to properties
right when we went out columns the first
thing they have to specify is what is
the data type uh and so uh we have
access to most of the ones that we see
in here uh and but we have to import it
from SQL Alchemy first so the ID column
is going to be an
integer and so we have to actually
import that we'll do
integer and now I can pass in
integer and that was a mistake let me
delete
that and then if we take a look at our
ID field we did say that this was a
primary key so we'll
say primary key equals true and then if
you want to you can also say
nullable equals
false right so that's the equivalent of
doing the not null all right then we can
Define the next column which is going to
be title and then we call column this is
going to be a string now
but we have to import string from our
SQL
Alchemy and once again this is going to
be nullable set to false so we can't
leave that
blank the next column is going to be
fairly simple uh similar now we've got
content this is going to be a string and
nullable is going to be set to false
then we got
published this is going to be a Boolean
but we got to import that from the
library and this one can be left as
empty and if you remember we set a
default value for our publish so it's
always going to be by default set to
true if we don't pass in a value and I
believe that's how we do it however I'd
have to double check just to make sure
that's what it is now the last column
that we'll need to add is the Tim stamp
but we're going to hold off on doing
that for now and we're going to leave it
as such and then later we'll come back
to um adding that Tim stamp in all right
and so we're pretty much done with our
model and what we want to do is in our
main file we want to copy this Command
right here so this create engine so this
is going to create all of our models so
we'll go to our code I'm going to go to
my main file and somewhere up top I'm
going to
create that right there however we have
to import the right
commands and so the first thing that we
want to import is our models so we'll
do from Star import
models and then from our database file
we'll say from dot which is current
directory so we're going to grab a file
from our current directory we're going
to import
sorry from our database file we're going
engine and so at that point that is good
to
go and then finally if we go back to our
documentation the last thing that we
have to do is we have to create this
dependency so just go ahead and copy
this for now and just paste it in here
and we want to import session local as
well and we should no longer get any
errors
here and so what this ultimately is
going to do is the the session object is
kind of what's responsible for talking
with the databases and so we've created
this function where we actually get a
connection to our database uh or get a
session to our database and so every
time we get a request we're going to get
a session we're going to you know be
able to send SQL statements to it and
then after that request is done we'll
then close it out uh and so it's is much
more efficient doing it like this uh by
having one little function and we can
just keep calling this F function every
time we get a request to any of our API
endpoints and so now that we've got our
uh dependency to actually get that
session for all of our path operations
where we want to perform some sort of
operation on the database what we're
going to do is with with inside the path
operation function we're going to pass
in another uh parameter and it's going
to be uh session equals depends and then
we're going to call this get DB function
so what that's ultimately going to do is
this line right here don't worry too
much about it but like I said it's going
to create that session to our database
so that we can perform some operations
and then close it once that request is
done and then we can repeat that process
for every single one of our path
operations so anytime you send a request
to any API endpoint uh you're going to
have this being passed into the path
operation function so that we can create
that connection and then close it out
and like I said a lot of this is just
copy and paste so once you write this
down even if you don't really understand
it you don't really have to touch it
ever again after
that all right so let's copy
this and what we're going to do is I'm
going to create another uh route or
another path operation just for testing
purposes because I don't want to mess up
any of our other code and so I'll just
say at
app.get and this is going to be at
slash SQL Alchemy so this is just to
test to see if it works and I'll say de
test
posts and then we want to pass in
that uh that code that we just copied
right here however we don't have a
session or depends in this case so we're
going to have to import those so from
our database
file our session is going to be from
there actually sorry that's not actually
coming from there is it it do we have a
session in here we actually do not have
session here so instead this is not
going to come from here actually instead
we're going to import that from SQL
Alchemy I'll say import
sqlalchemy.orm
import session and I realized this
should be a
from and then we also have to import the
depends method from from our fast API
library and so now if we go down to our
route we should get no more errors and
it looks
good and then here we're just going to
return uh
status success for
now and then finally the last thing that
we're going to do is we're going to
delete our post table I'm going to do a
delete drop hit yes
and we have no more tables now I can
close this
out sorry I didn't mean to save that
close that don't save
it all right now we've got nothing so
let's save
everything and pray to God that there's
no errors and it so it doesn't look like
there's any
errors and uh just by saving that code
and restarting our application what
should have happened is once our code
ran and we run this I believe should
actually create the tables within
postgress so let's refresh this real
quick I'm going to just right click here
hit
refresh we go under tables look at that
guys we now have our post table even
though we deleted it so if we take a
look at our post table and go under
properties columns you can see it's got
the three columns that we defi well four
columns that we defined and that all
comes from our models.py
and so we've got the four columns that
we we def find here and so uh if uh
whenever we start our application SQL
Alchemy will check to see if there's a
table called posts if it's there it's
not going to do anything if it's not
there it's going to go ahead and create
it for us based off of what we defined
in the
model now there's one last thing that I
want to do just to kind of clean things
up uh in our main.py file I don't like
having this get DB function within here
I want to keep all of my database code
um all of my database initialization
code within my database. py file so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to actually
cut this out paste it into my database.
py
file and then we're going to import this
into my main file so that I don't have
to uh have that in my main file
cluttering it up because our main file
is already fairly large so for my
database file I can import getor
DB and now we no longer need session
local cuz it's showing us it's grayed
out so we can remove
that and at that point everything should
still be working so just as a just to
double check I'm going to delete this
once
again and then I'm going to save this
which is going to trigger um a Reload of
our application and then once our
application reloads if I refresh my
database it should have created another
uh D another post table and it looks
like it did and let's just double check
that all of the columns are there and it
looks like they are so everything looks
good uh in the next video uh the one
thing that we do need to change is that
we have to add the created ad column so
we'll tackle that in the next video in
the last video we were able to get SQL
Alchemy to generate our own post table
however if we actually poke around with
it we'll see that there's a couple of
issues so if I go to uh right click on
it and select properties and I go to
columns all right we can see that all of
these fields are set to not null and the
primary key is set to the ID field so
everything looks good so far however
when I go to the
published column and I go to constraints
I can see that the default isn't
set and so if we go back to our code I
actually uh made one little mistake
right this default is not going to give
us what we need instead what we need to
do is we need to set this to server
default um because it's ultimately the
the postest server or the database
server that's going to actually uh send
the default so I'm going to put in
quotations as a string we can just set
this to be
true and then if you haven't added this
go ahead and add nullable to false I'm
going to make all of my columns uh not
allowed to be empty that's because the
server is going to add the default to
true for this so let's try this out now
if I hit save right now and I go to my
postc database and then we can just
right click on this hit
refresh and then we do properties again
and I go to
column and then we go to uh sorry go to
the publish column we'll see that
there's no constraint and so this is
kind of a limitation of SQL Alchemy
because SQL Alchemy will generate your
tables but it does it in a very simple
manner what it actually does is if I go
to my main.py file uh and then it runs
this code I believe this is the code
that actually creates the tables what it
does is it'll go through all of our
models and it'll look for a table named
called post if it doesn't exist it will
then create one based off of these rules
however if the table already exists even
though we've changed the different
attributes The Columns and things like
that uh if it looks for the if it finds
a table with that name already in there
it's not going to touch it so it's not
going to help us modify tables and
things like that in fact if you actually
take a look at the
documentation uh I've got so many tabs
open let's see if I can find it right
here I search for almic uh and so
normally when it comes to creating your
tables when it comes to handling
migrations which is a term that's used
for changing the columns uh and the
schema of your tables then you want to
use another software called almic uh SQL
Alchemy isn't really meant for handling
database migrations or making changes to
it so that's why we don't see it
automatically make those changes so for
now what we're going to do to get around
this limitation is I'm just going to
cancel out of this and we're just going
to delete the table so we'll drop the
table and then we'll go back to our code
and then I'm just going to hit save and
so now that it runs again it's going to
look for a table called post since we
deleted it it's not going to see it it's
going to then go ahead and create our
table and now if I just right click on
tables hit refresh we should see that we
have a post table and if I go to
properties we can then go to columns
published and then if we go to
constraints we can see the default set
to true so it looks like that fixed that
issue now the second thing I want to do
is I want to add our uh timestamp column
that's very important we need to know
when a post was
created so let's create a field called
created Created
at column now what's the column type
going to be well we're going to use a
column type of timestamp so type in
timestamp we can let VSS code
automatically import it um but all it's
going to do is it's going to import it
from SQL uh SQL Alchemy SQL do SQL types
and then within here we have to pass in
a property of time
zone equals true so this is going to
also add in the time zone and that's
going to be a capital
T then the next thing we want to do is
provide a it's going to be nullable set
to
false so it can't be left empty but
we're going to give it a default value
if the user doesn't provide it which
they never will and so we'll do server
default but we have to do something a
little bit different here I have to to
uh import a function or a method called
text from SQL Alchemy so from this right
here SQL al. sq. Expressions I'm going
to do
text and then here we're going to do now
right just like we typed in within our
post database you know if we wanted to
manually do this we would just go under
um the column let's say we had to
created that column we can just go in
there go into constraints and then type
in now like that and that's going to
generate a time stamp so we're doing the
same thing but we're just doing it
through python code now so once again
we'll save this we going to drop this
table so that we recreate
it and then we'll save it one more time
this is going to trigger a Reload and
then a refresh of the table we should
now see it so let's go into properties
let's take a look at our columns we've
got the created at column and then if I
go under constraints we can see the
default is now set to the current time
so we've got that working let's just
quickly test this out so I'm going to go
into view edit all rows and I'm just
going to create a
post we'll save this and let's make sure
all the default values get set looks
like that's good and it looks like the
time is set just right as
well so now that we have verified that
SQL Alchemy has created the proper
tables within postgress it's time to go
ahead and create our first query and
like I mentioned in a previous lesson
with SQL Alchemy or really any omm the
way we do queries is going a little bit
is going to be a little bit different
we're no longer going to rely on regular
SQL instead we're going to use basic
python methods uh and so go to your main
folder uh sorry your main file right and
we we saw this uh test uh route that we
defined so what we're going to do is
we're going to run our first query
within this test route and then
afterwards we can go ahead and delete it
and then we can update all of our uh
pre-existing path operations and so like
I mentioned before uh anytime you want
to perform any kind of database
operation with SQL Alchemy uh within
fast API we want to make sure that we
pass it as a parameter into our path
operation function so you just call DB
so we're saving it inside a variable
called DB and then we're just calling
the session object and then we're
calling the get DB function within
depends so this makes it a dependency
and so if you already forgot what that
is um just go to your database uh you
can see that it's this function right
here so this is going to actually create
a session towards database uh for every
request to that specific API endpoint
and then it's going to close it out once
we're
done right and then within main there's
one thing that we have to import and
that is models so you just do from.
import models that's going to import
this specific model so that we can
actually make queries to
it all right and to make a query right
we're going to access that database
object which is getting passed into um
our function
and then here we want to tap into the
query
method and then we have to pass in the
specific model for the table we want a
query we only have one model in this
case which is our post model so that
when we use this specific model it's
going to allow us to make a query to our
post
table and here so we'll call
models.
poost so that's going to allow us to
access that model and then from here
what we can do is uh we have a couple of
different methods that we run can run
but since we want to query all of our
posts we just do all so is going to grab
every single entry within the post
table and then here we could just save
this as a a variable called
posts and then for the return statement
I'm just going to say we're going to
return
data and then
posts so let's test this out now and I'm
going to go to get posts actually I'm
just going to create a new test test um
test route so our new
request and I'm just going to copy the
URL and then this is stored in SQL
Alchemy let's try this out and this
should result in us getting just one
post so let me just double check my
postris database just to make sure that
we only have one post so I'm just going
to open up the query
tool and we'll just do select star from
posts yep and it looks like I only have
one post and so that's why we only got
one Post in our request and if I add a
new
post and save that and we make a new
request we should get two posts so that
verifies that we are successfully
connecting to our database and we are
successfully retrieving those posts and
so I want you to stop and really take a
look at how the queries um vary when it
comes to working with an orm versus
working with regular SQL um because if
we actually see the uh path operation
for getting posts at/ poost here this is
where we're using regular SQL so here we
do select star from post but if you take
a look at this there's no SQL here right
we're just tapping into the database
object and we're going to call a query
and then from here we have to tell what
specific model which in this case
remember these models represent tables
and then we just say I want all posts
now what's even more interesting is if I
remove
this and then uh for now I'm just going
to hardcode you know successful just
some random data I'm going to do a
print posts so right here we're calling
the database object and then we're
calling query so what actually happens
when we just do
this well I'm going to save that we're
going to send a request we're not going
to get any data back that's to be
expected but take a look at this right
we're actually taking a look at what
what the query object returns and you
can see that it's just returning a
regular SQL statement so it's saying I
want you to return post. ID and then
it's just renaming it postore ID then I
want to grab post. tile we're renaming
it as post. tile so it's grabbing all of
the
columns and then we're going to grab it
from our post table so it's really no
different than just running you know
select star from Posts essentially
that's all it's doing but it's just
renaming all the columns to be a little
bit more easy to read so you can see
that these queries this query object is
just performing SE so it abstracts all
of the SQL away from you and it handles
all the logic of generating the SQL so
that you don't have to know or you don't
have to have as solid of an
understanding of SQL and this allows you
to really focus on uh building out the
API this allows you to focus on U
working with python and less with cql in
the databases
themselves so now we know when we call
query this actually creates the query
however to run the query we have to run
a specific method so there's a couple of
methods that we can run um but if you
want to grab everything then you just
call all and then it's going to take
this SQL query and then it's actually
going to run it against the database and
then return it but until we call this
last method it's nothing more than just
a SQL query that hasn't been run
yet all right so now that we know how to
fetch all posts let's just go down here
right and let's just put in this logic
so um this is our actual end point for
retrieving posts this is our get post
and what we're going to do is I'm going
to comment this out just so that uh uh
you know later down the road if you guys
want to just take a look back how you do
it with regular raw SQL you still have
that within the code
base and anytime you want to work with
the database remember you have to pass
it in to the path operation function so
this is going to make it a
dependency and you'll see by doing it
like this it'll make testing a lot
easier and then we can just copy this
right
here and then we're going to return the
post so let's test that out
so now if I go to get posts hit send you
can see that we successfully retrieved
both of our
posts all right and it really is as
simple as that uh and then in the next
video we'll start taking a look at how
we can create posts and so
on in this video we're going to start
tackling how to create a post using a
omm or specifically SQL Alchemy so once
again I'm going to copy out or comment
out all of the SQL code and what we're
going to do is we're going to see how we
can actually create a brand new object
uh or a brand new Post in this case so
first things first anytime any of your
path operations need to work with the
database we need to make sure that we
copy this exact input argument into the
path operation function this is going to
give us a access to our database object
so that we can actually make queries and
make changes to our database and by
passing it in like this it's going to
make it a dependency and it's going to
make it a lot easier for testing and and
things like that technically you don't
have to do it like this uh you could
just import it directly in there however
by doing it like this like I said uh
testing becomes a little bit easier all
right so we've got our models right and
we have one specific model so this model
represents our posts and so to create a
brand new post we have to reference this
model and pass in the specific fields
that we want to create a new entry with
so first of all we have to make sure we
import that model and you can see that
we are importing all of our models by
doing from. import models so we can
access models do um Post in this case to
access that specific
model and so here I'm going to do
models.
poost and then we have to pass in the
properties of the brandly of the brand
new post that we want to
create uh and so what are the properties
right if you take a look at our SQL
statement we need the title the content
and uh the published Boolean right and
that's all going to be derived from the
request that we get which is going to be
stored in the post object so I can
reference all of those fields so I can
say the title for the brand new post is
going to be set to whatever the title
the user sent and that can be accessed
with post. tile the content of the
brandly new created post is going to be
content equals post. content and then
the same thing is going to be for
published so it's going to be um post
dop published right if you take a look
at this code so far this doesn't look
too different from the SQL statement
right this says insert into posts and
then we pass in post. tile into the
title post. content into the content and
then post. published into published
right and so this is pretty much exactly
the same thing we're not doing anything
different we're just having uh SQL
Alchemy handle all of that logic so we
can do everything in just standard
python code and there's no SQL
anymore all right and the next thing
that we want to do is well let's save
the result as new
post and let's see what
happens so I'm going to save this
and then we're going to set a little
query so first of all I'm going to
create a new post I'm going to call this
a welcome to
Funland so much
fun okay and so then we'll we will send
a request and we got some data back and
so it looks like it worked however take
a look at our uh our data we've got a
title we've got a content and then we've
got published but where's the ID uh
where's the created ad field all the
fields that the database creates so this
makes me suspect that this didn't
actually work so let's go to postgress
and go ahead and make a query to your
table so select star from post that's
going to grab all of
them um and you'll see that based off of
the title welcome to Funland I do not
have that in there so it looks like this
was not successfully able to create a
post within our database so let's take a
look and see what went
wrong and uh if you actually take a look
at the uh the previous method right you
could see that uh we actually have to
commit something to the database so we
can create an entry but it doesn't
actually get pushed to the database
until we do a commit and so I'm
suspecting that we probably have to do a
similar thing so when it comes to SQL
Alchemy what we need to do is first of
all we have to tap into the database
object now we want to say db. add and
then we're going to add this newly
created post so this is going to add it
to the database however just like with
the connection. commit we have to commit
those changes so we do b.
commit and then the last thing that we
need to do is uh if you take a look at
our SQL statement we have this returning
star so that's going to return back the
uh newly created post uh with SQL
Alchemy it's a little bit different
right because we don't really have
access to that underlying SQL code we
can't add a returning statement to this
so the way that you do this in SQL
Alchemy is you do db.
refresh and then you pass in the new
post object so with this is going to do
is we create a brand new post we add it
to our database then we commit it and
then what we're going to do is we're
going to essentially retrieve that new
post that we just created and store it
back into the variable newor poost and
so all of this code should be uh
identical to this code and so now if we
uh we'll just return back new post and I
think that should fix our
issue so now if I hit
send right we do see an ID and we do see
a created that field so it looks like it
worked but we want to double check
within postgress so if I hit run and we
can see welcome to Funland so looks like
it's now successfully working and before
we wrap up this video uh there's one
thing I don't like about the way we've
done things right and this isn't
necessarily going to break or cause any
issues however you're going to see it's
very inefficient uh depending on what
your models look like now our model has
only a couple of fields and the user
only has to really pass in um two to
three fields which is title content and
published so it's not that big of a deal
but imagine if we have a model with 50
fields there's no limitation right you
could put as many fields as you want
well then things are going to get a
little bit more difficult because uh if
you see we have to extract all the
fields from our schema right and then we
have to kind of pass it in so we have to
say oh title equals post. title content
equals post. content and then published
equals post. published now if we have 50
fields we're going to have to do that 50
times and that's a little inefficient uh
and there's actually a much easier way
to do it and the the way to do this is
we have access to the post um object
which is you know um this is a pantic
model so it's going to ensure that it um
matches the schema that we set and we
want to say post. dict now we know
that's going to convert it to a regular
dictionary so if I do a
print save that and then just send a
request right take a look at this we've
got a regular python dictionary however
we need to be able to automatically take
that dictionary and convert it to this
format where uh instead of having uh you
know title like this and then welcome to
Funland it's going to be title equals
and then post out title content equals
post. content so how do we do that easy
all we have to do is unpack the
dictionary so you just do uh star star
and it's going to put it into this exact
same format so we can remove all of this
and just say star star post.
dict and that should ultimately do the
same exact thing except now if we uh go
back to our database uh or our model and
add in extra Fields it's going to
automatically unpack all of those fields
for us so we don't have to manually type
it
out all right we'll save that I'm going
to just uh put in some extra text just
to make sure we can verify
that and I realize we got to remove this
print statement it's going to throw an
error then we'll hit send it looks like
everything worked let's go to our
database search
and he it looks like it worked so you
can see that if we go back to our code a
lot cleaner uh than having to type out
each one of those fields and we can put
this all in one line so it looks a
little
better all right so now it's time to
handle querying for an individual post
so a post by a specific ID so once again
we will comment out the SQL
code and we will do this using SQL
Alchemy so once again copy the
database dependency right here and then
just pass it
in and this should actually be an
integer I don't know who changed that I
may have left that in from the previous
video yeah it should be an integer okay
uh and now what we want to do is uh just
like we saw when it comes to querying
all posts we have to do db. query pass
in the specific model that we're
interested in and then uh we're not
going to do a DOT all because we don't
want all the posts so we're going to
have to take a look at a different uh
query operation
so I'll say db.
query models. poost and then we want to
filter so we want to pass in a filter so
this is the equivalent of doing like a
wear you can see that we filter by doing
wear ID equals and then we pass in the
ID in this case we're going to
filter and then here we say uh whatever
the
models do post. ID is so this is going
to look through all of the posts in our
database and it's going to take a look
at all their IDs and we want to see
whenever that is equal to the ID that
the user requested so the ID from uh
this query parameter or this um path
parameter so we say when they're equal
that's the one we want to
return and uh if I do a uh print of
first of all let's save this to a
variable so I'll say post equals and
then I do a print of
post save that I'll open up the terminal
and then we'll send a request for an
individual post so we hit send um we get
a whole bunch of Errors that's okay let
me see and that's fully
expected all right and then we can see
the exact uh SQL statement that this
query actually
made uh and so here we're doing db.
query and then filter and we can see
that we got uh the select statement uh
and then here it's just grabbing all of
the uh all of the
columns right but then you can see from
post and then it says where post. ID
equals idore
1 all right and so this pretty much
looks exactly uh like we wanted right
it's if you look at our SQL statement
originally it doesn't look any
different and so at this point I think
this should be good to go however right
now it's still just raw SQL right we
could see what the SQL statement is but
if you recall from the previous one we
had to do a DOT all to actually send the
query so for us we can do a DOT all
technically and this would work right it
would grab all the posts who have an ID
of whatever ID we passed in however
there's one little issue with doing it
like this and that is that once it finds
one post it's going to keep looking
through all of the posts to see if
there's any other ones but we know that
only one post can have this specific ID
so it's a waste of uh post's resources
to continue looking when we know there
should only be one so anytime you know
there should only be one instead of
doing a DOT all it's better to do a DOT
first so so it's going to find the first
instance and going to return that so
it's going to save us some little time
it's going to be a little bit more
efficient in that case all right let's
save this and let's try this again and
let's see if this
works all right it looks like it worked
we got a post back no errors so I think
everything is good to go um let's go
back to our postc database we do see
that there's one with an idea four so it
seems to work but let's test this out
with an a random ID of like
666 and we should get the 404 so looks
like that's all we need to do when it
comes to fetching an individual post and
I'll remove this print statement we
don't need that anymore and then we can
just conclude this
video all right so let's move on to
handling our delete path operation so I
will comment out the SQL code once again
and then we're going to make sure that
we pass in the database dependency into
our path operation function
and so for our delete operation what
we're going to do is I'm going to do a
query and this query is going to look
exactly like this query so I can
actually copy this one in this
case so all we're doing is we're
grabbing um the posts model and then
we're going to filter based off of ID so
we're going to look for the ID of the
post that we want to delete and I'm
actually going to remove this first so
I'm going to save the query by itself
and we'll save this as a
postore
query I'll just save it as post it's
okay we'll understand that that's a
query and not an actual
post and then our if statement to check
if there actually is a post with that
what we're going to do is we're going to
say
if post dot how do we actually run this
query well we do first so that's going
to query it and so if this returns back
nothing then we're going to raise a 404
so really we haven't done anything
different from what we did here
however uh if it does exist so outside
of this if
statement I'll do a
post.
delete and then we'll just say uh
synchronize session equals uh false I
believe that's the default uh config
anyways uh I don't want to spend too
much time going over this uh it doesn't
really matter too much but if you want
to read about it um just take a look at
the documentation and if you go under
you know session basics you could see
them kind of describe all of them but
this option is the most efficient and
reliable so I just went ahead with that
one and it seems to work just
fine so this is going to delete the post
but remember to actually make changes we
have to do a db.
commit so that'll delete it and then um
everything else should and can remain
the
same I'm going to go back to my post
database we're going to delete uh post
with the ID of six so we'll go to our
our Postman we'll go to our delete
operation and then we'll do an ID of
six all right seems to work but let's
double check with
postgress right and now we can see that
there's no longer a post with an ID of
six and then let's test this out with a
random post number that doesn't exist we
should get a 404
perfect okay so it's time to tackle our
final path operation which is for
updating posts this is one's going to be
fairly similar to you know deleting a
post uh or even getting a post by a
single ID so first of all comment out
the previous postgress
code and because we're going to be
interacting with the database let's make
sure we copy the dependency in this
case and then what we're going to do is
we're going to do the same thing we're
going to say db.
query I'm going to query models.
poost and then we're going to filter on
the same thing we'll say filter
models.
poost do ID and if that equals to the ID
that we're passing here then we're going
to find the specific post we're
interested in so I'll say I'm going to
save this as postore query so right now
uh we're not actually running the query
we're just saving the query because I
haven't run first.
all and we'll say the actual post equals
postore query.
first so this is going to grab the post
if it exists uh if it doesn't exist so
say if post does not equal none or if
post equals equals none then we're going
to send a 404 however if it does
exist then we'll we'll grab the query
again we'll say post query.
update so we can chain an update method
so we're basically taking this query
right here and then we're chaining the
update method which would be the of
doing an update right
here so say do update and then what we
want to do is we want to pass in the the
fields that we want to update as a
dictionary so in this case what I'm
going to do is I'm going to hardcode the
values in just to show you what that
looks like so we'll say title is going
to be set to hey this is my updated
title and then the next one's going to
be the content we can update that to be
whatever we want and I'll say um this is
my up updated
content then we're going to do that same
synchronized session equals false as the
second uh property into the updated
method go to synchronize session equals
false and that should handle the update
and then we just want to do a db.
commit and right now this updated post
doesn't exist anymore so we're just
going to return uh successful or
something doesn't matter we're going to
change this a little bit later
on all right so let's go to our uh
update where is our update post it
doesn't really matter what data we pass
in because we're hardcoding the values
and so I'm going to update a the post
with an ID of one if it still exists and
it looks like it does so you can see
right now the title is new post so we'll
update this send says successful and
then let's go to back to postest do a
query and we can see that hey look it
got updated hey this is my updated title
and the content this is my updated
content so that's all we have to do we
just have to pass in a python dictionary
with the updated
fields and so instead of passing it a uh
python dictionary right we can pass in
our post schema right so that's going to
have all of the updated fields and we
can just say post. dict that's going to
return a python dictionary so that
should be exactly what we're looking
for and then finally when it comes to
returning data what we're going to do is
we're going to uh run another query so
we're going to say postore query so
we're going to grab this exact query
object right here and then we're just
going to get the
updated post so we just grab the first
one with that specific ID uh and then it
should return that so hopefully you guys
understand uh and I'm just going to
quickly recap exactly what we did we set
up a query to find uh the post with a
specific ID then we're going to actually
grab that specific post so we run that
query by grabbing do first if it doesn't
exist we're going to run a 404 um but if
it does exist then we can change the
update method to the same query object
so that we can update it and we pass in
the fields that we want to update we'll
commit it to our database then after all
of that's done we want to make sure we
get the updated post and send it back to
the user so we do postore query.
first so let's test this out and I'm
going to put in values because these
values now matter and I'll say um my
name is saniv
python is fine so let's try
this what happened here okay I forgot to
save it send we get an error and I
realize we have a little bit of an issue
so uh this the schema that we get uh
where we extract all of the body Fields
is named post but then we also save this
as post as well and so this leads to uh
issues because they're both named the
same thing and so I'm trying
to I'm trying to convert this to a
dictionary which only works on the
pantic model it does not work on our SQL
Alchemy model so we're going to have to
rename
these I'm going to name
this updated unor poost and then here
this is going to be updated
poost now let's try that again
seems to work let's check our database
though and we can see that it was
successfully updated and then let's try
to update something that doesn't
exist and we get a 404
perfect before we proceed any further I
do want to provide some clarifications
on what are the difference between a
schema or pedantic model uh and our orm
or SQL Alchemy model and I think it's
important that you guys understand that
and I do realize that there could be
potentially some confusion as to what's
the difference between them uh
ultimately what are they trying to
accomplish and why do we have both of
them so I've created a couple of slides
and hopefully that helps sort things out
hope and hopefully it provides a little
bit of clarification if you guys were
confused at that um but just to look at
our code you'll notice that in our
main.py file we have one class called
post here and this is extending base
model which actually comes from the
pantic library and you can see we're
importing pantic right here so this is
what's referred to as our schema uh and
uh we also have our and I don't even
want to explain it yet um
hopefully you guys already know what it
is but I have a couple slides that
hopefully make it a little bit more
clear but just to kind of show you where
this is being referenced it's being
referenced in our path operations so if
you go to you know our create posts
which wherever that is right here uh you
can see that we're passing that in right
here and then saving into a variable
called post so we're referencing it
right here um this is all about defining
the shape of a
request uh and so that's the pantic
model uh the other model is the one that
we have in models.py which is the SQL
Alchemy model so this SQL Alchemy model
defines what our database our specific
table looks like um but let me pull up
the slides just to show you guys uh you
know with some nice diagrams so
hopefully you guys get a better idea of
what that is all right so let's start
off by going over the schema models or
the pantic model so the schema or the
pantic model defines the structure of a
request and a response uh and so uh that
way you know when it comes to creating a
post we can Define exactly what the
request should look like so when we
create a brand new post we need the user
to provide What's the title of the post
what's the content of the post and
optionally they can also provide if it's
published or not but we've provided a
default value so they don't actually
have to send that so what we do is we
take the request and then we pass it
through the pantic model the pantic
model will uh perform a little bit of
validation to make sure that all the
fields that we need to actually create a
brand new post are there uh and that
they are of the proper type so if it's a
title it shouldn't be an integer and if
it's uh uh the published property it
shouldn't be a string or anything it's
just a simple Boolean so that's what the
pantic model or the schema model does
it's just there to provide some
validation to ensure that the body all
the data fields provide in the body of a
request match up to what we want and
that's important because we don't ever
want to give the clients which is the
web browser or the mobile phones or
anything like that uh freedom to do
whatever they want we want to tell them
exactly what we need for each specific
path or route and that's for the request
however uh we can also do this for the
response and we haven't actually done
that yet but we can actually Define
exactly what the response should look
like so you know as our um as our models
get more complex as uh our database gets
more complex there's going to be a lot
of fields when it comes to your posts
and your users that you may not want to
send back to the client when we send a
response so we can actually Define a
model to dictate fast API exactly the
data fields that we should be sending
back and so that's what your schema and
your pantic models do they just ensure
that the request and response are shaped
in a specific way now the other model is
the SQL Alchemy model so this is the one
that we've been working on with the past
couple of lectures right and these are
responsible for defining The Columns of
our posts table within postgress right
so it's going to Define all the
different attributes within a specific
table and then we use that post model to
perform queries to our database we use
it to create delete and update entries
within our database um but this model is
fundamentally different than the panding
model so that's why I created this video
I just wanted to make sure that you guys
understood what were the differences
between those and understand why we need
them both technically we don't need the
identic models but um you know when it
comes to building out apis you want to
be as strict as possible when it comes
to what kind of data can we receive and
send to the user and so pantic just
ensures that uh you know everything just
matches up with what we
expect so in the last video I described
the difference between a pantic model
and a omm model and uh there's a couple
things I actually want to do with our
pantic model so we've just got one right
here where we Define what a requ what a
post should look like uh and we use that
in a couple of places uh so if we go
down to create post we can see we use it
there so it's going to define the
structure of the data that we receive
from the front end when we want to
create a post and I think we also
provide it for um maybe updating and
post yep we also use it for updating a
post as well so what I'm going to do is
I want to create the schemas or I want
to move the schema in this case remember
this is what's referred to as a schema I
want to move that to its own file just
so that we don't clutter up our main.py
file so I'm going to go under app I'm
going to do new file and I'm going to
call this schemas py
and then within schemas if I go to my
main.py file I'm just going to cut this
out and we can paste it in here and
there's going to be a couple things that
we have to import uh so if we go to our
main.py we definitely need pantic that's
really all we need actually so if I go
there and then paste that into there we
should have no issues and then you know
this is going to actually break our
application because uh we need to
actually import this specific schema so
if I go into Main
py uh we can see here I'm doing from.
import models so that's going to import
everything from the models file but we
can also then import schemas as well and
so now to actually access this specific
class post we just have to go in our
main.py file and the reference schemas
dopost and so anywhere we use post uh
which should be right here we can
do schemas
dopost and then in our update post as
well we can do the same thing this is
going to be schemas dopost because now
we're importing it from another
file and what I'm actually going to do
is we're going to restructure this a
little bit so what I'm going to do is
remember these are regular python
classes uh and so we get all of the
abilities that we have when it comes to
inheritance uh when you come when it
comes to working with these classes so
what I'm going to do is uh we could
Define a couple things right we could
have one for uh we could create a class
for create post actually that should be
capitalized so create
post and then that's going to extend
base model and then this is going to
have all the fields that we need from
the user when it comes to creating a
post and so that's what this would be in
this
case and then remember we also need to
handle updating posts uh and so we could
create another model for
that so in this case I could call it
update post
and once again that's going to extend
base model H when it comes to the the
fields that we use for an update post uh
it would be the same exact thing right
whoops that should
be right here and I don't know why it's
keep doing
that and in this case there wouldn't be
a default value for
published because we want them to
explicitly provide each
column uh and so at this point right we
could then have two different classes
for each specific request and that's a
perfectly valid use case because when it
comes to creating they should provide a
certain amount of fields and then
updating it might be completely
different right because um you know
let's say in our application we wanted
to make it so that the user can't ever
update a post they can only update one
property and that's the publish so they
can just change whether it's published
or not we could remove this and this is
going to make it so that the user isn't
allowed to provide any other fields they
can only P um pass the published field
so that's why we would want to create
different um models uh for each of the
different
requests but what I like to do is
instead of having uh one for create post
one for update post uh and then one for
the you know we have to eventually
create models for the response what
we're going to do is we're actually
going to delete all of this and we're
going to create a class called post base
so I'll do class post
base and then base model and so this is
a regular class we can just copy all of
these
fields and then we can extend that class
so I can take this post base class and I
can extend it and say class post
create I want to extend post base we can
say post base and so it's going to by
default automatically inherit all of
these fields and so we can just say uh
for creating we can just say pass which
means it's just going to accept whatever
post bases so post create is essentially
the same thing as post
base but then we can create a brand new
one called uh class I don't know post
update and that's going to extend post
base and we can say that uh for
updating uh we can pass in whatever
specific fields we want to add in as
well so that gives us flexibility
because we can make use of inheritance
so for now I'm going to remove post
update and we're just going to keep it
as post create
um because uh you know updating and
creating is going to be fundamentally
the same uh and that way we can just
kind of piggy back off of this post Bas
model and then just create brand new
models based off of this so what I'm
going to do is go into my main.py file
and then for schemas actually let me
save
this then my main.py file there's no
longer a post it's going to be post
actually it's going to be create po post
create I'm going to do the same thing
for update as well
that was the update actually so then the
other one is for create post and then
this is going to be schemas
do Post
create all right and then the last thing
that I want to do in this video is we're
going to just delete this test route
that we had defined when we were
learning about SQL Alchemy we don't
really need that
anymore and then in the next video what
we're going to do is we're going to
tackle sending a response
back right and as I mentioned within the
slide deck right just like we can Define
what a request should look like we can
also Define exactly what a response
should look like so we're going to do
the same thing we're going to define a
penic model for a response for what a
post should look like when we send it
back to the user so that uh it stricks
to a very specific schema and then we
don't end up sending data that we don't
actually need to send to the
user in this lecture we'll take a look
at how we can define a ptic or schema
model to define the exact shape of a
response because right now if you
actually see uh any of our uh path
operations what we do is we just return
a post or multiple posts or an updated
post uh and whatever data we get back
from the post we just send it back to
the user and there may be times where
maybe you don't want all of the
properties or all of the attributes and
columns from our post table to get sent
back to the user because um you know
potentially that could be sending him
back information he shouldn't know about
uh especially when it comes to you know
like your your user account right when a
user logs in we don't want to send him
back his password he already knows his
password we don't want to continuously
transmit uh information like that so
there can be times where you do want to
remove certain fields or properties and
before we actually get to performing
that we're going to do a little bit of
cleanup because if we go to really any
one of our requests like if I go to get
post and hit send uh you see that we
have you know within data we then have
the list or array of all of our posts
and then if we look at create posts
right you can see we always have data
and then the actual post I'm going to
get rid of the data field just because I
think it's unnecessary and it kind of
clutters things so what we'll do is uh
within all of our path operations we're
going to just remove
data and instead of returning you know a
dictionary we're just going to return
posts and so it so fast API will
automatically be able to serialize that
and convert that into
Json and I'm going to do that for all of
these we're just going to remove that
data keyword for all of
them we don't need to do it for delete
but we do need to do it for
update and so now if we actually take a
look at what this is going to look like
if I hit send you can see we just get
back the post and we don't get that data
keyword same thing for get post what
does that look like perfect so we don't
have the the data keyword now let's
actually
Define what the response should look
like and we do that with our schemas we
do that with our pantic models just like
we have a pantic model for creating
posts which happens to just inherit from
post Bas so post create is just saying
that we expect a title expect a Content
published as optional and if you don't
provide one it's true and so we already
know how to work with that let's create
a brand new class for the response so
you know this handles the direction of
the user sending data to us and now we
want to handle us sending data to the
user so I can create a brand new class
we can call this post response uh or we
because it represents the response or we
can just call it post it doesn't really
matter I'm going to call it just post
and then we're going to extend base
model because all of our pantic models
have to end based
model uh and then from here what we have
to do is we have to specify all of the
fields that we want uh in the response
so we want to send back the title
because that makes sense so we'll send
back the
title we'll send back the content which
is going to be of a type string and then
um we'll send back published as well
which is going to be a
Boolean and let's see what that looks
like all right so this still looks
exactly the same as
uh the other ones but if you actually
see right now for any of the one
requests that we sent we get back the
ID as well as the created at field but
since we didn't include those two fields
we shouldn't actually send it back to
the user so let's actually try this
out and so I'm going to save this and
then to actually Define the response
model under a specific request we'll
start off with um uh we'll start off
with the create request or create post
and then within the decorator we just
pass in another field and this is called
response model and then you can just let
vs code automatically select it and then
here we just reference schemas Dot and
then the name of the class so let's try
this out and let's see what
happens so now if I create a post okay
we get a 500 air and let's see what
happened uh it says value is not a valid
dict so it's it looks like pantic is
saying that you know when we try to send
the response uh the the data we got back
was not a valid dictionary right and
because pantic the pantic class works
with dictionary it takes a dictionary
and then converts it to that specific
model so what exactly happened here why
is this causing an error well if you
look at the
documentation and where is it right here
and if you go under um SQL relational
database it says that for your models
your pantic models we have to add this
extra config called class config orm
mode true and it explains exactly why we
need that right because by default the
penic model will only read it if it's a
dictionary right and that's what it's
expecting in our code because we see
that error it's not a valid dictionary
and that's because when we actually make
this query right new post this is
actually not a dictionary it's a SQL
Alchemy model and so pantic has no idea
what to do with the SQL Alchemy model it
only knows how to work with dictionaries
so we have to tell it to actually
convert this SQL Alchemy model to be a
pantic model and we do that by passing
in this specific text right here so this
is going to say or mode true this is an
OM model and it's going to tell pantic
to you know ignore the fact that it's
not a dictionary and go ahead and
convert it so we can just copy this
text and add this to our
code for our post
model and that should be properly
indented so now that should be good and
let's see if we still get an error now
let's hit send look at that we got it it
seems like everything worked okay 2011
created but take a look at the fields
that we got back we just got title
content published and that's because our
model explicitly specified title content
published now we know if we go to our
postc database we do have an ID field
and a created ad field so if we wanted
to add those
we can say um ID which is going to be of
a type
int let's save that and let's see what
that looks
like right now we get the ID back
perfect well do we want the created at
time I think you know your front end
code probably wants that as well so
let's go ahead and add that so here
we'll do created
at now what should the type for created
at be right it is ultimately you know a
date and time well we can we could do
you know something like a string but uh
what we can do that's better than that
is we can import from date time import
date time and so now we can say that the
time the created at is going to be of
type date
time and so this is an extra little bit
of validation to make sure that what we
send back is a actual valid date time
just make sure that you import it on in
this file and so now if I send this back
we now get created that as well right
right so this is how we ultimately
Define the data that we send back we can
specify exactly the fields we want and
that way we can ensure we don't
unnecessarily send data that shouldn't
be getting
sent right and we can do this with
anything I can just send back the ID if
I really wanted
to now we just get the ID right you see
there's a lot of flexibility and a lot
of power uh when it comes to defining uh
your responses just like we had when it
comes to defining our requests and with
apis like I always say make sure you
explicitly Define the exact data you
want to receive and the exact data you
want to send back to the client now
before we move any further and wrap up
this video uh you'll see that there's a
lot of duplication right because this
post model for the
response right it needs title content
published and then we're just adding ID
and create at right and like I said when
it comes to a real application you're
going to have so many more field so many
more columns it would be such a pain to
have to repeat both of them and so
that's why I ultimately created this
postbase class because I can extend the
postbase
class and what that's going to do is
that's going to cause me to inherit the
title content and publish Fields because
they're already defined in
here and so I can just remove
that and so then I can just specify ID
and create it at and then it's going to
inherit the other three from the
previous class and so now if I try this
again
I send it you can see that I get the
same exact result but I only had to
specify the new columns I wanted to add
in the
response so this is really no different
than you know working with any other
model in Python we get access to all of
the uh usual features like inheritance
so we can help reduce the amount of code
that we actually
write all right and so now let's go
ahead and uh update all of the other uh
path operations as well because we can
see that we only did for create post but
let's go ahead and do it for get an
individual post so this is going to be
the same exact response
model and we can just reference schemas
dopost and we'll do the same thing for
our update post as
well we'll say response model
equals schemas
dopost and then let's just you know
double check so get one post this should
work just fine perfect uh and then
update
post and it looks like that works as
well and the last thing that we need to
do is get all posts right so right now
if we do get all
posts now where is that right here we
still haven't send that so let's do
response model equals and then we can
say schemas
dopost and then let's try that out we
hit send we get an error and this is
expected and I want you to stop and
whoops I want you to stop and think
about what exactly is happening because
we are returning a list of
posts and it's trying to shape that into
one individual post right we got a list
of posts we should be sending back a
list of our schema post so how do we do
that can we just put a could we just put
a bracket or something like that will
that
work let's try this well it looks like
there's an error so this doesn't seem to
work so how can we specify we want a
list of posts well we have to import
something from the typing Library so we
have optional from the typing Library we
can also import list and so now if I go
back to our get posts I can say list and
so now if I hit send we should get back
all of our posts so here we're just
specifying we want a list of our
specific schema post
model and that's just going to allow us
to get a list of posts very
simple in the next couple of sections
we're going to focus on creating user
functionality and what I mean by that is
having users be able to actually create
an account within our app uh being able
to log in as well as being able to
create posts that are associated with
their specific account and so the first
thing that I want to tackle is uh
handling user
registration so we need to be able to
provide a way for users to create a
brand new account and the first thing
that we have to do is we have to to uh
Define our model or more specifically we
have to create a table within our
postris database that's going to hold
all of our user information and so since
we're using SQL Alchemy we're going to
create a new uh om model just like we
did for post so that we can Define what
our postris table ultimately looks
like let's create a new class and I'm
going to call this class
user and this is going to extend base
that's just a requirement for any SQL
Alchemy model and then here we're going
to provide the table name uh within
postgress so I'm going to say the table
within postgress should be called
users then let's go ahead and figure out
what are the different columns that we
need uh and so we're going to handle
registration um by having the user
provide a email address so we should
have a column for us to be able to store
their email so we'll say
email equals column this is going to be
of a type
string and we're going to say that this
is uh nullable is set to
false so they have to provide an
email and then on top of that we
shouldn't allow someone uh with an with
a specific email to register twice with
that email right there should only be
one account with one specific email so
we're going to say that the unique
constraint is set to true so that's
going to prevent one email from
registering twice
the next thing that we need is for us to
be able to store the user's password so
we'll create a column for password this
is once again going to be a
string uh and then once again the
nullable is going to be set to false
because we shouldn't be able to let them
create an account without a
password and we don't need a unique
constraint because I don't care if two
users have the same password it's up to
them and then finally just like we had
with the posts uh class we're going to
have a column for ID so every user is
going to have a unique ID so I'm just
going to copy and paste
that and so at this point I think that's
all we need for our user class if you
save it um it's going to reload the
application and it looks like I got an
error and I realized this should not be
uh St Str this should actually be string
that's my
mistake and then actually before we do
anything else I want to create it at
column as well so we can just copy this
and then paste that in there like I said
pretty much anytime you create something
in your database you want to make sure
that um you record when it was created
you never know when you'll need that
information and so we've restarted our
application let's go to postgress and
under my tables I'm just going to do a
refresh and it looks like it went ahead
and created our users table and if we do
a users properties we should see that it
created all four columns and all of the
necessary constraints should be set
there as
well and so let's uh you know just play
around with this in postrest just to
make sure it works um because I don't
really trust SQL Alchemy ever so let's
do right click and then we'll do view
edit data so right now there shouldn't
be any users and let's create a new user
so I'll say this is H John
gmail.com password I you know just put
whatever you want for now and then if we
save that right it then successfully
created a user we got the the generated
ID as well as the created at timestamp
and then let's create a new user so I'm
going to use the same exact email so
this should throw an error because we
shouldn't be able to register again you
know some random
password and then if I try to save this
we should get a unique constraint on
users's email error so perfect so that
worked and I'm just going to change this
to be Cindy
gmail.com we'll save that and it should
create those users so
perfect so we've got the first step done
when it comes to um defining our table
the next thing that I want to do is we
will create a uh New Path operation so
that a user can actually send his
username and password to our API and
then we can actually generate that
user just like we did with posts we're
going to create a new path operation for
creating a new user so we'll go to the
bottom of our main
document and I'm going to create a new
function I'll say we'll call
this create user
and so just like we have for creating a
post I'm going to copy this decorator
and we'll rename
it so it is going to be a post request
but it's going to be sent to the URL of
users because we're no longer working
with posts and keep in mind you get to
select whatever URL or path you want to
use if you want to call this I mean it's
bad practice to call it create user
um but you can choose whatever you want
I just I think it makes sense to call it
users and anytime you create something
remember the status code should always
be the default 2011 and I'll get rid of
the response model for now just to keep
things
simple now we're ultimately going to be
using our database to create a brand new
user so let's go ahead and copy this DB
right here from all of the other path
operations because that's going to have
to go in there
and then anytime we want to you know
receive data from the user because the
user is going to have to send the email
he wants to register with as well as his
password in the body of the request it
always makes sense to define a specific
schema so that we can ensure that the
user does provide both of those so just
like we did with post we're going to
create a brand new
schema and I can call this user or we
can call this
user I think this one it makes sense to
call this user create so this is going
to handle just for creating users
and we're going to inherit from base
model and for the user create there's
going to be an email field which is
going to be a
string as well as a password field which
is going to be of a type
string and when it comes to validating
the user right it's going to check to
make sure that an email is provided and
a password's provided however we can get
a little bit more granular than that if
you actually go to the pantic
documentation we also have a field
called email string so this is going to
validate that the email property is a
valid email however we need to have the
email validator Library installed but
that should automatically have already
been installed for us when we installed
fast API with the all flag and so if you
do a pip
freeze right we should be able to see
that we have our email validator already
installed uh if you don't have it
installed for some reason just go ahead
and do a pip install email Val validator
and that should install that
library and so what we'll do is from the
pantic library we're going to
import email
string and then we can say this is going
to be email uh of type email string so
that's going to ensure that this is a
valid email and not just some random
text then back in our main.py
file just like we did before we can say
user and then this is going to use
schema. userc
create uh and so the email address and
the password is going to be stored in an
object called user there going to be a
pantic uh object as well and uh if you
forgot how to save data to uh the
database or create something uh with SQL
Alchemy just go ahead and take a look at
the create posts and we can essentially
just copy
this and we're just going to rename a
few things
we'll say new
user and then we're going to grab model.
user
now and then once again what we want to
do is we want to take the user that we
get back from here from our schema we
want to convert it to a dictionary and
then unpack that dictionary then we're
going to add it to our
database we're going to commit it then
we're going to refresh it so we see the
brand new user
and then we can go ahead and just return
new
user all right let's give that a
shot and then within our uh Postman we
can right click on this select add
request we're going to name this create
user this is going to be a post
request and then in the body we'll go to
Raw once again and then Json
and then here we can pass in the
email we'll give it some random email so
I'll call this Carl
gmail.com and then
password this will
be password one
two3 all right and then for the URL just
copy
posts and then here we'll just change
this to users
all right so let's give this a shot
let's see if this
works and it looks like it worked right
we got the email we got the password
back we got the created app and we've
got an ID but just to double check like
we always do go ahead and go to your
users table select query tool select
star from users now because we're now
querying no longer the post table we're
querying the users table if I run this
we can see that we do get the new email
that we created or the new user that we
created with Carl
gmail.com now as a quick test just to
make sure that email validator works uh
I'm going to change this and we'll just
say some random text this is obviously
not a valid email so let's see if it
properly creates that user and it looks
like our scheme of validator worked and
says value is not a valid email address
so you can see the powerfulness of the
penic library being able to
automatically check to see if that's a
valid email address all right but one
thing I didn't like about creating the
user is that if we change this back to a
valid email I'll say we just call this
new user
gmail.com we create that user you see
that he gets his password back now why
in the world would he want to see his
password back there's no reason to ever
send the password back to the user at
any
point uh and so one of the things I want
to do is I want to Define our response
model so that we never send back the
user and I think you guys should already
be able to do that but we'll walk I'll
walk you through how to do that so let's
go our schemas we've got our user create
let's create our let's create a new
class and I'll call this um user out and
so this is going to be uh the shape of
our model when we send back the user uh
to the client that requested it it's
going to extend base model as
well and here we're going to send out a
couple things uh so there's going to be
an ID now the user should know his ID
email that's going to be of email string
again
and then we'll just leave out password
so by leaving out password we won't ever
send it back but just like we did with
the post model remember this is going to
be a SQL Alchemy um model that we get
and we need pantic to convert it to a
regular pantic model so we need this
config right
here and then in our path operation we
can set the response model to be scheme
m. user
out all right and then now if I just
change the fields up a little bit create
a new
email you can see that we get the ID and
the email as well but there's no
password and that's exactly what we want
and so now you guys should be fairly
comfortable with um being able to define
a response model as well as an uh a
request model model so that you can pick
and choose whatever field you want one
last change I want to make is I want to
go ahead and just add the created at
field as
well and we can just copy this right
here so now just create another email
right and now we get the creative field
so we got all the fields that we want in
the last lesson we handled the logic for
creating a new user but for a lot of the
people that are familiar with security
I'm sure you guys may have had a little
bit of a heart attack because we did
something that's very very frowned upon
we took the user's password and we just
stored it as plain text within our
database and some of you might be
thinking well what's the problem with
that right it's in our secure database
well right our database is secure for
now but there are hacks there are things
that can happen you know these uh all of
these records could potentially get
leaked in some fashion and it's very
dangerous to just have a user's password
just stored in plain text like this that
anyone can read so when it comes to
working with passwords and databases
what you always want to do is you want
to Hash the password so we never store
the actual password in our database we
just store a hash of it so that if it
does get leaked well no biggie because
it's ultimately just a hash you can't
really reverse engineer that hash and
get the original password back so in
this lesson we're going to focus on uh
hashing the password when a user first
registers so that we never actually
store the raw password within the
database and within our fast API
documentation they have a good article
that kind of covers how to do that so if
you go under uh security and then oath
to with password it'll show you what we
actually need to do when it comes to
hashing so there's two libraries that we
need to
install right we need pass
lib uh and so that's going to kind of
handle the hashing but we need to
actually specify a specific algorithm
because passlib can work with different
algorithms one of the more popular ones
is bcrypt so we'll need two different
libraries we'll need the pass lib and
then the B library and we can just do
that by running pip install passlib
bcrypt so I'll just copy
this we'll go to our
application and I'm just going to run
that
command all right and then let's just do
a pip freeze just to make sure it got
installed and we see pass lib there now
and then do we see bcrypt and we see
bcrypt in there as well so we've got
both of the libraries that we need to
actually perform the hashing so let's go
to our main file and somewhere up up at
the top I'm going to import from passlib
do
context import crypto
context and then what we need to do is
some place below that we have to Define
this setting right here so we do PWD
context equals and then we reference
that crypto
context and then here we say schemas
equals
brackets
bcrypt and then we'll do
deprecated equals
Auto all right and so basically all
we're doing is and this should actually
be a
string uh all we're doing right here is
we're telling pass lib what is the
default hashing algorithm or what
hashing algorithm do we want to use in
this case we want to use is bcrypt so
that's all this is
doing now when we go to our user
registration down
here we have to do a couple
things and so before we actually create
the user we need to actually create the
hash of the
password so the first thing is whoops
that's we're not in JavaScript land
we're going to Hash the password
which can be retrieved from user.
password right because that's going to
be stored inside this object and so how
do we exactly do that well what we can
do
is all we have to do is reference that
password context right if you forgot
what that is just go all the way up to
the top that's this Command right here
so we reference password
context and we call the hash method so
that's going to perform a hash and then
we just pass in user.
password and then we can store this in a
variable called uh
hashed _
password and then what we're going to do
here is we're going to take the user.
password and we're going to set that now
to the new hashed password that's going
to update the pantic user
model and then at that point we can just
leave everything as is right so we
hashed the password so we got a hash and
then we stored it under user password
and then everything else can just be
kept the same so let's actually try this
out and let me just double check to see
there's no errors and there isn't so
let's create a brand new user and I'll
call this Mark atgmailcom
same password that's fine send it looks
like everything worked and then let's
just run this and then if you see that
most recent user you can see that we no
longer store the raw password we store a
hash of it and so that's going to help
it be a little bit more secure because
if it does leak then you know the
hackers will only get access to a hashed
password and they can't exactly uh
convert it back to the original password
that's the great part about hashing it's
a one-way Street we hash it we only get
the final password you can never put it
back into a function to convert it back
to a password now one thing I want to do
is I want to extract all of the hashing
logic and store it in its own function
so I'm going to create a new file I'm
going to call this utils.py these are
this file is just going to hold a bunch
of utility functions and what going to
do is I'm going to go to our main
file and I'm going to remove this line
or cut it and we're going to paste it
into my utils file and then we're also
going to cut this out and we're going to
move all of this logic into
here and then we're going to define a
function that we can call and I'm going
to call this function
hash and it's going to take a password
which is going to be of type
string and all it's going to do is it's
going to return PWD
context. of whatever the password the
user passes in and that way we uh really
extract and place all of the hashing
logic into one file or one function so
we don't have to import all of this
nonsense into other files and then in
our main.py file we can import
utils and then down here what we can do
is instead of calling this this I can
just call utils
do
hash and then we'll pass in the user.
password
again and this shouldn't really change
anything else in our
code let's try this again I'll create a
I'll just add a one here send seems to
work let's just double check and the
second user the password was properly
hashed the next thing I want to do is I
want to set up a route or a path
operation that allows you to fetch and
retrieve information about a user based
off of their ID and there's a couple of
different reasons why I want to do this
uh one of them is uh it can be part of
the authentication process so depending
on how you set up the front end uh if
you decide to you know set up JWT tokens
to get sent as cookies uh then the front
end may not actually know whether it's
logged in or not and so a lot of times
you'll see some apis have an endpoint to
let you kind of retrieve information
about your own account uh and so if
you're able to access it that means
you're logged in if you're not then um
you know that you need to fetch a new
token uh also there's other reasons why
you want to do this too uh you know if
you're you know thinking taking a look
at something like Twitter right you need
to retrieve a user's profile if you want
to view it and so uh in your API you're
going to have to set up a route so that
people can retrieve someone's profile
information uh and so that's why I want
to set up this route I haven't really
decided what we're going to ultimately
do with it but for now I just want to
set it up so so that you can retrieve uh
information about a specific user based
off of their ID let's go to the bottom
of our code here and we'll Create A New
Path
operation and I'll call this a get
user and before we do that I'm also
going to set up The Decorator so this is
going to be a get operation because
we're going to treat the information
about a specific
user and the specific path is going to
be slash users and then
slid so kind of like how we did when it
comes to retrieving a specific post
we're going to pass in the ID in the URL
and then we have to extract the
ID and I'm going to make sure that we uh
validate it as an integer and the next
thing that we have to do is since we're
going to be interacting with the
database we need our DB right here so
we'll copy
that and then in our uh actual function
we're going to do a quick query so we'll
do db. query and then we'll grab models.
user
and I'll say I want to
filter uh and then look for something
with models. user. ID equals equals and
then it's going to match up with the ID
that they
requested and because there should only
be one user with a specific ID we're
going to just grab the first one so we
don't spend extra resources looking
through the rest of our
database and we're going to store this
in a variable called
user all right and then uh just like we
did for fetching a specific uh post if a
user was not found so if not
user we'll say we want to raise an HTTP
exception and we'll say the status code
equals 404 whoops
HTTP status Dot and then we'll grab
404 and the detail is going to be
user with ID and we'll pass in the
ID does not
exist but if the user is properly
found we will return the
user and it looks like there's some kind
of weird issue with my formatting so all
right there we
go and so let's just quickly test this
out so once again I'm going to create a
new request and we're going to make sure
to save this one and I'm going to call
this a get user
copy this URL it's going to be the same
same route it's just going to be a get
operation and then we want to send a
specific ID so uh take a look at your
database and then see if you can grab uh
an ID that does exist so we'll just say
one we'll hit
send and it looks like there's some kind
of issue because I'm not getting a
response yet but let me cancel out of
that and let's see what we did wrong
and I realized I forgot to do
app.get great so we actually got the
user everything seems to be working
however there's one little
issue uh first of all we should not be
getting the password right we never want
to return the password to the user the
user already knows his password and uh
also if you want to if this route is so
that you can retrieve a user's profile
uh kind of like you can on Twitter
Instagram then we're sharing someone
else's password and that's a little bit
of an issue uh and the reason why this
isn't a hashed password was because I
didn't clear out my database uh before
we implemented the uh the hashing uh of
the password so that's why it's in clear
text but whether it's hashed or not you
never want to send this out right you
don't want anyone else to see your
password you don't even want the user to
see their own password because someone
else could intercept it and potentially
do malicious activity with that
information so what we're going to do is
we're going to filter out that specific
field just the password field I want
them to be able to get the ID the
created at field and the email and any
other fields outside of the
password and fortunately for us if we go
to our schemas uh we've actually already
defined
a a schema for the user out so this is
going to be uh any information about the
specific user except we're extracting
out the specific password and so we can
just set the respon response model to be
user
out and we'll go back to main.py and
we'll say
response. model sorry response uncore
model equals
schemas do user
out all right we'll save this and we'll
try this again so we'll retrieve this
user and we still got the password so
what happened here
and this could just be an issue of me
not saving so let's try this again still
a little bit of an
issue and let's just make sure I
imported
schemas I did and let's go to our
schemas and I've set just these fields
so this should be good to go I'm not
sure why it's giving us errors and I
made a stupid mistake this should not be
uh within the function parameters this
should actually go in inside The
Decorator so it wasn't actually doing
anything and now if we try
this we can see that the password field
has been successfully
removed now that we've added a couple of
path operations for users if you take a
look at our main.py file it's starting
to look a little cluttered uh you'll see
that we've got all of our path
operations for uh you know handling cud
operations for posts and then you'll see
that we also have all of our uh path
operations for working with users so
that's creating users and so well as
retrieving a user by ID and uh you know
as I said this is a little messy and as
we keep adding more and more path
operations it just seems almost
unmanageable to keep everything in a
main.py file and instead what I want to
do is I want to break it out and I want
to create two separate files and one
file is going to be for all of the
routes or path operations that work and
deal with posts and then I want a
separate file that will handle all of
the path operations for working with
users and you know it's not quite as
simple as just uh you know moving these
path operations to different files we we
do have to learn about something
specific to fast API and this is nothing
unique about fast API you'll see that
every single web framework is going to
have a a way to kind of accomplish this
and it usually involves something called
routers so we'll take a look at routers
in this section and how we can use them
to actually split up all of our path
operations so that we can organize our
code a little bit
better and so what we're going to do is
we're going to create a new folder and
and I'm going to call this
routers and then within here I'm going
to create two files I'm going to create
one called post. py and I'm going to
create one uh that's called user. py so
all of our path operations uh dealing
with users is going to be put into this
file and all of our path operations
dealing with posts is going to be put
into this
file and what I'm going to do is we're
going to go to our main.py file and I'm
actually just going to copy all of my
specific rout that deal with posts
first we're just going to keep going up
and I went too far
up oh this thing moves quickly here we
go this is going to grab all of our
posts and I'm going to just cut that out
and we're going to just paste it in here
and there should be plenty of warnings
and errors within vs code that's to be
expected don't worry about that we'll
fix that in a bit I'm going to do the
same thing for the users so let's go to
our main.py file and just grab the last
two path operations that we have for
users and then paste it into this
specific
file right so we've got a bunch of
Errors uh and uh let's go ahead and
actually fix those first before we
actually start working with routers uh
and so now that all of the uh the path
operations are within these files we're
going to have to import uh you know
things like app we're going to have to
import well we'll come back to that
actually we'll have to import status
we'll have to import our schemas we'll
have to import the session object we'll
have to import all of our database
related things our utils so all of these
things that we see little squiggly lines
we have to import them um because we had
already imported all of these uh in the
main.py file and so we'll start off by
importing the models the schemas uh and
the UIL folder if we need it for one of
the specific files you'll see that we
only need this for the user file uh and
so the way we did it in our main. P file
is we say from and then this dot means
current directory so uh we say hey from
this current directory we're in which is
if I kind of close that out you can see
that everything is in the app file app
folder sorry we're saying from the
current APP directory I want to import
models which is right
here and then I want to import schemas
and utils however in our user. py file
and our post. py file uh the models
schemas and utils folder is not in the
same directory because we actually have
to go up a directory to the app folder
to access them so instead of doing one
dot if you want to go up a directory you
do two dots so that's all we have to
change so in our user. py file we'll say
from dot
dot import and we'll say
models schemas and
utils and so right there we cleaned up
some of our errors that we're getting
and let's see we also have to import
status from the fast API Library so what
we can do is we'll just go up here and
I'm just going to copy this
and right above this line we're just
going to paste that in there and the
last thing that we need to import is
from the database we uh from the
database. py file we're going to have to
import get DB and then from SQL Alchemy
we have to import session so if we go to
our main.py file again the SQL Alchemy
uh code right here we can just copy that
and I'm going to import that as
well that's done and then finally we
have the get DB and if we take a look at
our main. p y file the way we got that
is so we're saying uh from the current
database file we want to import engine
and get DB and keep in mind that the
database file is not in the router's
directory it's in the app directory so
we have to go up a directory to access
this file so we just put two dots pretty
simple so from do
database import get
DB and we actually don't need to import
uh engine uh we're going to leave that
here in our main.py file
all right so now that we got all of that
the last error that we see is that uh we
don't have access to the app object and
so your instinct is to go to our main.py
file and then import this and that's not
exactly correct instead what we're going
to do is we're going to make use of the
routers that I mentioned and so from the
fast API Library we're going to import
something called API first three letters
actually the first four letters API
router and then from here we're going to
make use of the API router object so
we'll say uh router
equals API
router so we're basically creating a
router object and then what we can do is
we can replace the keyword app because
we don't have access to that in this
file and we just use the word router and
you'll understand why we do this in a
bit so we've got those updated and then
we're going to do the same exact thing
for our post. py so we have to get all
of these Imports I'm actually going to
copy most of these because most of them
are going to apply here as well
uh the only thing we don't need uh utils
for sure so we'll remove that and then
uh you'll see that list is still getting
errored out and that's because if we go
to our main.py file that's coming from
this typing import so I'm just going to
copy
that and paste that in there and it
looks like we don't need optional
because it's kind of grayish and so
that's just vs code telling us that
we're not using it in this file and I
think that should clear up all the
errors except for once again uh the app
object and so we'll do the same thing
we'll say router equals API
router and then what we're going to do
is replace the word app with the word
router all right and then finally we
have to go to our main.py file and
actually make use of these routers
because you'll see that in our main.py
file there's no reference to anything in
here so our API won't work if we try to
run it now so in our main.py file what
I'm going to do is I'm going to say from
dot
routers so from this
folder we're going to import post and
user and there should be plural
routers and then I'm going to show you
some magic that we're going to do and so
above this route we're going to
say we're going to grab the app object
right this is once again our fast API
object that we kind of do everything
with and we're going to say
include
router and then we'll grab the
post. router right that's what we just
imported we imported post which is
coming from here and we're importing
this router object and so what we've
basically done here is uh I have
basically said as we you know when we
get a p when we get a HTTP request uh
you know before we had all of our path
operations in here instead what's going
to happen is you know we go down the
list like we normally do and so as we go
down our list this is our first uh app
object that we kind of reference and in
here it just says I want you to include
everything I want you to include our
post. router and so the request will
then go into here and it's going to take
a look at all of these routes and it's
going to see if it's a match right and
if it finds a match it's going to
respond like it normally does so that's
kind of how we break out our code into
separate files we use these router
objects and we can do the same thing
with the user. py so we're going to go
to Main and then here I'm going to type
out the same thing I'm going to say app.
include router and this time we use we
grab the user and then we do router
again and so once again all we're doing
is we're just grabbing the router object
from the user file and that's
essentially going to import all of the
specific
routes and so if we save our code and
then we just quickly take a look at the
the terminal just to make sure there's
no errors uh it looks like everything's
working let's test this out now so I'm
going to get all post let's see if this
works it looks like it works great uh
let's create a new post looks like it
works get one post uh well it looks like
that post doesn't exist anymore but if I
try one looks like it works I we'll
delete post with the ID of
three great we'll update
post create user just put in a new
unique email and then get user so grab
that user and we can see that every
single route works perfectly so we
didn't change the functionality of our
project at all in this video instead all
we did was we used a uh a router object
to be able to spit split up all of our
routes or our path operations into
different files and then we import them
just by calling app. include router and
then the specific router object of that
file and you'll see that our code looks
so much cleaner now and as our app and
our API continues to grow we can just
add new files into the routers folder so
that we don't continue to clutter up our
main.py file
in our two router files you'll see that
we use the same URL for almost all of
our specific paths uh and so you'll see
for the get route we'll use SL poost for
the Post we use SL poost uh from the get
specific post we do SL poost and then
the ID and then the same thing goes for
delete and uh and put as well and I
think it's kind of annoying having to
continuously a copy and paste the same
exact path when it's pretty much just a
copy from each one so is there a way we
can kind of kind of remove this
unnecessary it doesn't seem like that
big of an issue but keep in mind that
our API is very simple right other apis
could have very long
complex uh you
know uh routes that you know may not
look as simple as ours so they could
have you know multiple things right so
it could look something like that and
then having to kind of copy and paste
all of that every on every single route
can seem a little unnecessary and so
anytime you're working with routers what
we can actually do is we can pass in a
uh parameter into the API router um
function or method and so what we can
say is prefix and we're going to say
that since every single route in this
file always starts with SL posts we can
say prefix equals
slost and so now anytime you see a slash
post we can just remove
that and just put in a slash this just
going to be a
slash and then when it gets to SL poost
slid this this is where it gets a little
tricky but once again we just remove
everything but a slash and so what this
is saying is that we're going to take
slash posts and then we're going to
append it
with ID right because that's that's what
this is saying we're saying slid so it's
actually appending it with slid so the
final thing actually looks like it's
going to look like SL
poost ID so nothing actually changes
it's just a simpler way to do things so
that we don't have to write SL posts
every everywhere and so we can uh we can
remove this and just do SL ID and we can
just do SL ID here as well and we're
going to do the same thing in the users
file as well because both of them start
with SL users and so we're going to put
in a prefix
here and we're going to say
slash users so this can just be removed
to slash and this can be removed to just
slash ID all right and once again we're
going to test this out we're just going
to test a couple of routes so if get
routes get post work and if create oh
we'll try a get one post that works
perfectly and then let's try creating a
new user we have to give it another
unique email looks like it works and
then finally uh get user we're going to
try this again and it looks like it all
works so uh you know this is a
completely optional step it doesn't
change the functionality of things but I
think it does make it a little bit
easier to read um because we put the
prefix up here so that we don't have to
keep copying and
pasting now as I mentioned one of my
favorite features of fast API is the
automatic documentation that comes from
Swagger UI uh and so if you actually
navigate to the URL but just go to/ docs
like I have that's where you're going to
see the documentation and like I said
this is interactive documentation so you
can actually make requests from here so
you didn't technically have to use
Postman for a lot of things you can just
test it out right here and it's going to
do the same thing however I did also
want to teach Postman but the reason I
bring this up again is that uh you'll
notice how we've got a couple of routes
for dealing with posts and then we've
got a couple of routes for dealing with
users and then we've got this random
test one that we created when we were
first learning about path operations and
what I would like to do is I would like
to structure this documentation so that
uh instead of kind of grouping them all
together we can kind of group them based
off of uh the their responsibility so I
would like to create a group that
handles all of the post operations uh so
all of these five right here and then I
would like a separate group that handles
all of the user-based operations so that
it's a little bit easier for your
clients and your users to understand
what each one does by grouping them
accordingly uh based off of their
specific action and so I want to have a
group that actually is titled posts and
a group that's titled users so that when
they see that they say oh the user
section is going to be dealing with
users and the post section is going to
be dealing with posts uh and getting
this fixed or update and our code is
super simple with fast API so uh let's
go to our fast API go to our routers and
if we go to the post.
py uh to add a specific group name what
we call uh it's actually called a tag so
we say tags
equals we just say
posts and I forgot that comma right
there we're going to do the same thing
for users so we'll say tags
equals
users and you you can see that this is a
list so you can pass more than one um
but we'll save that and then I'm going
to refresh this page
and so now you can see that we now have
these little titles so that we can now
group our specific requests uh into
categories and so the readability of our
documentation has improved tremendously
with essentially one line of
code in this section we're going to
start tackling one of the most important
topics when it comes to building out an
API or really any application and that
is authentication now when you're
working with authentication on an API or
any application there's really two main
ways to tackle authentication there's
the session based authentication and the
idea behind a session is that uh we
store something on our backend server or
our API in this case to track whether a
user is logged in so there's some piece
of information whether we store it in
the database whether we store it in
memory that's going to keep track of if
the user has logged in and when the user
logs out so that's one way of doing
things the other way of doing things is
doing it uh is using JWT token based
authentication and the idea behind uh
JWT Authentication is that it's
stateless and what I mean by that is
that there's nothing on our backend
there's nothing on our API there's
nothing in our database that actually
keeps track uh or store some sort of
information about whether a user is
logged in or logged out uh we and you're
probably thinking well how do we know
that they're logged in well that's the
power of JWT tokens is that the token
itself which we don't store in our
database and we don't store in our API
uh it's actually stored on the front end
on our clients uh actually keeps track
of you know whether a user is logged in
or not and and when I first started
learning about jwt's it was a little bit
of a complex topic it seemed like there
were so many pieces that were in play
but then when you when I actually sto to
really understand it I realized it's one
of the simplest Solutions so hopefully I
can make this as easy as possible for
you guys I hope this doesn't end up kind
of confusing you like it confused me at
first it really is simple and there's
really only a couple steps but uh you
got to really understand what a JWT
token is and what we're doing on the
front end and the back end to make it so
that we can actually use it as an
authentication solution
solution so let's take a look at the
flow for how a user logs in how a user
is essentially authenticated and then
how a user accesses a specific path
operation resource or endpoint uh by
using the JWT token to ensure that the
API knows that we're logged in so that
we can actually provide him that
important information and so what's
going to happen is the client or the
front end whoever it is they're going to
try and log in so what we're going to do
is we're ultimately going to create a
path operation uh called login and and
the the client is going to pass the
username and they're going to pass in
the password so whatever their
credentials are so it doesn't
technically have to be username and
password it could be email and password
it can be uh whatever information that
you want so technically in our
application it's going to be email and
password because uh we don't have
usernames I guess uh we mostly just have
emails um but they provide their
credentials and so after we get their
credentials what we're going to do is
first of all we're going to create well
first of all we're going to verify if
credentials are valid right so if the
credentials are correct if the password
matches uh the if the username and
password match with the account we're
going to create this JWT token and we
haven't talked about what the JWT token
is so don't worry too much about it but
I've created an example token right here
and so you're probably thinking it just
looks like a bunch of gibberish and for
the most part it is so moving forward I
want you to think of this as nothing
more than just a string you know just a
regular string in Python that's kind of
fundamentally what it is uh but there's
a little bit more information embedded
in it but of it as a string from the
perspective of the client the client
doesn't know what the token is and it it
never cares really the only the API
cares what's actually in the token and
what it
means and so we'll send a response back
with the token and so now the client has
the token and so he can start accessing
uh resources uh that require
authentication so anytime he wants to uh
you know let's say our application
requires a user to be logged into
retrieve posts what he can do is he'll
send a request to the/ poost endpoint um
but he also provides the token uh in the
header of the request and you may not
know what the header of a request is but
I'll show you guys it's very simple you
can just think of it it's somewhere in
the payload of the request and so he
sends that and what the API is going to
do our fast API is first of all it's
going to verify the token is valid and
there's a couple of different steps
needed to actually verify if a token's
valid and we're going to cover that in
the next slide but just know that the
API just checks hey is this a valid
token and if it is well then he just
sends back the the data and that's it
right our authentication system is dead
simple you you provide your credentials
you get a token and then anytime you
want to access anything that requires
you to be logged in you just send the
token in the header and that's it so
hopefully this wasn't confusing
hopefully you guys see the Simplicity in
this solution the API doesn't actually
track anything there's no information
being stored on the API instead the
client just holds on to the token and he
provides it to us and if we verify that
the token's valid that's all we have to
do do so let's break down what exactly a
JWT token is and what are the components
that make up a token and so I've got an
example token right here and this is
kind of the same piece of text that we
saw in the previous slide uh and so it
once again just looks like a bunch of
cryptic characters just Jam together and
that's kind of what it is it looks like
it's encrypted but keep in mind it is
not encrypted this is important to
understand and we're going to make sure
I drive home this point it is not
encrypted um but the token itself is
made up of three individual pieces
the first thing is the header so the
header includes metadata about the token
uh and so we're actually going to sign
this token uh so we're going to think of
it almost like hashing the token uh and
so we have to specify the algorithm that
we're going to use so in this case the
default is hs256 so we've included that
in the metadata and then you can see the
type is set to JWT so this is a JWT
token so that's why the type has been
set so the metadata is going to be the
same for all of our tokens this is just
kind of fixed don't worry too much about
it it's not really that important we
don't really ever touch it now the
payload is a little bit more interesting
so the payload of a token is ultimately
up to you you can send absolutely no
payload you can send any piece of
information that you want to send uh
within the payload you can include
anything that you want however you want
to be careful with what you put in the
payload because uh it's important to
understand that the token itself is not
encrypted uh and so that means anybody
else in the outside world can take a
look at a token and they can see what's
in the payload so you don't want to put
any confidential information you want
you don't want to put any passwords or
Secrets or anything like that uh instead
you want to stick to some very basic
things so very common things that we put
in the payload are what is the ID of the
user right so when I log in right
normally our API is going to create a
token and then embed my user ID into the
token so that when I ask to get all of
my posts the the API will be able to
take a look at the token verify it's
correct extract to the payload and it'll
automatically know the ID of the user
that requests did this but we can
include other things we can include uh
the user's role so are they an admin are
they just are they a privileged user are
they a regular user um we can
technically include any information one
thing to keep in mind is that anytime we
need to access anything authenticated we
have to include this token so if we Jam
a lot of information in there well it's
going to increase the size of our packet
and that's going to be a waste of some
bandwidth so you don't want to jam too
much information just a couple of small
things here or there and then finally we
have a signature so a signature is a
combination of three things we've got
the header so we take the header that's
already in the token we take the payload
that's already in the token and then we
add our secret so there's a special
password that we're going to keep on our
API this is only on our API clients will
not know it no one else will know it uh
and it's probably the most important
thing to our whole authentication system
so you don't ever want this secret to
get out but we take those three things
the secret the header the payload and
then we essentially take that
information pass it into the signing
algorithm which is the hs256 and then
it's going to return a
signature and this signature is
important because we're going to use
this to determine if the token is valid
because we don't want anyone else
tampering with our tokens we don't want
them changing data you know I don't want
some user to log in and then just start
changing numbers in here to make it seem
like it's a different user because then
they can potentially access other users
information uh and so that's why we have
this signature it's just to make sure
that no one has uh tampered with our
specific token and so you know I just
want to drive home that same point first
of all there's no encryption so anyone
can see the data the signature is just
there for um data integrity and what
that means is no one has changed it that
means all the data that we have in there
is still what it should be no one has
messed with the data all right and if
you're still confused as to what a
signature is we're going to take a look
at how signature work why we use them
and how they ultimately help us detect
if someone changes uh any of the
information are token in the next slide
and then I think at that point you guys
will see it's not really a complex uh
concept and uh once you get that you'll
see that the whole authentication
process is fairly simple okay guys so
we're going to do a deep dive into why
we need the signature within the token
and you'll see this the slide may look a
little complex there seems to be a lot
of boxes a lot of things going on but as
soon as I explain this I think you guys
will see that it's not too complex of a
concept so let's break this down step by
step let's say a user has logged into
our application he sent our credentials
and our API has created the token and
it's in the process of sending it back
to the user so this is going to be our
token that we create on our API and it's
going to create it's going to have three
things the same three things we
discussed in the previous slide we've
got the header that's got all the
metadata it's got the payload right and
this is going to have whatever
information we want to put in the
payload and in this case we've decided
to embed the user's ID as well as his
specific um role uh in this case he's a
plain user he's not like an a special
privileged user or a staff user or an
admin he's just a regular user of our
application so he can only do very
specific things and then we have to
generate a signature and our signature
is going to be uh a combination of three
things it's going to be a combination of
our header and remember this header is
the same thing so even though our token
already has the header what we do is we
take that header we take the payload
with the specific pieces of information
we've included in there and then we
include finally our special super secret
password remember this password only
resides on our API servers no nobody
else has access to it our clients don't
have access to it the front end doesn't
have access to it only we have access to
it on our API server and this is very
important because this is the special
password that no one should ever have
access to and so we take all of these
three things we pass it into a hashing
function essentially and then we create
a signature and so we take these three
things and that's going to make up our
token and so we send that back to the
user now let's say that we've got a user
who decides that he wants to do a little
bit of shady things and he wants to kind
of hack our application and do some bad
things to our application ultimately and
so what he's figured out is say hey look
this token right it's not encrypted I
can see all the data I can see that I'm
a user and so what he's decided to do he
changed a few bits in The Token to make
it now read admin instead of user but he
could have really done anything right he
could have changed the ID so that it's
someone else's ID and he can potentially
have access to someone else's
information doesn't really matter but
he's changed a few things and so now
he's got a this token which has the
header signature and payload uh and he's
now a admin user or the payload says
he's an admin
user now the reason he can't actually do
this is because ultimately remember the
signature that's currently in the token
was generated by having a header the the
same header uh and then you pass in the
payload with this specific ID and a role
of
user and then you pass in the secret and
so this signature is no longer valid he
can't use this same signature because
it's not going to match up with the data
that he has so if we actually try to
create a signature from this it's going
to look different and so what he has to
do is he has to create a brand new
signature so that it matches the data
he's sending however he can't create a
brand new signature because he doesn't
have this super secret special password
this only resides on our API server and
so if he tries to create a brand new
signature he can only pass in the header
and this payload into the hashing
function to generate a new signature and
so that once again is not going to be a
valid signature because when he sends
let let's say he does create that
signature with only the header and the
payload and no secret well we now have
this token right that's made up of these
three things we send it to our API and
what our API is going to do is to verify
if the token is valid he does a super
simple test he takes the header he takes
the payload and he takes the secret and
he creates a test signature because
remember that's what we did in the first
place to actually create the original
token we take the header the payload the
secret and we pass it in to our signing
function uh and we pass it into our
hashing function create the signature so
we do the same thing and then we take
the signature in the token that was sent
by the user and we just compare them if
they don't match which they won't
because remember he doesn't have access
to the secret and since we use the
secret in our hashing function right the
signatures aren't going to match and we
know that this token is not valid so
this signature once again only ensures
that the data Integrity is still valid
that no one has tweaked any of the bits
no one's changed any of the data that's
all the signature can do it can just
verify that it hasn't been changed uh
since we created the token in the first
place but once again and I can't stress
this enough anybody can change the data
of a token anybody can see the data of
the token they just can't generate a
brand new signature because they don't
have access to the secret and so that's
why the password's so important because
that's how we ensure that the token
hasn't been manipulated or changed in
any way shape or form so hopefully that
made sense uh I didn't understand this
at first it took me a while to actually
grasp why we needed the signature I just
kind of was like I'll figure this out
later um but after a year or so I was
like oh this is actually a super simple
concept and hopefully I can do a
slightly better job of explaining it
than some of the documents that I read
when I was first learning it and
hopefully this kind of uh you know gets
rid of some of the unnecessary uh stress
that kind of comes with learning about
JWT based Authentication
so once again let's quickly take a look
at how we're going to handle logging in
the user more specifically how do we
actually verify that his credentials are
correct because it's not going to be
exactly the same way that you would
think so the user is going to uh hit the
login endpoint and he's going to provide
the email and the
password and I've colored the word
password in red because this password is
going to represent what the user is
trying to log in as this is his
attempted password that's what we're
going to call it and that's going to be
in red and keep in mind that when he
sends this this password it's in plain
text right it's just the regular
password that he typed out and so when
it gets to our API the first thing that
we're going to do is we're going to hit
our database to try to find the user
based off his email or his username and
the database is going to send back all
of the information about that user uh
which includes the password however if
you remember how we actually created the
password and stored in the database we
actually stored a p a hashed version of
the password in the database so that if
anyone hacks our database uh the user
passwords aren't actually in plain text
so no one can really hack their
passwords but this creates a a little
bit of a problem because we have the
attempted password uh for the login
attempt in plain text however we've got
the password in our database as a hashed
password so how exactly do we check to
see that they're equal uh because right
now a hashed password does not equal the
same as the regular password and your
first instinct is to hey well let's just
convert this back to a plain text
password and we can't exactly do that
because remember a hash is only one way
so if we Hash a password we can't get
the original password from the hash
that's what's great about hashing a
password uh and if you think you can do
that that's actually what I guess what
we would refer to as encryption but
we're hashing in this case so what do we
do uh to verify if the passwords are
actually equal it's pretty simple we
take the hashed password and then we
take the raw and once again this hashed
password is the the correct password in
our database then we take the password
attempt and we hash it again so we hash
this password and so then we get a
hashed password and so if we have the
correct password then if we put it
through the hashing function these two
should be equal uh and so if they're
equal that means the password they
provided us is the correct password in
the database uh if it's not the if they
don't match that means he gave us the
wrong password and so uh if they're
correct we'll then go ahead and send
we'll create a token first and then
we'll send it to the client so it's as
simple as taking the attempted password
hashing it and then comparing it with
the hashed password in the database
because if the passwords are correct
then the hash should equal the hash in
the database okay so we're going to
create the login path operation and what
I'm actually going to do is you're
probably thinking that we can just store
the path operation in the users. py
router however I think it would make
more sense to actually store this in a
authentication router so we're actually
going to create a brand new router for
this so that we can keep the user routes
versus the authentication routes in two
different files however if you really
wanted to you could store it all in one
file so I'm going to call this o. py and
the first thing that we have to do is
from the uh fast API we're going to
import a few things uh we're going to
import the API
router uh we're going to need
depends status HTTP
exception and maybe we need the response
I haven't
decided and then we're going to Define
our router so we'll say router equals
API
router and we're going to pass in a tag
you know just for the documentation so
we'll say tags equals
authentication all right and then we're
going to create our uh login so we'll
call this uh well first of all this is
going to be a post request because
remember the user is going to have to
provide his credentials so generally
when you want to send data in one
direction it's going to be a post
request and we'll send it to the login
endpoint you can call this whatever you
want you can call it authenticate
however I like login and then we'll
Define our function and I'll just call
this login as well and because we're
ultimately going to have to uh fetch the
user from the database we're going to
have to import uh our uh our database
session and so
from SQL Alchemy we'll
say. orm import
session and so we'll do the same thing
that we did with every other path
operation I'll say DB session equals
depends and then we're going to have to
actually import our get DB function so
from here we'll
do from and we have to go up
a a directory and I'll say database
import session sorry not session
um actually you know what I'm going to
do I'm just going to say from dot do
import database and then I can just
reference it as data database
do getor
DB right and since the user is going to
be providing the login information I
think it makes sense to set up a schema
so that we can ensure that they provide
the exact uh pieces of data that we
ultimately want and what we're going to
do is we're just going to create a new
class and I'm going to call this user
login and this will extend the base
model as
usual and the two pieces of information
that we want our
email which is going to be a string and
then we can do
password which is going to be a string
actually I'm going to I'm going to use a
email string like we did
before and then from our Offa py I'm
also going to import
schemas and here I'm going to store the
schema as a user credentials
this going to be schema. user
login all right and so now we can access
all the user information or the
attempted login information with the
user credentials variable and we're
going to make a request to our database
specifically our users table to retrieve
the user based off of his
email so we'll say db. query and we'll
and we have to import models now so that
we can access it we'll say models. user
and then we have to filter based off of
the
email we'll say models. user once again.
email equals equals
user credentials. email and then there's
only going to be one user with that
specific email so we'll do
first and we'll store this result in a
variable called user now if there's no
user with that specific email then we're
going to return a error or we're going
to raise an exception so we'll say if
not
user we're going to raise an HTTP
exception and the status code is going
to be status Dot and I'm trying to
remember what code was oh it's going to
be a 404 because that user doesn't exist
and then the detail field we're just
going to say uh invalid
credentials because normally with
authentication you don't want to say hey
this is the wrong email or this is the
wrong password cuz you don't want to
make it a little bit easier for them to
kind of guess other people's information
just say this is invalid credentials let
them figure out whether it's the email
or the password and then after this uh
once we verify that we did actually get
a user object we have to verify that the
passwords are equal so this would be um
you know performing that logic of of
hashing the password that they gave us
and seeing if that it compares to the
password from the database and so what
we're going to do is we're going to
create a new function in the utils
folder that's going to be responsible
for comparing the two hashes or actually
it's going to take in the Raw pass
password the password attempt it's going
to Hash it for us and then it's going to
compare it to the hash in the database
so we'll create a function we'll call it
verify and it's going to include the
plain password which is the password the
user is trying to attempt and then the
hashed password which comes from the
database and all we have to do is just
return and then we can reference the PW
context right so if you want to Hash a
password you just call the dash the do
has method however it's also got another
method for us which is verify so it's
going to perform all this for us so we
just pass in the plain
password and then we pass in the hashed
password and it's going to figure out
the rest now you're thinking well you
know what is the point of such a tiny
function why don't we just include it in
our aop py well we 100% could because
you know it's it it's really two lines
of code it doesn't really make sense to
store it in in another file however then
we also have to import all of the um the
bcrypt code and I like to have
everything kind of separate so keeping
all of the bcrypt logic in one file just
makes things a little a little bit
easier to manage but in our o folder U
we can import utils
now and we're going to run the utils
verify and we're going to pass in the
first the plain password which is going
to be uh stored in user credentials so
we'll say user credentials. password and
then we pass in the hashed password from
the database which is stored under user
so we'll say user.
password all right
and if they are not equal so if they do
not equal each other which means they
provided us the incorrect password then
we're going to raise another HTTP
exception and this is going to be the
same thing we're going to send a status
code of uh
404 and the detail is going to be the
same thing we're not going to tell them
that was the wrong password we're just
going to say invalid credentials so that
it's not easy for them to kind of keep
guessing passwords or emails all right
and then at this point what we would do
is we would create a token which you
know we haven't really gone over how to
do that and then we would just
return return
token um but once again we haven't done
that so I'm just going to
return and we'll just say
token and I'm just going to say example
token right because we haven't
implemented that logic but I do want to
make sure that the rest of the code
looks good so we'll try that
out and I'm going to go in create a new
request this will be login user can be a
post
request I'm going to copy
this actually this is just going to be
slash
login and then in our body we're going
to provide uh some
Json and here we're just going to going
to say
email is
whatever and
password is
whatever and before I actually do
anything uh I'm going to run a query on
my database because uh if you see I've
got a couple of users that don't have
hashed passwords so I'm actually going
to delete
everything just so I can clean up some
mess and uh I'll just say and what I'm
actually going to do is I'm just going
to delete everything I think that's
going to just make things simple because
I don't even remember these guys'
password so it's going to create some
issues for us so we'll just say delete
from and I'll say users and then I just
won't provide any condition so this
should delete everything we'll run that
and you can see that it looks like it
deleted all 12 results and that's
perfectly okay and I'll add my original
query back select star from
users and what we're going to do is
we're going to just register a new user
so I'll do create user
and I'm going to call this sanjie at
Gmail and then the password is going to
be password 1 123 so let's create that
user let's take a look all right we've
created that user and now let's log in
uh this user so we'll go to login and
I'm going to provide my san at
Gmail and then we're going to provide a
password which was password 1 23 let's
try this
out and it looks like we ran into an
issue so what well first of all that's
the wrong error message I'm not sure why
it gave me that let's just it should say
invalid credential so where is this
actually happening and guys I made an
absolute silly and stupid mistake I
forgot to actually wire up this router
in our main.py file so it doesn't even
know about it so let's import this we're
going to say Import
off and all we have to do is just one
skin I'm just going to copy this
and we'll just say o.
router right let's try this
again right and we've got our example
token which means that we verified that
the passwords are correct and everything
was good to go we just haven't
implemented the logic for the token but
let's just make sure that uh when we put
in the wrong password it still works or
actually it shouldn't work and we get
invalid credentials let's put the right
password back in and then let's use the
wrong
email and we get invalid credentials as
well so um so far we are almost done
with the whole login process the next
thing that we got to do is uh handle
creating a token it's not going to be
too difficult um but I do want to save
that for the next
video now if we head on over to the fast
API documentation under security there's
going to be ooth with password and so
most of the things I cover are going to
be coming from this documentation right
here now the first thing that we have to
do is we have to install a library that
handles signing and verifying JWT tokens
and so so we're going to use this python
djy library and then we have to provide
a uh cryptography back back end so we're
just going to copy this line right here
and we're going to run this uh in the
command
line and what I'm going to do is when it
comes to authentication and anything
with jwg tokens I'm going to create a
new file and I'm going to call this ooth
2.
py all right and the first thing that
we're going to do is we're going to
import from Josie
we're going to import JWT error and
JWT now there's going to be three things
uh three pieces of information for our
token well actually uh well there's
three pieces of information but there's
three other things about the token that
we need to provide so we're going to say
uh we we're going to need the secret key
right that's that special key that I
mentioned that ultimately handles uh
verifying the data Integrity of our
token which resides on our server only
so we're going to have to provide that
secret key we're also going to need to
provide the algorithm that we want to
use we're going to be using
hs256 and then we're going to need to
provide uh one other thing which is uh
the expiration time of the token so we
haven't really discussed the expiration
time if we just give a plain token
without an expiration date that means
that user's logged in forever and
there's no application that just lets a
user log in forever I don't think uh so
we're going to provide a expiration time
so that we can
dictate exactly how long a user should
be logged in after they actually perform
a login operation and so we need an
expiration time and what I'm going to do
is I'm going to just save these as
variables I'm going to say secret
key equals and then this is just going
to be some arbitrary long
text I'm just going to paste that in
here and if you're just wondering why I
mean this if you just follow the
documentation actually
all right you'll see that they do the
same thing so we just need to give it
some really long text in this
case and it even gives you a command to
kind of get a string like that for your
password um because you you could
theoretically just put you know hello or
something here and that's going to work
just fine however it's not quite as
secure but for learning purposes it
doesn't matter just provide some kind of
string right and then the algorithm is
going to look like this and then the
expiration time is going to look like
this so I'm just going to copy this from
the documentation
and then we're going to Define our
function so this is going to be create
access
token and what we're going to do is
remember the access token is going to
have a payload so whatever data we want
to encode into the token we have to
provide that so I'm going to pass that
in as a variable called data and this is
going to be of type
dict and what we're going to do is we're
actually going to make a copy of this
data because I don't want to actually
change it I want to make a copy of it
because we're going to we're going to
manipulate a few things and I don't want
to accidentally change the original data
so we're going to say
data. copy so this is going to make a
copy and I'm going to store it in a new
variable and it's going to be 2core code
so this is all the data that we're going
to encode into our JWT
token and then now we're going to create
the expiration field so to actually do
that there's a couple things first of
all right now we have it set to 30
minutes uh and so what we need to do is
to provide the time uh of 30 minutes
from now right so we have to provide the
time that it's going to expire in so we
have to grab the current time and then
add 30
minutes and so anytime you're working
with dates and times we have to import
the date time
Library we'll say date
time import date time and time
Delta and I'm going to say expire equals
date time. now so this is going to grab
the current time and I'm going to pass
in time
Delta
of and then since this is in minutes I
would say minutes
equals access token expire
minutes and then what we want to do is
we want to grab the two encode which is
a copy of a dictionary so this is also a
dictionary
and I want to update
it and here we're going to pass
in expiration and then we're going to
provide the expire time so we're just
adding that extra property into the uh
into all of that data that we want to
encode into our
JWT and so now our JWT will tell us when
it's going to expire and what we're
going to do is we're going to call JWT
um coming from the is it Jose I guess
it's the Jose library so JWT doin code
the this method is actually going to
create the JWT to token and we'll say
the first property is everything that we
want to put into the
payload the second one is going to be
the secret
key the
signature and then we have to specify
the algorithm so the algorithm equals
algorith algorithm right
there and then at this point we're just
going to return oh we have to save this
in a
variable and here we just encoded
JWT and then now we can go back to our
specific path
operation and since we're already
importing actually we have to also
import awath to
and then here we're going to create an
access
token and we're going to call the sorry
not utils oo
2 dot create access
token and we're going to say the data
equals and then we're going to pass in a
dictionary so here the user
ID remember this is the data that we
want to put in the payload so I have
decided that I'm going to put in the
user ID and pretty much nothing else I
don't really care about anything else we
could give it a roll we could something
else but for me I just want to encode
the user ID so that's what I'm passing
in here however if you wanted to provide
some extra information about the user if
you wanted to provide uh you know their
scope of different endpoints they can
access you can put all of that
information in here and so I'm going to
say the user ID is going to be set to
user. ID and so now what we can do is
we're going to return a few things I'm
going to say we're going to return the
access token
which equals access
token and then we're going to tell the
user what kind of token this is so this
is token uncore type and this is what's
referred to as a beer token and I'll
explain how to actually configure that
on the front end um but literally in the
authorization header we just write the
word Bearer and then we provide the
token so nothing special there all right
let's try that out and it looks like I
got an error and I don't know why I put
an equal sign
there and let's try TR this out so we
we've got the login in point let's put
in the correct email this time and let's
see what happens look at that we got an
access token and this kind of looks like
a JWT token right it just looks like a
bunch of random text and then it tells
us it's a bearer
token so let's actually copy this and
what I want you guys to do is uh go to
your web browser and I want you to
search for
JWT and then go to the first well go to
JWT doio and then here what we can do we
can paste in our JWT token and what's
really cool is it's going to decode the
token for us and so you can see this is
the algorithm we used it is a JWT token
but take a look at the user ID right
this is the actual user ID that we
passed into the token so all of the data
that we encrypted into the token are all
sitting right here so we also got the
expiration time and then the signature
somewhere in here as well um but isn't
that pretty cool right it was able to
decode that and it's important to
understand that you know none of this is
encrypted anybody can see this
information but by being able to sign it
we know that no one can kind of mess
with it and we can also specify an
expiration time so we know that how long
this token is valid so when the the our
API gets it it's going to just verify
that nobody touched the token it's going
to verify that hey the expiration time
you know isn't before the current time
which would mean that it's already
expired at that point it already knows
the token's valid and then we can assume
that uh everything is good to go we're
going to make one small change when it
comes to to retrieving the user
credentials in our login route instead
of passing it in the body we're going to
use a built-in utility in the fast API
Library so if we do from fast
api. security do o oops oo 2 we're going
to import something called oath 2
password request
form and so what we can actually do is
instead of just doing the you the usual
here with the user credentials we're
actually going to delete that and I'm
going to provide a dependency well
actually I need the user credentials
because we have to store it someplace
but here we say this equals ooth to
password request form equals depend so
we're setting up a dependency kind of
like we do with the database and so this
is going to require us to retrieve the
credentials and then fast API is
automatically going to store it inside
this variable called user
credentials however we have to make one
small change so the username in when you
retrieve the uh the user's attempted
credentials from here what it's going to
do is it's going to store it in a field
not called email but it's going to store
it in a field called username so when we
compare the models. user. email when
we're querying the database we can't
compare to user credentials. email
because there's no field called email
right it's going to only return two
things it's going to
return oops it's going to return
something it's going to return our
username which equals whatever and then
it's going to return our
password which equals whatever uh and so
we don't have access to email we have to
use user dot uh sorry user credentials.
username because uh well this is
actually a bad example because you have
to think of it as like a dictionary
right it's coming in like this and then
there's going to be a a user
field you're going to have username oh
why is that
capitalized username which equals
BL you're going to have username which
equals you know blah and then you're
going to
have password which equals blah right
and so we'll just tag user credentials
Dot and then we'll grab the username
which in our case will happen to be the
email uh the ooth 2 password request
form doesn't really care what what the
username is it could be a username it
can be a email it can be an ID it
doesn't really matter it doesn't really
care it's just whatever the user
actually sends it's just going to store
it in a field called username so those
are all of the changes that we have to
make uh from our back end side now when
it comes to testing things we no longer
send the credentials in the body like we
normally do like if I try to send this
now we're going to get an error right
because it says uh
username uh is field required value
error missing so what we and the
password is also missing so what it's
doing is it no longer expects it here
instead it expects it inside form data
so here I'm going to say username
and this is going to be my email in this
case and then my password
here and so let's try this now and now
it successfully works so those were the
couple of changes that we have to make
um but you'll see that it makes life a
little bit easier by setting up that
dependency and using the built-in
functionality of fast API in the last
lesson we learned how to log in a user
by sending a request to the login
endpoint and providing the username and
password and our API will then return an
access token which the user can then use
to retrieve data from our API so anytime
he needs to access a endpoint or path
operation that requires a user to be log
in he'll just send this JWT token in the
payload and then our API has to actually
validate the token so in this video
we're going to handle the logic for
verifying that the token is still valid
then that they didn't temper with it as
well as verifying that the token hasn't
expired
now before we do anything what we're
actually going to do is we're going to
define a schema for the token um because
uh we know that the user has to provide
the access token so uh just like any
other piece of data uh if we expect them
to send something it's best to set up a
schema so we're just going to set up a
schema for Access token and token type
and just make sure that they match
accordingly and so here we're going to
do class
token and we'll say the access token
is going to be ftype
string and the token uncore type is
going to be of type string as well and
then we can also set up a
a a schema for the token data so the the
data that we embedded into our uh access
token so we can say token
data base model and then here we did
embed the ID
but I'm going to say this is optional
for
now and it's going to be a type of
string if it is
set so it can be optional and we got to
import optional as well and so that's
going to come from the typing
library and then in our ooth 2 file we
created an access token function and
then we have to create a function to
verify the access token so let's create
that function and it's going to just be
called verify access
token and what we're going to do is
we're going to pass in a
token which is going to be a
string and we're also going to pass in
the specific credential exception so
we're going to pass in uh what our
exception should be if the credentials
don't match or if there's some issue
with the token so we'll just store this
in a variable called credentials
exception and I'll explain this a little
bit later
and so here I'm going to say JWT right
so we're going to access the JWT Library
I'm going to say JWT Dot and then it's
going to have a function and if you take
a look at our options I'm sure you have
an idea because creating a token we did
uh uh encode encode I'm guessing you can
figure out what is the specific method
for decoding it's going to be decode
obviously and here we're going to pass
in a couple things first of all the
token then we have to pass in the secret
ke
so that we can decode
it and then we have to pass in the
algorithm that's used so we can just
pass an
algorithm once again these both of these
are coming from these variables right
here not it's obviously not a good idea
to store the secret key uh within your
actual code uh but like I said we're
going to have a later section where
we'll turn these into environment
variables so that it's not hardcoded
into our code and we're going to store
this
in payload in a variable called payload
all right and so this will just store
all of our payload data and to extract
the data what we can do is we can say
payload doget and then we have to get
the specific field that we put in so if
I go back to my o. py file in my routers
and you take a look at my data you can
see that we have a field called user ID
and that's going to get the ID of the
user so here we just say
get and then we just pass in that same
exact name users ID and we'll say that
this is going to be stored in a variable
called ID and this should be of type
string and if there's no
ID then we're going to
raise a credentials
exception right so whatever exception we
provided into this function it's going
to raise that and then we're going to
say token data
equals schemas do
token
data with the
ID
equals uh the ID that we extracted out
of
here and I see that we didn't import
schema so I'll import that real
quick so we'll say from
dot import
schemas and so all this is going to do
is it's just going to validate you know
that it matches our specific token
schema now if you look at our schema
right it's literally one thing so it's
not super exciting and I made it
optional so we shouldn't actually make
it optional but we'll come back to
fixing this in a bit um but this is just
going to ensure that all the data we
pass in the token is actually there and
so that's why I'm using a schema for
that however for one actual variable you
don't actually need to do that
especially since we're checking to see
if it exists right here but it's good to
always make sure so that in the future
if we do add extra Fields uh we can also
validate the schema here now we're
almost done with this function however
there's one little issue um because we
can run into an error in any one of
these lines and so anytime you're
working with code that can error out uh
you want to do a try accept block so
we'll do
try and then I'm going to indent
these and then here we'll say
accept and then we're going to pass JWT
error and this should not be capitalized
and remember this is coming from the
Jose
library and once again we're just going
to raise a credentials
exception uh if there's any kind of
error that we didn't account
for all right and the next thing that we
have to do is Define one last function
and this is going to be called get
current user so what this is going to do
is and so what this is ultimately going
to do is that we can pass this as a
dependency into any one of our path
operations and when we do that what it's
going to do is it's going to take the
token from the request automatically
extract the ID for us it's going to well
it's going to verify that the token is
correct by calling the verify access
token and then it's going to extract the
ID and then if we want to we can have it
automatically fetch the user from the
database and then add it uh into uh add
it as a parameter into our path
operation function so here all we're
going to do is we're going to pass the
token and so this is going to be a type
string and then here we just say depends
which has to be imported from the fast
API Library so we'll say from Fast API
import we're going to import depends
status and HTTP
exception so here we'll say depends and
then we'll pass in a oath 2 schema or
oath 2 scheme so what we have to do here
is it's going to be a little bit
confusing we'll say oath 2or
scheme and this is going to be equal to
and we have to import one more thing so
we'll say from fast api.
security
import aath
to password
bear and then here we just reference
Olaf 2 password
bear and what we have to do is we have
to provide one field called token URL
and so this is going to be the the
endpoint uh of our basically our login
endpoint and so if you go to your o. py
you just grab whatever name this is uh
keep in mind you don't have to name it
login but you just have to pass this
into
here actually sorry you removed the
slash so it's just login
and then we're going to grab this
variable and I'm just going to pass it
into
here and this is kind of just tying
everything
together and then we have to Define our
uh credentials exception that we're
going to pass into the verify access
token
function so when the credential is wrong
or there's some kind of issue with the
JWT token what uh exception should we
raise so here I'm just going to say HTTP
exception and we'll set the status code
to
be a
401 so
unauthorized detail here I'm going to
pass a
string once again could not validate
credentials and then we have to set some
headers as
well and so just go ahead and just copy
this in
and then finally we're going to return
uh a call to our verify access token
function and since we have the token
passed into the get uh current user we
can pass it into our verify access
token and then we also can provide the
credentials
all right so just to quickly recap
because I know we did a lot and I think
some of it may be confusing um but
what's going to happen is anytime we
have a specific endpoint that should be
protected and what that means is that
the user needs to be log in to use it uh
what we're going to do is I'm going to
uh well as an example let's say that uh
users who want to be able to create a
post they need to be logged in what we
can do is we can just add in an extra
dependency into the path operation
function so I can say uh here I would
just say get
current uncore
user which would return an
INT and then we'll say this equals and
then we pass in a dependency so we'll
say depends on oath
2.get current user so this is going to
add a dependency uh which is going to be
that function that we created called get
current user so anytime anyone wants to
access a resource that's requires them
to be logged in we're going to expect
that they provide an access token and
then we provide this dependency which is
going to call this function get current
uh sorry where is it get current user
and then we pass in the token that comes
from the request we're going to then run
this verify access token in this case
and then it's going to Pro uh provide
all of the logic uh for verifying that
the token is okay and that there's no
errors and if there's no errors then we
go ahead and uh return nothing
essentially and that means that they
were successfully able to um be
authenticated if we do return return
some kind of error with the credentials
exception then it they're going to get
that appropriate 401 response back so
that's how our login works it's nothing
special um but there are a couple of
different components that are involved
and uh in the next lecture we'll start
to take a look at um starting to protect
our specific endpoint so that it forces
users to be logged in to actually
perform that operation all right guys I
made one little mistake uh in the verify
access token function I forgot to return
something and so if you ran into any
issues uh it's because of this so what
we're going to do is here is we're just
going to do return token undor data and
so what's really happening here is once
again we're going to decode the JWT
we're going to extract the ID if there's
no ID then we're going to throw an error
uh and then we're going to validate uh
with the schema the actual token data
which in this case is just an ID so
that's the only field but if you had
extra Properties or or extra information
you can pass that in and then we want to
make sure we return the token data so
that we can actually make use of that
data and keep in mind remember the get
current user is what actually calls the
verify access token so when it calls
verify access token it expects us to
return the token data and then when we
get the token data we return it to
whoever calls this
function okay guys so I found a few
extra bugs that we need to fix now the
first thing that I messed up was when we
actually set the expiration time under
the create access token function instead
of datetime.now it should be date
time.utc now this is important um
because as I was testing it I kept
getting an expiration error and that's
because this should be a UTC now and the
second thing is we want to put this in
Brackets because I guess it expects a
list of algorithms maybe we'll put that
in there and then finally uh this is
also a bug right here because if you
take a look at the payload when we
create the token uh which I believe
should be in the
o.y when we log in we pass in uh the
data as user ID and not users ID like we
did here so remove that and this should
prevent us from running into any other
potential issues in the upcoming
lectures sorry about that I know we ran
into a couple of bugs but that's what
happens when you try and copy and paste
really quickly before we wrap things up
there's one last change that I want to
make inside the login route in the o. py
router file um I noticed that for the
response or or the exception that we
raise if the either the users email is
wrong or if their uh if their password
is
incorrect um I use the wrong HTTP status
code for the exception and I can't
remember what I actually had it before
cuz I went ahead and fixed it but I want
you guys to go ahead and change the two
exceptions here uh in both of those
cases to a 403 I think that's a better
representation of what we should be
sending when the user doesn't provide
proper
credentials so just update it here and
then update it here as well and then you
guys should be good to go
okay guys we're pretty much done with
all of the authentication side of things
the only thing that we have to do is
require the user to authenticate because
right now you know if we perform any
operation like creating a post uh you
can see that I could just create a post
and that's it I don't have to log in
first I don't have to do anything so
anyone can create post anyone can delete
post anyone can do anything they want
obviously that's not how your API is
going to work uh you're going to want to
ensure that users are logged in to
perform certain operations and there may
be certain operations where they don't
necessarily need to be logged in
depending on how you want to structure
your application right because you know
if it's like a a twitter- like
application right anyone can see
anyone's tweets I just can't delete
anyone else's tweets right and to create
a tweet I have to be logged in uh so it
depends on what you want to do for your
application but what we're going to do
is we're going to start off by forcing
the user to be logged in before they can
create a post and doing this is actually
really simple so let's go to our uh
post. py and let's find our create posts
now the first thing I want to do is I'm
going to import
oath 2 which is coming from this oath
2py file and then in our create posts
path operation function we're going to
add an extra dependency and this
dependency is going to be the uh create
or sorry get current user function that
we defined in our oath 2
file so we say is depends and then we'll
say ooth
2.get current
user and then we're going to store this
in a variable called uh we'll say
userid and this is going to be
a
integer okay and so all this is saying
is that uh this function is now going to
be a dependency so this is what forces
the users to have to be logged in before
they can actually create a post and so
when this function is called whenever
they hit this endpoint the first thing
that we're going to do is we're going to
call this function and this function all
this function does is really just call
the verify AIS token but and passing in
the T the token which comes from the
user uh and so it takes the token uh we
first decode the token we extract the
ID from the payload and if there's no ID
we throw an error and then you can see
we validate the schema uh and then this
sorry this is something I actually added
in uh off camera so we can just delete
that and then go back to what you guys
have um but we ultimately return the
token data which is nothing more than
the ID right so we could rename this as
ID for now but like I said in the future
you may want to add extra uh Fields into
the payload and then it's no longer just
the ID it's going to include extra
information so we're going to return the
ID which then gets returned by the get
current user function and then in our
post. py uh in our function we're going
to return the ID and stored in a
variable called user ID and so then we
can ultimately access the user ID by
just calling user ID that's it and we
can do whatever we want uh with this
user ID and you'll see we'll eventually
add some more logic uh but for now I'm
just going to print it out just to see
what we
see and let's go ahead and try this so
first of all I'm going to create post
and then we're going to see what happens
now when I try to create a post post
look at that not authenticated so by
putting in that extra dependency we have
ensured that the user has to be
authenticated before they can use this
post now how do we actually provide the
token so that we can actually use the
create post well first of all let's get
a token so we're going to go to the
login user I'm going to hit send going
to get a brand new
token and then what we want to do is we
want to go to create post and then we
want to go to headers and then we want
to create a header and you know you can
see I can I created one already but I'm
going to type this out for you from
scratch in the line below it so we say
authorization is going to be the the
key and then the column is going to be
and you type the word in Bearer because
it's a bearer type token so you do bear
with a capital b space don't forget the
space and then paste it
in okay and so now this is included in
our header and so we should be able to
send a request and so now look at this
this we were now successfully able to um
send our token the API was able to
validate it was a valid token and it was
able to then allow us to create a post
and uh just another little Postman tip
uh you can uncheck this for now so that
it's not authorized for you if I try to
do it now you see I get error you can go
into authorization and then just type in
uh go to Bearer token and then paste it
into here does the same exact thing uh
it's just you don't have to type in the
word bear for yourself and then you know
have to do all of that you could just
hit send now and it does does the same
exact thing whichever method you prefer
more now that we've protected our create
post route uh let's go ahead and do this
with some of our other routes so it's
just a matter of just copying the
dependency for get current user and then
uh for retrieving a post well remember
this part is up to you you decide
ultimately what routes you want a user
to be logged in to actually perform an
operation um but for delete posts I'm
definitely going to force a user to be
logged in and for update post I'm going
to do the same
thing and then finally uh you know like
I said for getting post you know it's
really up to you um we'll say that you
have to be logged in to do anything so
for get posts or getting all posts we
want to make sure that they're logged in
and then for getting an individual post
we want to make sure that they're logged
in and then finally the last thing that
we well it's not the last thing but uh
one of the things I forgot to do is
under o. py when we send our access
token uh after they log in uh if you
remember in under schemas we actually
created a token model sorry token schema
we never actually used it so let's
actually use that um by setting the
response model
here and this is going to be
schema do
token emma.
token but let's save this
and this should be capitalized sorry
about
that and so now if we log in a user we
should still get no error so perfect
okay so just in case in the future we
accidentally change something uh we're
still going to perform that validation
to ensure that the token we only send
those two Fields when we return a
token now let's quickly just test all
the other route uh so if I do get posts
and I hit
send you can see well let me save
everything sorry about that once again
now if I hit send you can see I'm not
authenticated so I have to do the same
thing uh so once again you can do
authorization Bearer or you can go to
authorization and then just select
Bearer token and then paste in the
token so now if I hit
send oh sorry I got to recopy the token
again now if we send it works now get
one post let's try this not
authenticated we'll go into
authorization bear
token send that works deleting
posts go to once again to
authorization uh there's no post with an
ID of three about
four all right that worked and then
finally update
post we're going to do the last thing
and bear token
all right and that works and then let's
just double check to make sure that if
there's no token what
happens error perfect okay guys so I
think that's going to wrap up this video
for now we've pretty much done uh all
the authentication that we need to do up
to this point there's one last thing
that I want to test to verify that
everything works the way it should and
uh we probably should have test this in
one of the previous videos but I forgot
to do it and I want to make sure that we
test the expiration process because a
JWT uh has an expiration time that we
set ourselves and this just ensures that
a user is logged in only for certain
amount of time now we set the access
token expiration time to be 30 minutes
uh and so that means that if a user logs
in and he keeps his token for more than
30 minutes after that 30 minute Mark if
he tries to use that token to access any
of our end points it should throw an
error because it's already expired so
let's test this out and the easiest way
to test this is first of all we're not
going to wait 30 minutes that's
ridiculous ulous so what we're going to
do is we're going to set this to 1
minute and we're just going to test this
real quick and so I'm going to log in
this
user so this token is valid for exactly
1 minute and so we'll go to create post
actually we'll just do get post it
doesn't really matter and I'll paste
this in here and you'll see this works
and we're going to just wait for one
full minute and after 1 minute let's
just verify that we get a unauthorized
error because the token has expired
okay so it should be about 1 minute now
and so if we test this we should now get
an error so after 1 minute it says it
could not validate credentials now we
could set up a log message to say that
hey this token is expired but um we
don't need to worry too much about that
uh as long as it throws an error and it
gives them a 401 I think that's good
enough for
now and so this confirms that our
expiration functionality works and the
last thing to do is well let's make sure
we change this back so once again it
doesn't matter what time you choose it's
up to you I'm just going to do 30
minutes actually I'm going to do 60
minutes just for testing purposes moving
forward I don't want to have to
continually uh get a new token after
every 30 minutes so 60 Minutes is a good
number now you might be wondering why
exactly do we have this get current user
function when all it really does is just
call verify access token we could
completely just remove this and just
call this directly whenever we want to
authenticate a user and you Absolut
absolutely could at it with the current
implementation but the idea behind the
get current user function is that uh
once the verify access token uh REM uh
Returns the token data which is the ID
the get current user function should
actually fetch the user from the
database uh and so that way we can
attach the user to any path operation
and then we can perform any necessary
logic now you don't actually have to
fetch the user here uh it's up to you
how you want to implement this if you
want each of your path operations to
fetch the user themselves they have the
ID so they can do it themselves however
if you wanted to automatically do it
here you 100% can do that and so I'm
going to show you guys how you can do
that in this
lesson and so keep in mind we get the
token data back which is going to be
nothing more than an ID and what we're
going to do is first of all uh we need
access to our database so that we can
fetch the users so from here I'm going
to import database and within this
function we can pass in uh the the
dependency so that we can actually get
access to the DB object so I'll say
depends and then we're going to access
database Dot and I already forgot the
name of the the function what is it
getor DB so
getor DB and we'll say DB
session equals and then we have to
import session from SQL Alchemy
and so now we can make requests to a
database and what we're going to do here
is first of all I'm no longer going to
return that
directly and I'm going to say token
equals and then we're going to call the
this function right here verify access
token
all right and since we have access to
the Token what we can do now is we can
say db.
query and then we have to import models
and I'm not sure if we've done that
already we haven't so I'll import
models I'll say models.
user. filter and then we want to filter
based off of the ID so I'll say models.
user.
ID equals equal token and then we just
grab the idid
field and then we're going to grab the
first
one and then we can return the
user which I forgot to save it so user
is going to be equal to the result of
that and if you want to you can print
user here but um I already know this is
going to work so we can just go and save
this and then in our post. py right when
we call this uh dependency right here
it's no longer returning the user ID so
I don't think it's it's a good practice
to call this user ID anymore because it
represents a user so I'm going to say
I'm going to call this current user and
we're going to rename this
everywhere all right and then here
within the function I'm going to print
out current uncore user
and so if I try to create a post
now and then open up my console you can
see that it printed out the user object
which not very helpful but uh what we
can do real quick
is I'll just say current.
user. email so we can see the email of
that user just to verify that we are
actually getting the user and we can see
that it does print out the email so
that's ultimately why this function
exists because normally here this is
where you query your database to grab
the user and then you return the user
and then whatever you return here is
ultimately what allows any of your other
routes to get whatever you're returning
so since we're returning a user we're
going to store it as a variable called
current user in this video we're going
to take a look at some of the more
advanced features of Postman and we're
going to start off by taking a look at
environments so select the environments
Tab and you'll see that uh Postman just
gives you a quick description of what an
environment is it says an environment is
a set of VAR Ables that allow you to
switch the context of your request so we
can set up some variables that change
depending on uh what environment we work
in and uh you're probably thinking what
exactly is the point of that and let me
give you a great example if you take a
look at all of our requests you can see
that we hardcoded them to be 127.0.0.1
8000 and this is our development
environment now when we ultimately go to
deploy our app it's not going to be
deployed on 127.0 1 it's going to be
deployed on some server it's going to
have a public IP somewhere on the
internet and so when we want to test out
our production server or make some
changes to our production server make
some test request to it we would have to
change the IP address the port number as
well as we probably are going to be
running um https instead of HTTP so all
of our requests we'd have to change all
of them uh and then continuously flip
back and forth every time we move from
Dev to prod and then from prod back to
Dev and so instead of having to hard
code these values and then change it
constantly we can actually create a
variable that changes depending on what
environment we use within Postman so
let's go to environment and let's create
an environment and I'm going to call
this environment we'll say this is Dev
and then uh our project name which is
fast
API so this is our environment and what
we can do is we can define a variable
and I'm going to call this one
URL and then here I'm going to actually
just copy this
URL and then go to our environment again
and and then I'm going to give it an
initial
value all right and then our current
value should update and then we can just
hit save okay and so we've set this
variable to be this specific IP in our
Dev environment and so if we go back to
collections and then go to our G posts
first of all now moving forward you want
to make sure that you're working in some
kind of environment so we'll select the
environment we just created and then
instead of hardcoding this value here
I'm going to change this and I'm going
to just say to actually use a variable
you do curly Braes curly brace the name
of the variable and then curly brace
curly brace okay and it should be orange
instead of red if you get a red it's
going to mean that it wasn't able to
resolve something and there's some issue
so just double check what you did orange
is good and then if you see this result
when you hover over hover over it that
means that everything's working and so
just to quickly test this you can see
that it says could not validate
credentials that's perfectly fine I
didn't set up the access token or
anything but this does confirm that
we're able to resolve that variable and
so that way you know if I go and then
create a new en enironment and I'll just
add
a here and then we'll say this is
prod fast
API we can then give a different URL for
the um production environment so this
could be like you know https colon slash
SL I don't know you know some domain
name that you buy I'll call this sanjie
doxyz
Flash and then I can save this and so
that way uh if you ever are testing your
development environment you just go to
Dev and then when you want to quickly
switch to your production you just
change that and then the URL will
automatically update so you don't have
to change anything yourself and it's
super handy to set this up and we're
just going to do this for all of our
requests moving forward so I'm just
going to copy
this and we're going to do this for all
of them
okay and if you go ahead and test this
yourself uh you should ultimately not
run into any issues uh I'm not going to
bore you through you know individually
testing these you can do this yourself
uh and if you know if you run into areas
it's just you probably past it in
something wrong now that we've set up
authentication on our API testing our
API has gotten a little bit more
challenging and that's because I can no
longer just go to create posts and then
just hit send because I have to be
authenticated first to be able to
actually create a post and so what I
have to do in Postman is I have to hit
send I have to log in and then get the
access token I have to copy the access
token and then go to the specific
endpoint I want to test and then I want
to paste that in there and then hit send
and then I can finally create post and
this is a little cumbersome and tiring H
and it gets really hard if you have a a
short expiration time on your token
imagine if you had an expiration time of
five minutes then every 5 minutes you'd
have to repeat this process um but
luckily postman has a way to actually do
this uh through an automated fashion
right we're all developers we all want
to do things automated so let's take a
look at how we can do this and I had to
make sure that you guys understood uh
environments and variables beforehand
because uh this the method that we use
actually makes use of environment
variables so let's go to the login user
endpoint and we're going to hit send and
get a new access token and so we've got
this access token and what I want to do
is through code I want Postman to
automatically set an environment
variable so how do we do that well let's
go to
tests and here we can put in whatever
code we want and so we can read the
documentation on how to do this but the
ultimate goal is to uh set an
environment variable through code so how
do we do that well there's a little
snippet here that kind of gives you
examples uh and what we want to do is we
want to set an environment variable and
so to set an environment variable you
just do environment. set provide the key
and then the variable name and so just
like we did with uh environments right
if you go into your environment uh
you've got the URL which is the key and
then the value and so we're just going
to do the same thing but just through
code so here I'm going to set the key to
be
JWT and I'm going to set the
value to be this access token so how do
we actually retrieve the access token
from the response of the request well we
can do pm. response that grabs the
response object then we'll convert it to
Json and then we need to get the token
and the token sits on a property called
accessor token so whatever this field is
called this is is what you're going to
pass in so we'll say dot accessor
token all right and so now if I send
this
again we'll get the token the code
should have run and it should have set a
variable called access token and so now
under create post instead of hard coding
this what I can do is I can
actually uh just reference the JWT
variable and so I set minus capitals
there looks like there's one from a
previous project maybe but we want this
one right here and if you want to just
double check you can see that this ends
in
wd30 and if you want to go back into
login user you can see that this ends in
wd30 so it looks like it did set that
and update it accordingly so we'll set
that in there and so now if we send you
can see that it uh we can now create
posts and so anytime you log in a user
it's going to update that token uh and
we can verify this if you take it the
last three letters q0a is the new token
and then I'm going to just remove that
so we can see the value and we can see
that q0a is the last three letters as
well so this updates it dynamically so
that all you have to do is now uh just
hit login user and then you can start
testing all of your other endpoints and
we're going to update all the other
endpoints as well so for get posts I'm
going to put that in there as well and
then for getting an individual post
deleting a post updating a post uh we
don't need it for create user um we
might want to do it for get user if we
set up authentication for get user but
we haven't done that yet so we'll hold
off on doing that for
now now currently our application
doesn't work like a traditional
application would and the reason I say
that is you know if you take a look at
how everything's been set up um not just
in our API but in our database we've got
two tables a user table and a post table
so we can create modify delete users
however we want we can log in and then
we can create modify and delete as many
posts as we want right and you think
well that that sounds perfectly fine yes
however think about any other
application think about any social media
type application when someone creates a
post and you see that post on your feed
what are you going to see next to the
post you're going to see the user that
created it right so every post is
ultimately associated with the user
account that created that post but we
have no way to actually do that in our
application at the moment because
there's nothing that ties a post to the
user that created it right take a look
at all of the columns in our database
we've got an ID a title content
published technically there's a created
at column that I didn't draw in this
diagram but that's okay so how do we
know what post was created by what user
and this is where relational databases
really start to shine because the the
main idea behind a relational database
is that you set up these relationships
between tables so we need to set up some
kind of special relationship between the
users table and the post table that will
allow us to associate a post with a
specific user that created that post so
let's take a look at how we can do that
uh within postgress or any SQL based
database and the way we do that is we
actually create an extra column in our
post table so we've got a column you can
call it whatever you want but I'm going
to call it user ID and I'll explain why
and what we're going to do is we're
going to set up a special foreign key
and a foreign key is a how we tell SQL
that this column here is connected to
another table
and what we do is we specify two things
we specify the table that it should be
connected to so here I'm saying hey this
should connect to the user's table and
then we specify what specific column it
should use from that table and here
we're saying the ID column because this
connection is connected to the ID column
of the user's table and so that's what
we set the foreign key on and all this
is does is this is really such a simple
concept whatever user creates this post
we just embed the ID of that specific
user so for the Post with the ID of 621
the user that created this has an ID of
212 so if we take a look at what user
has an ID of 212 we go here and we can
see that clay gmail.com created this
post and so that's all we have to do to
set up a relationship between these two
tables and so now moving forward any
post we create will easily be able to
tell what user created it because we're
going to embed the ID of that user into
this column called
userid and if you take a look at the
second one as an example we can see that
this was created by a user with an ID of
378 so we go into the user table and we
can see that this user is Mike
gmail.com and it really is as simple as
that and this is what's referred to as a
on to many relationship within SQL or
any relational database uh and the
reason why they call it that is because
one user can create as many posts as
they want however a post can only be
associated with one user two users can't
create a
post and so that's this is referred to
as a one to many relationship one user
can create many posts and that's all we
have to do it is actually that simple we
just create another column and then we
have to specify this special forign key
constraint where we just tell SQL hey
what table do we look for and what
column and keep in mind in this case I'm
using the ID of the user table um but
when you get a little bit more advanced
with SQL uh and setting up relational
databases you'll find that it sometimes
you don't have to always point to the ID
of another table there's there's going
to be a lot of instances where you set
up foreign keys to other columns that
aren't necessarily the ID column
depending on how your relationships are
set up and how your application should
work that is a perfectly acceptable
thing there's no um specific uh
restriction saying that it has to point
to the ID column of another table and so
I think that's enough theory behind
foreign keys and relationship so we're
going to connect to our postgress
database in the next section and we'll
start creating that extra column adding
the foreign keys and then we'll start
learning about how to actually work with
these
relationships all right guys go ahead
and open up PG admin and before we get
started I'm going to do something a
little unusual I'm going to delete
everything from our post table now when
it comes to creating an extra column and
creating a foreign key that's not a
requirement you know you don't need to
do that in a production database I'm
just going to delete everything just to
keep just to make things a little bit
more simple moving forward um because if
we don't delete anything when you start
to add columns that especially have a
not null constraint uh we have to do a
little magic to kind of get that to work
and I want to keep things as simp simple
as possible so what we're going to do is
we're just going to delete everything
from the post table just to make things
as simple as possible so we can just say
delete from Posts and that should delete
everything and everything's gone and we
should be pretty much good to go to
actually start setting up our foreign
key so right click on your post table
and then click on properties and the
great part about these foreign Keys is
that you know we just have to do this on
the post table because it's a one to
many relationship there is nothing in
the users table that we have to do so
what we're going to do is we're going to
go to column
and then we're going to add a new
column and I'm going to call this user
ID and you can once again name this
anything you want the actual name
doesn't have to make sense but uh you
know I think naming it user _ ID makes
sense because this is a column that's
going to represent the ID of the user
that created our post the data type now
this is important because the data type
of this column needs to match whatever
the uh data type is of the ID column
uh from the users table so we always set
the ID up to be integer so you want to
match this however keep in mind that
sometimes when you're working with data
bases it might be uh some other data
type right if you use big int you
definitely want to make sure that this
is also a big int if you use a small in
make sure this is a small int if you use
uu IDs make sure that this is a uu ID as
well you just want to match up with
whatever that column is in that
respective
table uh now we have uh the options to
set this as not null so right now we can
create a post with a null user which
which means there's no user that created
this post uh and if and to figure out if
you should set this to be not knowledge
just depends on how you want to set up
your application should the database
allow you to have a post without a user
it's up to you to decide I'm going to
say no for now I'm going to say Not N
because I don't want to be able to
create a post without a user it doesn't
make
sense right and then after that what we
can do is we have to set up our foreign
key constraint so let's go to
constraints
and then we want to go under foreign key
so this is where we set up that magical
connection between the two tables hit
the plus sign and then give this foreign
key a name the name of the foreign key
doesn't matter right it doesn't impact
the functionality of this is more just
for you as a user to be able to read it
a little bit more clearly when you see
it on the
CLI but there's a standard convention uh
that we like to use when it comes to
naming our foreign Keys what we like to
do is we like to take the table that
we're working on so it's going to be
posts
and then we do underscore then the table
that we want to set a foreign key to so
it's going to be
users and then we just do underscore F
key once again this is just nothing more
than a a name to describe the foreign
key it's not actually doing anything at
the moment to actually set up the logic
of the foreign key we have to open this
up and we have to go under columns and
so this is how we actually set up the
relationship so here we're saying what
is the name of the local column like the
column in our posts uh table well we
created our brand new user ID then it's
going to reference what table well we
know it's going to reference the users
table so we select the users table and
then what column from the users table is
it going to reference well it's going to
reference the ID column of the user
table and at that point you just hit
plus it gets added up
here and before we move on there's one
last thing I want to cover because we're
almost done we have to go under actions
and because we're setting this
relationship up between two different
tables we have to figure out you know
what happens when uh a user gets deleted
right because right now a post is going
to have the idea of the user that
created it what if we delete that user
what do we do so if you go to the on
delete section we have a couple of
different options uh one of the more
common ones is Cascade and so what
Cascade does is if I let's say if I have
a couple posts that were created by a
user with an ID of seven if I delete
that user user then postgress will
automatically go into my post table and
delete any posts that were created by
that
user and so that's one option that's
what I'm going to use however we have
other options as well we can uh set it
to the default value of the column so if
we give the column a default value uh
maybe we create like a like a random ID
of zero or something then it's going to
assign all of those posts that were
created by the deleted user to zero we
can set it to null so if we did set null
then it's just going to set the user ID
column to null if that user gets deleted
keep in mind if you want to be able to
use set null then you have to go back to
columns and make sure this is not set to
uh allow you to set it to null so we'd
have to set it to no or then it would
throw an error when you try to delete
someone and then there's a few other
options but uh we're going to stick to
Cascade and then keep in mind you can do
the same thing with on update so what
actions do you want to perform when you
update a specific user in that case um
but we'll leave it as no action for now
I just mainly care about the on delete
at this point that's all you have to do
for foreign Keys you just specify the
column of the other table it should
point to and you're good to go we'll hit
save and then we're going to go under
posts well actually before we do that
we're going to go under users we're
going to view all
rows and let me clear out some of these
there's too many windows open right and
these columns got a little
squished um but right now I have three
users uh it's got an ID of 17 18 19 so
go ahead and remember that obviously
your database is going to be different
so uh just remember the IDS of a couple
users and what we're going to do is
we're going to go under our posts and
we're going to view
edit and so right now I have no post CU
I deleted everything so I'm going to
create a brand new post and I'll just
call this this my first
post and then content is just going to
be some random
content I'll leave published blank um
because we've got a default value and
then right now if you take a look we've
got this new user ID column so if I try
to save a post right
now take a look at what happens it gives
me an error it says null value in column
user ID Vol um violates not null
constraint so because we said that user
ID cannot be null we have to provide a
user ID so let's give it an
ID and if we go back to users I can see
that there's going to be I can use 17 18
or 19 so whatever user created this I'll
just say John created this so we'll grab
an ID of 17 and I'll say that this is
going to be an ID of 17 and then if we
save this look at that we now have a
relationship between the users table and
the post table let's create another
entry I'll call this second
post and just going to have some random
content and I'll say that this was
created by the user with an ID of
18 and that should work just fine now
what I'm going to do now is what happens
if I create a post and I give it an ID
of a user that doesn't exist so I have
IDs of 17 18 19 what happens if I set
the user ID column to be a value of 20
well let's let's try that out so I'll
just call this third
post and then we'll set the content to
be something
random and if I set this to 20 let's see
what happens if I hit save look at this
insert or update on table post violates
forign key constraint there's no user
with an ID of 20 right so that doesn't
exist in that table so it's going to
throw an error so uh that's the magic
behind foreign keys that it's going to
check to make sure that that user
actually
exists and so this isn't going to work
so we'll just set this to 17 as
well now save that right and that's it
guys and when it comes to you know kind
of querying these users right let's uh
go back to our database and let's just
set up a query now let's say I want to
get all of the posts created by user 17
well we can do
select star from Posts where and now
instead of you know searching for based
off ID we grabb the user ID
column and we set that equal to 17 so
this is going to get me all of the posts
that were created by user 17 if I run
that you can see that this got the two
post from user 17 and then if I change
this to 18 we're going to get the one
post created by user 18 so from a SQL
perspective right nothing's really
changed you just specify what column you
want to match on and then provide a
condition now what I'm going to do now
is I'm actually going to delete this
user so I'm going to go and just say
delete from users uh where ID equals 70
so we're going to delete John at
Gmail and we're going to actually do
that here so I'll say first of all
select star from
post all right so we've got all three
posts and I'm going to run another query
except I'm going to say delete from
users where ID equals 17 so what is
going to happen when we delete those
users because we have posts that have
relationships to them well since we set
the on delete to Cascade it should
delete these posts automatically for us
so I'm going to leave this down here so
it's going to run another query so we
can see exactly what our table looks
like after we delete this user and so if
I run this you can see that when I run
select star from Posts there's only one
entry left and that's the one with the
user ID of 18 because it automatically
deleted all of the posts created with an
ID of 17
all right and so from a database
perspective uh I think this is all we
really need to cover for now uh
eventually we'll start taking a look at
joins which is how to run these complex
SQL commands that allow you to uh Jam
The Columns of multiple tables into one
result uh to make it a little bit easier
to retrieve information because right
now if I if I try to get all of the
posts you know like send me every single
post in my database right it's just
going to give me the user ID but if I
need the information about the user like
what's the name of the user what's the
the username or the email then I would
have to individually query the uh the
IDS of these users so i' have to go then
I'd have to do you know a select whoops
make sure I don't delete anything I'd
have to do a select star from users
where ID equals 18 and I have to do this
one by one for every single post so that
I can get this specific user and so
that's when we start to make of things
like joins um but that's a little ahead
of us at the moment and that takes a
little while to explain so we're going
to come back to that um but before we
actually kind of move on from this
database side of things because we
pretty much covered everything we're
going to delete that column for now
because we're going to make sure that
SQL Alchemy actually sets up all of
these constraints for us automatically
so that we don't manually have to do it
so let's go to our properties go to
columns we can just delete this column
and then I think this should
automatically delete the foreign key
does not delete the forign key so make
sure you delete that as
well and then we can save
that and it looks like there's it's
throwing an
error so let me cancel out of that and I
think we're going to have to do this in
a two-step process so we'll say
constraints we'll delete the foreign key
first we'll save that and
then properties we'll delete the user
ID there we go and so now if I do a
select star from
Posts right there should no longer be a
user ID column so this put our database
back into the state it was in before we
started playing around with
it so now that we know how to create and
set up a foreign key within postgress
and PG admin we're going to see how we
can do this through code using SQL
Alchemy because ideally since we're
already using SQL Alchemy to generate
all the tables uh generate all the
columns for each table and all the
different properties we should also set
it up to generate the foreign key for us
as well so we're going to go to the
models atpy file this is where we Define
what the tables are going to look like
with the different classes and we're
going to add a new user ID or owner ID
column to the post class and that's
going to create a specific column within
the post table
and so we can just go here and you know
call it owner ID user ID whatever you
want I'm just going to call this owner
ID and this is going to be column and
then here we have to specify the data
type of the column and as I mentioned
the data type should match up with
whatever the data type of the foreign
key is so since this column is going to
point to the ID column of the user table
it should match up with whatever is here
so since this is integer this has to be
integer as
well then to to set up a foreign key
constraint you just type in foreign key
and then go ahead and Auto Import that
if you don't know where it's getting
imported from it's going to get imported
from SQL Alchemy so uh if you didn't
automatically do it you can go ahead and
just manually type that out and then
there's going to be two fields that
we're going to pass in so the first of
all we have to pass in the exact column
uh and table table and column that we
want to reference and so we want the
user's table and then grabbing the ID
column and so your instinct would be to
use the class name but we don't actually
reference the class name instead we want
want to reference the table name so it's
going to be lowercase in this case so
you say users Dot and then what's the
column name it's called ID so we say do
ID and then the second thing we need to
do is uh if you recall we have to set up
what the policy is for when we delete
the foreign key or the parent table uh
and so we always used uh Cascade so that
if the parent object gets deleted all of
the child object objects get deleted as
well so we can do that through SQL
Alchemy as well and we'll say on delete
equals and then we just say
Cascade and then finally we want this
field to be nullable equals false so it
has to be filled in all right and now if
we save this restarter application we'll
take a look at
postgress and if I actually refresh
this and this is actually an
old an old panel so I'm going to remove
that and then if I just do uh we'll go
to our post table
go to query tool I'll say select star
from
Posts run that you can see that there is
no actual owner ID column uh and so the
reason for this is that uh SQL Alchemy
when it when we start our application
SQL Alchemy will check to see if there's
a table called posts and if there is oh
sorry if there isn't it's going to then
create a table based off of these rules
however if there's already a table named
posts uh it's not going to do anything
so if we update any properties for a
pre-existing table it's not going to
change that that's not exactly what SQL
Alchemy is meant for instead we would
have to use a database migration
tool kind of like a lmic uh which we
haven't covered yet uh so instead for
now what we're going to do is we have a
couple different options we can manually
just do it go into PG admin add the
things yourselves or we can just take
the easy way out since this is a
development environment we can just drop
our post
table and that's one of the luxuries of
working in development so you can then
hit save again and that's going to cause
it to restart the applic the application
and then if we go to
postgress and we just hit refresh it's
going to create a new post table and
then we can go into properties and we'll
go into columns and we now see that we
have an owner ID column which is set to
not null that's good and then if we go
to constraints foreign key you'll see
that we've got our foreign key and you
can take a look at the details down here
and the main thing I want want to check
is for actions we do have on delete
Cascade all right and so now that we
have everything set up if I just run
this query again we should see the owner
ID show up so let's create a few entries
and um before I do that I need to make
sure that I actually have some users um
because I kind of went in and deleted a
few things so I've got two users with an
ID of 20 and 21 and so what we're going
to do is we're going to make sure that
the foreign key po points to one of
those IDs so we'll grab a post I'm going
to just set this to be post one as the
title and it's going to be some
gibberish and then we can set the post
uh the owner ID to be the ID of a user
that we already have in our database
we'll save this and we can see that it's
successfully created now if I create a
new
post and this time leaving the owner ID
blank if I hit save you can see that it
throws an error because this can't be
set to null and if I try a ID of a user
that doesn't exist like 57 it should
also throw an error and so it's saying
that hey the owner ID of 57 does not
exist in the user
table and I'll just change this to 21
and then it should
work great now let's quickly check out
the on delete functionality just to make
sure that it works uh and what we're
going to do is let's go to well I'll
just run the query right
here so we'll do delete from and we'll
say users where ID equals and we're
going to delete the user with an ID of
20 so if everything works we should see
just this entry also get deleted in the
post table because the owner is has an
ID of 20 and since that owner is going
to be deleted then we should only have
this one left so if I run this yep we
can see that the one with the owner ID
of 20 is now
deleted all right and so that kind of
handles all of the database side of
things at this point if you try to test
the rest of your application you're
going to probably run into a couple of
issues um but that's just because you
know we' had hard coded our schema to
match a certain you know number of
properties and so since we've added this
new property to our posts it's going to
throw a few errors so we're going to
have to update a few things in the next
video but you'll see that updating your
schema is very simple With The Changes
we made in the last lecture it's never
really going to cause some issues with
our application so there's going to be a
few things that we have to update within
our app and so let's just quickly run
through a couple of our requests just to
see what they look like see what changes
we need to make and so if you haven't
already done so uh log in a user and so
once we're logged in we should update
the variable and now we can retrieve our
posts so if I hit send here you can see
that we retrieve all of the posts in our
application I just have one in this case
but the first issue that I see is that
we're not returning the owner ID right
this is a brand new column and I would
expect this information to get sent out
to the user and the reason why it's not
included in here is that uh we have to
actually update our schema cuz our
schema probably doesn't have that owner
ID cuz we never added that in and you
might be thinking well do we actually
need to send it yeah I think it makes
sense for us to send it because in any
application the user should know who
creates a post so ultimately they're
going to have to uh get that information
and so we should provide the owner
ID so let's go to our code and if you
actually go to the posts uh router and
take a look at the uh get all posts
you'll see that the response model is
going to reference schemas dopost so
let's go to schemas
dopost and you can see that this is what
we're using to return um this is the
schema that we're going to use for
returning post to a user and so this
actually inherits from postbase so
postbase has title content published and
then we extend that and we're going to
add the ID which gets created at the
database level as well as the date and
time or the created at field which gets
added by the
database so we can add it
here however I'm sure you're thinking
well could we add it at post base should
we add a post create well let's think
about this right the the first thing
that we have to think about is when we
create a post should we be passing in a
owner
ID well that we 100% absolutely could do
that uh and that actually does kind of
make sense so in that case if we did
want it to be available or require it
for creating a post then we would add it
under post create here as well or we
could just add it under post Bas so that
both of them inherit it however what
we're going to do is we're actually not
going to require the user to provide the
owner ID uh instead what we're actually
going to do is we're going to let the
the logic of our route to actually just
grab the ID from the token and then use
that as the field so we don't actually
need the user to pass that into the body
so we're not going to we're not going to
use that field or apply that field to
either one of these classes we're just
going to do it for the Post class which
is the one that's responsible for
sending the post
out so I'll add a column here and we'll
call it owner ID and I'm going to say
that this is going to be a type of int
all right let's save that and let's see
if that makes a difference so let's hit
send and so now we can see that we get
the owner ID and that's really all the
changes we have to make so if we
actually go to get one post and we look
at our code here and if you look at the
post. py for getting an individual post
you can see that we're returning the
same exact model and if we take a look
at uh creating a post we return the same
model so all of those will be updated
accordingly and same thing with the
update post the update post also uses
schema. post so since we're using the
same schema for all of them we don't
have to do anything else and we can just
quickly test that out so I'll do get one
post and I realized we have to actually
get what was the id id is four so we're
going to update this to be an ID of four
you can see that we now have the owner
ID there if we update
it right we can once again get the owner
ID and at that point it looks like
everything else is good
however if we go to create posts real
quick and we create a
post right we get a crash actually so
there is an issue with creating a post
and I'm sure you guys can guess exactly
what it is take a look at the error when
we try to create a
post right it's saying uh there's some
kind of SQL error and it says there's a
null value in column owner ID and that
makes
sense and that makes sense so we'll
actually tackle this in the next video
and you'll see that it's going to be
pretty straightforward to actually get
that resolved so in the last video we
learned that uh the create post
functionality is broken now cuz if I try
to create a post you can see that it
sends back an uh a 500 status code and
if we take a look at the logs we can see
that uh it looks like there's some issue
with the SQL and it's saying that the
null value in column owner ID violates
the not null constraint and so looking
at our model we obviously set the owner
ID right here and this is set to be
nullable false so we actually have to
provide who the owner ID is for this new
post so how do we do that well let's go
to our post path operation and let's go
to the create post path operation and so
it's right here and so nowhere in this
code are we actually providing a user ID
or owner ID into this new new post that
we're creating we're just grabbing the
post which comes from post create the
schema and if we look at that schema you
can see that we do do not provide a
owner ID and like I said we're not going
to actually pass the owner ID into the
in the body what we're going to do is
whoever is logged in and creating the
post should automatically be the owner
right if you're logged into Twitter and
you post something Twitter knows that
you're the one creating the post so
whatever ID is associated with your
account it's going to set that
automatically so we shouldn't have to
pass that in the body we should
automatically retrieve it from uh your
authentication
status So within post right you can see
that we have the current user and so we
should be able to um get the current
user uh or the user's ID so if I do
current user.
ID and we can remove this I don't need
the email and if I try to create a post
it's still going to error out that's
okay I just want to see what it prints
out though before the error and you can
see we got a lot of Errors that's
okay and you can see that it printed out
the ID of my user which is 23 and just
to double check that that's actually my
user I'm going to select star from users
and you can see that 23 is sanjie at
gmail so we can just take that and just
add that into the new post
object and so we're creating the new
post right here where we reference
models that post and what we're doing is
we're just spreading whoops we're just
spreading out the uh schema that we got
from the body and so to actually add the
ID property it's very easy all we have
to do is just say owner
_ ID is going to be set to current user.
ID so we're just grabbing um that from
the get current user function just like
we did right
here and I think we probably need a
comma
there and that should be all that we
have to do so let's I'm going to remove
this
code and let's test this out now so if I
do create
post look at that no errors you can see
that the owner ID was automatically set
to the ID of my user which is
23 currently in our application we do
have authentication set up for delete
post and update post however there's no
check to make sure that a user is only
deleting his own posts right now if
you're logged in you can delete anyone's
posts and no application works like that
you should only be able to delete your
own post no user should be able to come
in and delete one of my posts that
doesn't make sense so let's implement
the logic for setting up a quick little
just if state just to check hey is the
person that's logged in trying to delete
a post that he owns if he doesn't then
we're going to return an error and so
right now if you take a look at our
delete post path operation function uh
we query the post that he's trying to
delete and we check to see if there's no
post if there's no post then we send a
404 that's expected um but if we did
find a post the next check is just going
to be another simple if statement and
we're going to say
if post.
owner ID does not equal
get current
user. ID so these two things have to
match for the user to be able to delete
it if they don't match then we're going
to send another uh HTTP exception so
we'll say raise HTTP exception now the
exception will set the status code to be
a new one so this one's going to be a
403 so this means forbidden that's a
that means it's a resource that they
specifically aren't uh able to access
because on we could send a 401 but they
are I guess a 401 could also work but
I'm going to do 403 I think that makes
more sense and then we can set the
detail and I'm just going to
say not
authorized to perform requested
action and this exact same check can be
used for updating posts as well because
it's the same exact logic and I'll just
do that right here
right under the same check so same logic
right first thing we're going to do is
we're going to check to see if that post
exists and then the next thing we're
going to do is we're going to make sure
that the
owner of the post is whoever the user is
logged in as now let's test this out so
right now if I do a get posts uh you can
see that the owner Okay so we've got a
post created by both owners and I'm
currently logged in as um I actually
can't remember who I'm logged in as but
we can see that I used sanjie at Gmail
and that's going to be user
23 and what I'm going to do is go back
to get posts and I'm going to try to
delete the post with an ID of four
because that's the owner ID of 21 and
keep in mind right now I'm logged in as
user
23 so let's try this we're going to
delete
post with an idea four okay it's already
set there so we should get an error in
this
case and it looks like I got a server
error that's a problem and I already see
the
issue and right now post is actually not
the post itself it's the
query and to actually get a post I have
to do post. first one so what I'm going
to do actually is I could change this to
uh post. first and then grab the owner
ID but I'm going to actually perform the
query right here I'll say
post I'll change this to postore query
I'm going to make a few changes actually
and I'm going to set this to be post
equals postore query. first
and then I'm going to set this to be
post and this is going to be set to
query all right and just to kind of
quickly recap uh we Define the query
here we'll then find this post we'll
check to see if it's not there and then
we'll check to see if the owner is uh if
the user who's logged in actually owns
this post and then we're going to grab
the original query and then we're just
going to append a delete so that we
delete it that's all and let's just make
sure the update is set up the same way
and it looks like the update one was
already working that way so it should be
good to go now hopefully there's no
errors and let's try
this and once again we got an
error and it looks like function object
has no attribute
ID and I realized my mistake again first
of all uh this is getting stored as
current user not get current user so we
need to change this to be
current user I'm not sure why I did it
like that seems pretty goofy and then
this also should be current
user right because we're calling that
function and we're storing the result in
current user so we want to reference the
variable I'm not sure if that was like
an autocomplete that did that or I just
had a brain fart either way hopefully
it's the last of our issues so let's try
this all right Perfect Look at that not
authorized to perform that re requested
action that's to be expected because we
don't own that post however if I do a
quick search again um I do own the post
with an ID of8 because we can see the
owner ID is 23 and that's who I'm logged
in as so let's try to delete post with a
with the value of
eight send and we get a 204 so that
means it's successfully deleted we'll do
get post just to verify and we can see
that we get those uh just the one post
now so that seems to be working uh I'm
going to go back in actually let me
create a post real quick because I no
longer have a
post all right so we have we created a
new post and so you can see that this is
my post right here and I'm going to just
update it so let's go to the update
one uh first of all I'm going to try to
update a post that I don't own so we're
going to try to update the post with an
ID of four we should get it not
authorized and then let's grab the ID of
the post that we do want to change which
is nine let's hit send and it looks like
it updated but let's check our database
always so we'll say select start from
Posts and the post with the nine got the
updated
entry oh wait wait a minute it looks
like it may have updated both of them uh
only one way to find out if that's
actually what's happening I'm just going
to create a quick new
post I'm just going to set the ID to be
23 all right and I'm going to update
post with nine with an ID of
nine okay and then let's refresh
this okay so post with an ID of 10 is
still the same so okay it wasn't a bug
um it looks like maybe I had changed
this
earlier and I'm not exactly sure why I
had when I updated this post but that's
okay and so I think that's going to wrap
up this video um we've uh handled the
update and delete so that we can only
update and delete our own posts all
right before we proceed any further I do
want to talk about one last thing and
that is that when we do get posts which
is an authenticated route so it requires
you to be logged in to retrieve the
posts uh if I try to retrieve the post
you'll see I get posts from every user
now this may or may not be the result
that you want right it's going to depend
on what your application's going to work
uh look like uh you know if this is like
a you know like a note taking app or
something where all of your posts and
things like that are all private then
you wouldn't want to return everyone
else's posts you'd only want to return
the user the user specific post however
if this is some kind of social media app
right then obviously you're post
Republic so when you do get post you'd
want to return everyone's posts and so
it really just comes down to how you
want your app to to function I'm going
to show you guys what you would need to
change if you wanted to make it so that
you returned your only your own posts
but after afterwards uh we're going to
actually delete those changes because I
want to leave my app like this this is
kind of how I wanted it to work more
like a social media app but I do want to
make sure that you guys understood how
to make this
change and the same thing would go for
get one post we want to make sure that
only the user that created a post can
retrieve that specific post and so if we
go back to our path operation for
getting all posts you could see that we
just do a db. query uh doall and so if
you only want to return the post for a
specific user that's logged in it's very
simple all we have to do is do a
filter and here we'll say models.
poost doid equals
equals and then we just get the current
user
ID and it looks like I still left this
as user ID so this should actually be
updated to be
current user and if you notice the you
can see that the type is set to int even
though it's actually returning an entire
user object I found that this whatever
type you put here doesn't actually
impact the code so put whatever you want
you can put in a you know some sort of
dictionary that actually correctly
matches it um but you could just leave
it as well so I'm just going to leave it
like that it doesn't break any logic H
and then at this
point I believe I'm still logged in as
user 23 if I try to retrieve all post uh
looks like I got
nothing and that could be a little bit
of a problem so let's see what we broke
and the easiest way to kind of
troubleshoot this is what I'm going to
do is I'm actually going to remove the
dot
all so that's going to return the query
it just won't actually run the query and
I'm just going to print the query let's
see what that looks like sometimes it
helps to see the raw
SQL let's hit
send all right we should get an internal
server a that's to be expected but I
just want to see my print
statement all right so let's see our our
print statement so select we're getting
all of the columns that's expected from
Posts where posts ID
equals this value so that looks like
it's perfect well let's just quickly see
um before we move any further uh what
exactly is my user ID and we'll just
check our database
okay and we'll run this
again and then we're going to
check right so 23 and then if we go to
our database and I realized the exact
mistake that I made and this is a stupid
mistake right this
is this is looking for a post with an ID
with this specific ID we don't want the
the ID of the post we want the owner ID
so we'll do owner ID equals current user
ID all right let's test this out
now once again an error but I just
realized I forgot to update this to
Beall and then we'll try this again and
now we get all the post with an ID of 23
if I log in as a different user let's
say uh this is sanjie 1
I'll login that should update the token
so now if I do it get all posts it
should return all posts with an ID of 21
and so that's that's how that works and
then if you want to see how that looks
like for retrieving an individual post
we'll go to get _ poost and to actually
handle this logic it's going to be the
same thing as a delete so you can just
copy what we did for the delete
one and here I can just say post. owner
and this should do the same exact
thing so now if I do get one post well
first of all let's take a look at all of
our
posts I'm going to do it in our database
so I'm logged in as user 21 so I should
be able to access a post with four but I
can't access a post with an ID of 10 so
let's try 10
am I able to access him not authorized
let's try idea
4 and I can get that one so that's how
that works but like I said I don't want
my application to work like that so I'm
going to remove that functionality I'm
going to make all posts essentially
public and then we're going to remove
this
filter and I'll remove this print
statement and this print statement just
to clean things up a bit
and let's just double check that we
didn't break anything once again so
let's get all posts we get all posts and
let's get an individual post regardless
of who owns it and that's all fine and
dandy
now now just kind of thinking ahead of
what our uh you know front end would
look like even though we're not going to
build it uh taking a look at any social
media type application you know when we
retrieve the posts we usually want to
embed uh the users's ID so we W want to
know who actually created the specific
post we wouldn't just put the owner ID
because no no user none of your users
understand that ID they want to see what
is your you know Twitter handle what is
your email whoever created that we want
to see their user ID so it looks like
for all of the posts that we retrieve we
would have to then send a second query
to retrieve you know hey what is the
information for user uh with an ID of 23
and then once we get that we would then
have to kind of combine all that data so
that we can figure out what post uh it
belongs to what user and what is their
specific
username now with SQL Alchemy we can
kind of set
up set it up so that it automatically
does this for us and so if we actually
go to our
models what I'm going to do is I'm going
to set up a
relationship and so this relationship
isn't a foreign key it does nothing in
the database whatsoever but what it does
is it'll tell SQL Alchemy to
automatically fetch some piece of
information based off of the
relationship and so here I could say
we'll create a
owner and I'm going to say owner equals
relationship and we probably have to
import
this and so it did so it imported
relationship from sqlalchemy.orm
and so if you haven't done that go ahead
and do that and what we'll see is this
is going to return uh the class of
another model so here I want to return
the
user and this is going to be be a
capital u because I'm not referencing
the table I'm referencing the actual SQL
Alchemy class so what this is going to
do for us automatically is that it's
going to create another property for our
post so that when we retrieve a post
it's going to return a owner property
and what it's going to do is it's going
to figure out the relationship uh to
user so it's going to actually fetch the
user based off of the owner ID and
return that for us and there's nothing
else we have to do it actually is that
simple this is one of the great Parts
about SQL Alchemy is that these
relationships will Auto automatically
make it so that it fetches that data for
us so that we don't have to manually do
it
ourselves so let's test this out let's
see if this actually works I'm going to
go back and I'm going to retrieve all
posts and it looks like nothing's
changed we don't get any user
information we do once again just get
the owner ID so what happened well you
probably can guess we need to update our
schema and so if we go to our
post we're now going to return
a
user and so here what we would do is we
would just add another property called
owner and then here it would instead of
returning an INT or a string or anything
like that we can actually return
a pantic model so I can say I want you
to return a user oops a user but I it
looks like we don't have a user class we
have user out and then we have user
create so which one do we actually want
to return um probably user out cuz
that's what we're turning we the user
create is for creating a
user and you notice that we get an error
actually
here and that's because this user out
hasn't been defined uh at this point in
the code so you have to read python top
down and so user out is actually defined
all the way down here so if you wanted
this to work we would have to move all
of the user
stuff up a level so I'm going to cut
this and I'm going to just put it right
above put post and so this should remove
the error and so now it looks like it's
good and so once again all we did was we
added a new property called owner and
this is going to return a pantic model
type called user out and so that's all
this is returning now so let's see if
this fixes our
issue and now I'm going to retrieve all
posts and so now take a look at this it
automatically fetch the owner it got the
ID it got the email it got when their
account was created at um we may not
want that but for now I think this makes
sense we could create another class to
kind of um narrow down the exact fields
that we specifically wanted for this
situation but I think this is good
enough uh these are all the informations
that I want actually returned so this is
perfect it's going to do this for every
post and if I try to get one
post it's also going to return that
specific owner and so in reality to get
this functionality right once again all
we had to do was just create this
relationship and so once SQL Alchemy
understands a relationship it's going to
fetch that piece of information for you
from the user
model in this lesson we're going to take
a look at query parameters and if you've
never worked with an API you may not
know what that is but I guarantee you
you have worked with them before and you
have seen them you just had no idea what
they were and so I'm on yelp.com and I'm
just doing this for demonstration
purposes but I'm just going to do a
quick search here I've just picked a
random City in this case it's Miami
we're going to search for that and I
want you to take a look at the URL
and so our URL is first of all we have
the domain name which is kind of like
the IP address and then we have the
specific endpoint that we want to reach
so this is the SL search endpoint and so
in their API they've set up uh you know
some sort of endpoint that probably is
uh allows you to search for restaurants
and then we have a question mark and I
know you guys have seen this before
because pretty much any website you've
ever uh you know used uh you'll see that
question mark whenever you're you know
searching for things and any results you
get you'll see that in the URL and and
so everything to the right of that is
what's referred to as query parameters
so all of this is query parameters and a
query parameter is a optional key value
pair that appears to to the right of the
question mark and these query parameters
allow us to kind of filter the results
of a request so you know if we're trying
to retrieve posts maybe we don't want
all posts maybe we want to get posts
that were created in the last two hours
maybe we want to get uh posts that uh
you know if it's a social media type app
maybe we want to get posts that have
rece received over 100 likes right these
are all things that you would do using
query parameters where you can say Hey
you could just pass in a key and a pair
and you can say I want to find posts you
know that are less than 2 hours old and
so a lot of other operations uh that are
necessary in an API things like
pagination those are all going to be
done with query parameters and if you
take a look at this one uh since we
searched for Miami right it looks like
it passed a query parameter called
findor Lo which probably means location
and then it says Miami Florida and so
it's going to basically talk to the API
and say Hey listen I need you to get me
all the restaurants and I want you to
filter Down based off of restaurants in
Miami and so that's kind of how query
parameters work and so for us it's it's
up to us to Define what query parameters
we want to allow and what we want them
to do and it's going to vary from app to
app but you'll see that most apis have a
couple of uh query parameters that they
all use so let's go to our app real
quick and what we're going to do is
we're going to go to our post router and
in this case we've got our path
operation of retrieving all posts and
what I want to do is I want to let the
user be able to kind of filter down on
the post that they want to see and the
first thing that I'm going to do is I'm
actually going to allow them to specify
how many posts they want to retrieve
altogether so I want to give them the
option to say hey I want 10 posts or
maybe I want 100 posts or maybe I want
uh 50 posts we should allow the user to
Define that and so
to to allow a query parameter
we could just go into our path operation
function and just pass in another
argument so I'm going to do question
mark then we give it the name of the
query parameter so this is the key
essentially and I'm going to call this
limit so this is going to limit the
number of posts they get and this is
going to be of type
int and we're going to give it a default
value so we'll say that you know by
default if they don't provide a limit uh
we're going to say the limit by default
is
10 and now I'm all I'm going to do is
I'm going to print out limit all right
and I'll show you guys how to actually
send that query parameter so let's go to
our get all posts and so to send a query
parameter it's very easy you just type
in a question mark then you grab the
name of the query parameter which once
again is
limit so we'll grab
limit and then you say it you set it
equal to whatever value you want to be
so if I want to get a limit of
three if I hit send right nothing should
have changed in our code but you can see
that we were able to print out the limit
so that's how we access query parameters
in fast API it's pretty simple you just
pass it in as another argument into your
path operation function but let's
actually set up our query so that it now
takes into account the limit and with
SQL Alchemy uh anytime you want to you
know perform another operation you
usually have a built-in method so I'm
going to remove this do all for now and
so if I want to uh limit the number of
results I just do Dot and then let's see
what uh methods we have at our disposal
uh since we're looking for something
that limits something let's maybe check
to see if there is a limit method and
looks like I don't see one here but
there actually
is we can do limit and then here I'm
just going to pass in the limit variable
and then after that we can just do the
do all as we usually
do all right and so now well first of
all in our database we don't actually
have that many posts so I'm just going
to create a couple well actually I could
just do this through our API a lot
quicker so I'm just to create a whole
bunch of
posts and so that should give us five
posts now let's create a few
more all right so we've got 11 posts
now and we'll go back to our API and
we'll say I want a limit of three so
let's send that and let's see if we only
get three posts we get one 2 3 perfect
and if I don't provide a limit well
actually let's try a different number
let's try five
now all right we get one two 3 four five
perfect and if we don't provide a limit
alog
together it should return 10 because our
default was set to 10 posts the limit of
10 and so we get one 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
and there are 11 results so there's one
result that it didn't provide so we've
got the limit functionality down what I
want to do now is allow the user to skip
results so it grabbed you know depending
on however postgress has decided to
return uh you know 10 posts it grabbed
the first 10 based off of some
criteria and if we actually take a look
at how did it looks like we got ID of 10
ID of 4 so it's kind of just all over
the place uh so it's
uh not sorting based off of any specific
field we may want to specify that but
what we're going to do is I'm going to
actually set the
limit equal to
two and so we'll get the first two
however postris determines what are the
first two it should send we get two but
let's say we want to skip over a couple
of them maybe we want to skip the first
the first two maybe we want to skip
these two well I want to be able to send
another query parameter called skip so
that we can specify how many we want to
Skip and if you want to send more than
one query parameter we just do the and
keyword and then we provide the next key
value pair so it would be like skip
equals 2 and so just taking a look at
the IDS here we've got one with an ID of
10 and one with an ID of four and we
want to skip both of those so going back
to our code we're going to provide
another path operation function uh sorry
another argument into the function and
we'll call this skip this is going to be
a integer and the default is going to
be uh we'll say zero we don't want to
skip anything by default and to add this
to our query uh we use the keyword
offset we do
offset and then here I'm going to say
offset
equals
skip all right and so we should be able
to skip over both of these and so if I
provide a skip of
two you can see it first starts out at
nine and then
11 if we do skip zero right it shouldn't
skip any right 10
and then an idea four if we Skip One it
should just skip the 10 and then start
off on four and we can see that the
first one is four so it allows us to
skip over post and so that's ultimately
how we're going to implement pagination
on the front end is because the front
end should be able to skip um based off
of what page they're on so if each page
returns 20 results and you want to go to
page two then you want to skip 20
results if you want to go to page three
you would skip 40 results now the last
query parameter I want to set up is a
search functionality I want the user to
be able to search based off of you know
some keywords in the title or maybe even
the content depending on how we want to
implement searching uh for for now we're
just going to say we'll be able to
search based off of the title and the
way that the search will work is we'll
have another
and and we'll say search equals and then
you know some random text and so once
again we're going to provide another
argument called
search and this is going to be of type
string however this is you know we can't
exactly give a default search so I'm
going to say this is a
optional it's going to be an optional
string so we don't have to provide
this and the default
is uh just an empty
quotes and it looks like I have to
import optional from Fast API or from
typing and so here I'll just say import
optional and this is going to give us an
optional query
parameter and so what we're going to do
here is I'll say
filter and to filter this and just kind
of like how we filtered based off of a
specific uh user ID or a specific post
ID I can say models.
poost do
tile and then we can use a method called
contains
so we can say contains and then the
search keyword so this will allow us to
provide some kind of string and it'll
just search for the entire title of a
post and it see if the Search keywords
are anywhere in the post title it
doesn't have to match completely it just
has to be somewhere in the post so this
will give us a little bit of flexibility
so that we don't have to match the exact
name of the post we could just provide
some keywords like uh like hot dogs or
beaches or whatever and it should be
able to just see if it's contained in
there so let's take a look at our
database uh you can see that we've got a
lot of ones that say top beaches in
Florida so I'm just going to do a search
and if I just search for beaches it
should return all of these because they
all contain the word beaches and I'm
just going to do a search and I'll I'll
get rid of the the limits and the skip
for now we don't really need
that and all of the results should
be actually I don't think I saved it let
me let me save that and now if I do this
you can see that every result is going
to have the word beaches in in the title
and when it comes to query parameters
you can string as many as you want so if
you wanted the the limit as well and
we'll set the limit to two and we can
also provide a
skip equals 1 you can add as many of the
query parameters that you want so now
you can see that we set the limit to two
and we skipped the first one now the
last thing I want to show you guys is to
use spaces in your search query um
because right now we just have the word
beaches but let's say I wanted uh you
know just going into our postris
database let's see what I've got maybe I
want to search for beaches hello or
something beaches right how do I how
would I search for that in a URL I can't
put a space in the URL I can't say you
know something
beaches so how do I do a space well I
can do
perent and 20 which is reference uh
which means space in your URL and then
you can do beaches so then just to
verify that that's actually returning
what we want I'm going to do a print and
we're going to print out the search
keyword and we're going to test this
out so if I hit send you can see that it
returned the one result that has the
word something and then beaches um but
it doesn't return anything
else what I would like to do now is do a
little bit of cleanup on our main.py
file uh you'll see that there's a lot of
unnecessary Imports that we don't need
as especially since we moved all of our
routes uh into their respective folders
so you'll see that a lot of these are
grayed out and so anything that's grayed
out we can move but before we actually
do that uh what I actually want to do
first is I want to take this uh code for
connecting to our database using uh the
you know the regular postris driver and
I'm going to move that uh to our
database. py file and keep in mind we
can just delete this because we're no
longer using this and we're using SQL
Alchemy to actually connect to our
database so you can actually delete this
but just for documentation purposes I'm
actually going to just cut this
out and I'm going to move this into our
database. py file just so that you guys
have this for reference uh in case you
ever want to uh you know run raw SQL
directly using this postgress Library
instead of using SQL Alchemy I want to
make sure this course covers as many
different uh you know possible
situations for you guys um but moving
this here obviously we're going to get
some errors because we have to import
all of these and and I'm just going to
go to our main and I'm going to import
them from here so here I'll just copy
these
two and we'll actually just cut it
out and then it looks like we also need
time where is that coming
from it's just coming from the time
okay all right that should uh remove any
errors and we can just comment this out
actually cuz we're not going to use that
anymore
more and then going back to our main uh
you can see that both of these are
grayed out so we're not even importing
anything from uh typing anymore or we're
not using anything from typing so I'm
going to remove that uh you can see that
we're no longer using status so I'll
actually we're no longer using all of
these so I can remove all of
those and I'm not using the body here
anymore I'm not using anything from
pantic and I'm not using anything from
random we'll just get that a little bit
closer uh we're not using session
anymore either so I'll remove that this
whatever that is going to remove
that and then we'll remove schemas and
utils we can remove get DB as
well and then obviously the uh the post
array or list that's no longer needed
these two functions they're no longer
needed they were U before we started
working with
databases and then um I mean we don't
actually need this route anymore but
I'll just leave that in there but you
can see that our code is a lot cleaner
now after removing all of those
unnecessary
Imports I'm just going to structure this
a little bit better so all the codes a
little bit closer together and I think
that's all the cleanup that we need to
do for now I just wanted to make sure
there wasn't too much uh garbage
building up in our application when we
first started working on databases I
mentioned that we should never hardcode
our database information or the database
URL into our code because this creates
two issues first of all we're exposing
our username and password right there in
code so anyone can see it if we check it
into GitHub anyone who has access to it
can see our password now and at that
point we've compromised our
application but on top of that uh the
other big issue is that right now we've
set this URL to go to our development
postr instance which is running on our
local machine
when we actually deploy this to
production our postest server is not
going to be running on this machine it's
it may not even be running on the
machine that our application is actually
deployed on it could be on a a
completely different system so we would
need a way for the code to automatically
update in in a production environment to
point to the actual production postgress
database instead of using the one that's
hardcoded in
here and so we need a way to do that and
keep in mind this uh this isn't
exclusive to just working with the
databases any kind of uh confidential
information any passwords Secrets
anything that needs to get updated uh
based off of the environment that it's
in uh needs a way we we'll run into the
same exact issue right and if we go to
our oath 2. file you can see that we
have our secret key hardcoded in here
this is something that we don't want to
do we don't want to expose this and we
need this to get updated between our
development and our production
environment because they may not be the
same on both so how do we do that well
we're going to make use of something
called environment variables and so an
environment variable is just a variable
that you configure on a computer doesn't
matter what operating system they all
support it and when you configure an
environment variable on your computer
any application that's running on that
computer will be able to access
it and that includes our fast API so Pi
your python app will be able to access
any environment variables on the machine
and so instead of hard coding the values
in our code what we'll say is hey
retrieve an environment variable named
you know what whatever like we might
have an environment variable called
postgress URL and that's going to
contain the URL of our postgress
database and so we don't need to
hardcode the actual value we hardcode
just the name of the variable and then
python will automatically pull in that
that variable so let me show you guys
how to do that and I'm going to show you
guys how to do this on Windows first and
then we'll take a look at this on a Mac
or a Linux machine Mac and Linux are the
same steps so I'm going to search for
environment and you'll see this edit the
system environment variables
and what we want to do is we want to go
to environment variables under the
advanced Tab and here you'll see two
sections you've got system variables
this is going to be environment
variables uh that are systemwide which
means any user can access them and then
we have user specific variable so these
are variables that only I can
access and you can just kind of you know
go through these and just take a look at
them um but you can see that we have an
environment variable called path don't
worry about what it's used for uh this
is something that gets set up when you
install machine but we're going to take
a look and try to access this so you can
see that this is the key the variable
name path and then the value is some
sort of path in our operating system or
in our file system so how do we actually
access that well let's open up a
terminal and here I'm just going to type
in
Echo and then we want to access an envir
variable just do percent and then the
name of the variable so I'll say path
with a capital P and if I run this you
can see that it prints out that specific
path and so that's how you access an
environment variable on the command line
uh with python code it's going to be a
little bit different but it's still
pretty simple I'm going to open up a new
file just for demonstration purposes you
don't have to actually follow along on
this and to actually access a
environment variable we have to import
the OS
module and then to access that variable
you say OS
do get
NV and then within this method you uh
just passing the name or the key of the
variable so in this case it's path and
I'm just going to store this in a
variable we can call this anything I'll
just call this path why
not and then I'll print out path so we
can see how see if it actually works but
now if I do
pi-3 and then run example.
py you can see that it printed out that
same exact
path now to set a new environment
variable we would go to new
and maybe I create a URL um a variable
name called postgress or we can just
call this how about myor
dbor URL so this is going to have the uh
URL to access our database I'm going to
say this is at Local
Host col
5432 I think that's what our database is
running on and I'll hit okay and so here
we can see that this is our new
environment variable that we created my
dpor URL and it's set to Local Host 5432
I'll hit okay
and then I'll hit okay here and then
what we're going to do is we're going to
try to access that variable so I'll do
Echo myor dbor
URL percent and actually it should be
percent
percent and you can see that it does not
print out what we said it just prints
out exactly what we wrote so what gives
what happened here well anytime you set
a new environment variable what you got
to do is you got to close out your
terminal and open up a brand new one so
I can you know I can close this out or I
can just open up a new one and this new
terminal well actually I don't want a
pow shell I want a command
prompt so this new terminal will be able
to access uh newly created environment
variables because they get Set uh as
soon as the terminal opens so once the
terminal is open I can't change them so
I have to open up a new one so that it
can reread and import all of those
environment variables so now if I do
Echo percent
mycore dbor URL percent
it looks like I may have mistyped this
so hold on let me see
what what is called and that looks like
it's correct so what's what's happening
well I'm going to close out all of them
that's probably what's the issue so let
me open up a new
terminal and I'll open up a new CR
command prompt and now I'm going to try
Echo
percent my underscore DB _
URL and now we can see that we can read
it so we have to close out our Terminals
and open up a brand new one it's kind of
annoying um but that's just the way it
works now on top of that there's an even
bigger issue and I think this is
exclusive to Windows uh and that is that
VSS code the terminals here it's
whenever you set a new environment
variable they never have access to it so
you could try deleting all of these
Terminals and then creating a new
terminal and then accessing
that new environment variable my dbor
URL and if I try
to if I try to access if I try to run
this
code you'll see that it just says None
and if I just try to run the same Echo
command
here you'll see that it just spits it
out so it's not able to read it and it's
a it's a little bit of an annoying issue
with vs code and windows you have to
close out every single VSS code window
that you have and and then reopen them
and sometimes even then that doesn't fix
the issue so know that this is just kind
of a limitation with
Windows But ultimately uh don't worry
too much about that because uh you're
going to see that especially in a
development environment going into and
actually setting all of these variables
yourself is unnecessary right I don't
want to have to go in and Set uh one for
my database IP my data base Port um as
well as my secret key my password my
username the it's just too many to
manage yourself and you'll see that more
complex applications could have 10 20 30
environment variables that need to be
set so instead of going into your system
and actually changing it I'm going to
show you guys in the next video I'm
going to show you guys how we can get
around this um by using what's referred
to as an environment file uh and so you
don't actually need to worry about the
limitations while we're running here
because we're never actually going to
set our own environment variables on our
local machine especially in our
development machine because it's just
too slow of a process and it makes
things unnecessarily difficult to
troubleshoot so before we wrap things up
if you want to delete that environment
varable feel free to do that which we
can just go here and I can just select
that and then hit
delete and let me get let me show you
guys how to do this on a Mac to set an
environment variable on a Mac machine
the command that we run in the terminal
there isn't a gooey kind of like in
Windows um we actually have to use a
terminal which I actually prefer uh what
we do is we just type in the command
export
and then we provide the name of the or
the name of the variable or the key so
I'll say myor dbor URL then we say
equals and then we just provide the text
uh the value so in this case maybe this
is Local Host all in
5432 all right and then to actually read
the environment variables that have been
set you type in print
NV and here we can take a look at all
the environment variables most of these
have been set by the machine itself and
you'll see that nowhere in here do we
see well actually we do see my DB URL
right here however uh just like I said
in Windows sometimes uh you know
depending on the terminal you're using
and a few other things sometimes you
actually have to close out this terminal
and open up a new one to actually get
the new environment variable um but here
we can just access
it by typing Echo and then we can just
say dollar myor dbor URL and and you can
see it prints it out and then within
python uh just like we did on the
Windows machine accessing it is the same
exact way it shouldn't matter depend it
shouldn't matter which operating system
you're on it's the same exact thing from
your codes
perspective with any project there's
going to be a certain number of
environment variables and as I said as
your project grows you're going to have
more and more of them and one of the
issues that you can run into is that you
could potentially forget to set one of
them either on your development
environment or your production
environment and it's probably going to
cause your application to crash and so
what would be good is to perform some
sort of validation to ensure that all of
the right environment variables have
been set for your application to
actually run properly and on top of that
it's important to understand that when
you read an environment variable it's
always going to come out as a
string which which is fine but it just
means that you have to do all of the
validation in code so if you're setting
an environment variable for your uh you
know your access token expire minutes
right we needed this to be an INT not a
string but when we read the environment
variable it's going to come out as a
string so we have to convert this to an
integer so when it comes to verifying
that all the properties are set as well
as performing validation we might have
already kind of addressed this issue
with a different part of our application
right and that's our schemas right we do
the same thing with all of the data we
send in the body by using pantic to
perform all that verification to make
sure that every single property that we
need is there and to also perform all of
the type casting so if we set it
something to be an integer it'll
automatically convert it and validate
that is a valid integer and what's great
about pantic is we can actually use
pantic to perform all of that validation
for our environment variables and let's
see how we can actually do that so I'm
going to go to main.py and as an example
I'm just going to uh import from the
pantic
library something called base settings
and so just like with uh you know any
other pantic model right we can set up a
class and I'm going to call this
settings and this is going to extend
base
settings and I didn't mean to
accidentally import
base and here we can basically just
provide a list of all of the environment
variables that we need set as properties
on the class itself and so you know
maybe I need something called
database undor
password and this needs to be a of type
string and we can even give it a default
value which is Local
Host and then maybe I need a
database
username which is going to be string and
we can give it once again a default
password we don't actually have to give
a default value but if you want to you
can and I'll say this is going to be
postgress
and then maybe we want the secret
key and this is once again going to be a
type string and we can just give it you
know some arbitrary default and let's
say these are the only environment
variables that we need for our
application to run by setting it like
this it's going to automatically perform
all of the validation for us to ensure
that all of these have been set and an
important thing to understand is that
when you set environment variables uh
you know if we just quickly go back to
um the environment variables on my
machine normally best practice for
environment variables is to do all caps
with underscores right it it doesn't
have to be all caps but this is just
kind of standard convention you can see
I've got some that aren't like that but
in general you want to do it all caps
and you can see here we reference it all
in lowercase so pantic will
automatically handle all of this from a
case insensitive per perspective so it
doesn't matter if you capitalize this or
lowercase everything it it'll take all
of your environment variables and it'll
convert it to lowercase just to simplify
everything then we create a variable
called
settings equals and then we say
settings so right here all we're doing
is we're creating an instance of this
settings class and so at this point
pantic will read all of these
environment variables and once again
it'll look for them uh from a case
insensitive perspective so it doesn't
matter if they're capitalized or not and
then it's going to and then it's going
to perform all of the validation it's
going to ensure that they properly a
string uh and and so on and then finally
it's going to store it in a variable
called settings so then we can access
all of these variables by just
saying settings Dot and then the name of
the property so if I want to get the
database password I just do settings.
database password and so we can print
this
out and I'll just start my
application right and you can see that
it printed out Local Host post and if I
want to grab maybe the
username I just say
username actually sorry it should be
database
username and you can see it prints out
post which is the default values because
I haven't actually set my system uh
environment variables to be any of these
values so it's going to use the default
one and like I said we're going to run
into that Windows issue where I can't
exactly update it without closing
everything so I'm not going to bother
doing that but what I will do just to
show you how this validation works is
let's remove
this let's say there's no default
password and so if there's no default
password then you know it's first going
to check my system uh my my system or
user environment variables to see if
there's something called database
password and since I didn't provide a
default one if there is no environment
variable with that name it's going to
throw an error because the whole point
of this is to validate that all of the
environment variables that we have are
configured
here right and so after I save it if we
take a look at this you can see that we
get one validation error for settings so
settings database password and we can
see that it's missing right and so
having that quick check makes our life
so much easier so that we don't have to
figure out you know which environment
variable is is missing which one's not
because like I said you could have 10 20
30 40 of them there's going to be a lot
of them and managing them does become a
little bit of a challenge now one quick
thing uh you know let's say I go to my
environment variables once more and I've
got uh something called path right so
path is uh you know some the path to a
specific
directory and what I'm going to do is
I'm going to say I want to access the
path but we're going to say that this
needs to be of type int so piden is
going to perform some validation it's
going to read it and every environment
variable is always read as a string and
then it's going to try to typ cast it
into an INT and if it fails it's going
to throw an error and so since this is
clearly not a integer it should throw an
error so let's try this out and we can
see that value is not a valid integer
now for all of the settings and the
environment variables I usually like to
create a separate file to hold all of
this information so under
app I'm going to create a new file
called
config.py and I'm going to move all of
that
code into that
file and then in our main py file I'll
just import from config
import
settings right so ultimately we're just
importing that final class the instance
of the class that we
created right and so once again it's
able to perform the validation and it's
going to report an error with the path
variable all right so having it in its
own file is going to make things a
little bit easier because then we could
just go to the config.py file and we'll
know exactly um you know where to look
for all of our environment variables and
all the configs related to our
application the last thing I want to do
is let's go ahead and actually figure
out what environment variables we want
to use moving forward and actually set
this up so we're going to clear out all
of these and I'm going to create one for
all of the database related stuff so
database uncore host name this is going
to be a string by
default we're going to have database _
Port once again a
string we'll have a database
password and then we'll have a database
uncore name so that's the
database within postest that we're
connecting
to we'll need a username all of these
will be
strings and you may be wondering why the
port is set to a string but uh the
reason why it's going to be set to a
string is because if we actually take a
look at our database connection it just
goes into a URL so we don't actually
ever need need to uh have it be an INT I
guess you could make sure that it's a
valid port number and then convert it
back to a string but that seems a little
unnecessary at that point uh then
there's a secret key for our for you
know our Json web
tokens and we've got the
algorithm for signing our token
and then we have the axis
token
expire unor
minutes which is going to be an INT all
right and if we save all of this we
should get a whole bunch of errors and
that's okay because none of these have
been set so at this point you could
technically you know whether you're on a
Windows or Mac set these on your machine
and get everything to work but like I
said that is an unacceptable thing to do
because that's a lot of work and we want
to simplify things so what we can
actually do is with in our fast API
directory we're going to create a new
file called EnV so this is kind of
standard convention but this file and
don't forget the dot this file is going
to contain all of our environment
variables so we can set it much easier
just by having a file do all of the work
now in production you're not going to
use this uh in in production you're
going to actually set it on your machine
but in development it's perfectly okay
to just set everything in here and so
what we're going to do is we're going to
take all of those uh environment
variables that we defined and we're
going to provide values and so like I I
said in real
life you generally want to capitalize
everything um but luckily pantic
automatically looks at everything from a
case insensitive
perspective and so our database right
now is running on Local Host so we can
just say Local Host our database
Port is going to be
5432 the password that's going to be
whatever you chose to use as your
password this going to be password 1 2
3 and we've got our database
name um mine happens to be fast API but
yours is going to be something different
probably the username I'm guessing
everyone's probably going to be using
the default
postest the secret
key I'm just going to grab whatever I
used in my file so I'll just grab this
the algorithm is going to be HS
256 and then the access token expiration
time it's going to be set to
30 so we've got all the values set here
and uh one thing to note I didn't
provide any default values and you could
100% go ahead and add default values
into yours if you want to but I'm going
to leave them as such and now we have to
tell pantic to actually import it from
ourv
file and the way to do that is inside
this class we just say class
config and we say enor file and then the
path to our specific file so we say EnV
so we'll save this
and I forgot to save my EnV file and
then I'm going to run this again and our
applications should start up with zero
issues and so hopefully you guys see how
easy it is to work with environment
variables especially when you're allowed
to set it on a file so that we don't
have to worry about setting it either in
the terminal or uh you know on a Windows
machine having to go through the guey to
do
that but one thing to keep in mind is
that you never want to check this EnV
file into git
right because this has all the
credentials for your development
environment maybe you don't want those
to get out uh and there's no need to
ever check it into git so if you create
a git ignore file so which isg ignore
you want to make sure that you put in
EnV and we'll come back to the get
ignore file when we start working with
Git in this course um but you also want
to make sure you remove anything with
underscore uncore pachore uncore which
is all of these as well as your virtual
environment uh folder so you want to
make sure none of those get checked into
G so they don't get uploaded to your
GitHub repo and just to make sure that
everything's working let's go ahead and
just test this out real quick just to
make sure that nothing's broken and that
seems to work and then if we try to get
all posts everything seems to be working
so we have now successfully moved
everything over to environment variables
and actually sorry we forgot to do one
very important thing we're not actually
using the environment variables right
now because if I actually go to my
database you can see that it's still
just a hard-coded value so we have to
make sure we actually update that to use
the environment variables so we're going
to change this to be an F an F string
and then here this is going to be the
username this is the password uh this is
the host name and then this is the
database name and then there's also
going to be the port number which would
be right here which is 5432 I believe
that's yeah and that's going to be the
port number so what we have to do is
since we're using an F string I can just
remove this and I can
say well first of all we have to import
our config file that we have access to
it or we can do from
config import
settings just put a dot there and now I
can just say settings dot database and
then we'll grab the username
here and then for the password I'm going
to do the same thing I'll
say settings
do database
password and the host
name this is going to be
settings. database host
name and then this going to be the port
number and then finally we've got the
actual database name
I
think everything should still work just
to test this part let's just quickly log
in
now all right everything still works so
we our access to our database is now
working just fine um but there's a few
other things that I want to update and
keep in mind if you were using the uh
the post Crush driver to actually
connect and make queries then you would
just update it here with the settings
whatever um but if we go to our oath 2
we
can well first of all let's
import our
config and we'll change the secret
key now this is going to
be settings
do Secret Key not schema secret key
the algorithm is going to be settings.
algorithm and then finally this is going
to be
settings. access token expire
minutes all right let's reload this
let's uh just double check a few things
so let's uh well let's create a new
user all right we are able to create a
user let's log in that user
we're a to log in and then let's get
posts and we're able to get posts and
let's just double check that there's no
errors so everything looks good and so
now we have successfully migrated all of
our code to using environment variables
and so when we move to production we can
just on the machine set all of these
values that we have inside our config.py
file and it's going to automatically
import it and then update those values
wherever we reference them in any social
media type app there's going to be some
sort of voting or likes system so
Facebook has likes Reddit has up votes
and down votes Instagram has likes
Twitter has likes as well and so we're
going to implement a simple like system
as well and we're going to quickly go
over the requirements for it so the
first thing is a user should be able to
like a post a user should only be able
to like a post once we shouldn't be able
to like a post 10 times and then
artificially cause the number of likes
for that post to go up and then finally
any anytime we retrieve a post from our
database uh or from our API we should
also fetch the total number of likes for
that post now let's take a look at the
requirements for our voting model or our
like model and so naturally just like we
have a table for users and a table for
posts it makes sense to store the votes
in another table just like we always do
and if you think about the requirements
or what we should do for the columns
well we need to have a column that's
going to store the ID of the post that
we're ultimately going to like and then
we're also going to need a column that
references the ID of the user who like
the post so those are the two absolute
minimum number of columns that we need
to get our voting system in place keep
in mind if you wanted to do a you know
an up vote down vote type thing like
Reddit does then you might want to have
a third column for the direction of your
vote but we're going to keep this nice
and simple and it's just going to be a
very simple like system so it's just One
Direction but the most important thing
of the vote table is that since a user
should only be able to like a post once
this means that we need to ensure that
every entry every post ID and voter ID
is a unique combination so what do I
mean by that well take a look at this we
have a post with an ID of 12 and this
post was liked by a user ID of four so
this is what an entry would look like
and that's perfectly fine and if we go
and we here we've got a post ID of 28
and it looks like a user with an ID of 9
like this post and if I go all the the
way down to here you'll see that post ID
of 12 which you could see that there was
already a row with the post ID 12 is
liked by a different user nine so it's
perfectly okay to see a repeat in this
column and under the user ID section
it's perfectly okay to see a repeat uh
in this column as well because we can
see that a user of id9 voted and liked a
post with an ID of 28 as well as a post
with an ID of 12 and then obviously one
post can be liked by different users so
a post with an ID of 12 was liked by a
user with an ID of four and a post with
the the same post was also liked by a
user with an ID of nine now what we
can't have is a user liking a post more
than once so you could see here uh user
2 liked a post with an ID of 55 we can't
have him do that again right it's a
duplicate this isn't allowed or or this
shouldn't be allowed in our system
because we don't want users to be able
to uh live like a post more than once
and so there's a couple of different
ways of setting up this requirement but
we're going to take a look at the
simplest solution and we're going to
learn about something called composite
keys so we've already covered what a
primary key is it's a it's a column in
your table that's going to ensure that
every single entry is unique and we
always used a column um called ID which
had a auto incrementing integer however
what we can also do is make use of
something called composite keys and a
composite key is nothing more than a
primary key that spans multiple columns
so we've only worked with one column
primary keys but we can actually have it
cover more than one column we it can
have two columns or three columns and
since a primary key must be unique this
will ultimately ensure that no user can
like a post twice if we make sure that
both of these columns are part of the
primary key right and so when you have a
composite primary key it does not care
if there's duplicates in one row it does
not care if sorry in one column and it
does not care if there's duplicates in
the other column
all it cares about is are both of the
columns the same in two different rows
so once again you know for a post of ID
12 we have a user of four who likes it
as well as a user of nine that likes it
and so with the composite primary key it
sees that as two different entries
because it needs both of them to be the
same to be considered a duplicate so we
can uniquely identify this row by saying
Hey I want the row with the post ID of
12 and a post ID of 9 there's going to
be no other rows with that combination
and the same thing goes in the other
direction the user 9 can like post 28
and he can also like post 12 and so once
again we can uniquely identify either
one of these rows because we can say hey
post a 28 with the user ID that's a
unique combination and a post ID of 12
with a user ID of 9 once again a unique
combination however we can't have a user
with ID of two like 55 and then once
again the user ID of two like 55 because
the combination of these two is now
duplicate because one is 55 and two and
the other one's 55 and 2 and so that's
all a composite key is it's just a
primary key that spans two columns and
ensures that across both columns we have
unique combinations for
things so let's figure out how to create
our new votes table and I'm going to
first show you guys how to do this
within PG admin so just with regular
postgress and then we'll take a look at
how to do this with SQL
Alchemy and I'm just going to go under
tables and I'm going to create a new
table we call it
votes and then under columns here I'm
going to add a column and this is going
to
be postore ID so this is going to be the
column that referenced the ID of the
specific post this should uh and then um
actually before we do anything else I'm
going to add the other column in as well
and then we're going to have the user
uncore ID and so these are both going to
be integers
and then we can just select primary key
primary key and that's going to create
that composite key and then we have to
set up the foreign Keys as well so these
are going to reference other tables so
for the Post ID we can go into uh
constraints and then we'll go into
foreign key We'll add a new foreign key
and I'm going to call this votes uncore
postscore primary whoops not primary key
foreign
key and actually sorry I didn't mean to
do that and then we're just going to go
into here for the columns we're going to
select the local column which is going
to be post ID sorry it's not post ID
yeah post ID and then for the
referencing table it's going to be the
posts
table and then we're going to grab the
ID of that and for action on delete
we're going to make sure it's set to
Cascade so that if the you if the post
gets deleted we're going to delete this
entry
and then we'll add that in
there oh it looks like it's got deleted
let me just redo this we'll add that and
so we've got that in there now and that
should be it for the first foreign key
let's add another foreign key and this
is going to be called votes uncore users
forign
key columns this is going to be user ID
of the local table this is going to
reference the users table and then it's
going to reference the ID we'll hit that
actions uh this is going to be a Cascade
as
well and we'll save
that and then I'm going to right click
on the votes table and then we can go to
view edit data we'll go to all
rows you can see it's a very simple
table so let's create a
new uh let's create a new vote first uh
and so I'm going to first of all I've
got way too many of these windows so I'm
going to just quickly delete
those all right so I got those deleted
I'm going to open up uh a new
query and I can just go into database
we'll do
query and I'm going to do
select star from
Posts and then select star from users
just so I can get a list of uh post IDs
and user IDs so I got user ID of 21 23
24 and uh for the
post we get
1049 so let's try those
out and I already forgot them so let's
let's get that post ID again uh so we'll
just grab a post ID of 10 so this going
to be 10 and then the user ID well I'm
going to open up a new window so I can
just switch between
them so now we have the both of these
windows for quering and I can do select
star from
users uh 21 okay so we'll do
and it looks like we hit a bug in PG
admin because I can't write anything
here so I'm just going to do view edit
data all rows again and that looks a
little bit better so let's get a post 10
and a user of
21 so
10 21 and let's see if we're
successfully able to get that and looks
like that worked and then if I grab a
post ID that doesn't exist uh so let's
say like
99 and then a valid user let's see what
happens it's going to throw an error
that's good and then if we grab a valid
post number but a ID of a user that
doesn't exist we should also get an
error and then if any of these are
blank and save it should throw an error
as well okay so our table looks set
that's pretty much all we have to do
there's nothing else for these tables
you'll see that once you can create one
table you can really create all so I'm
just going to drop this table for
now and in the next video we'll take a
look at defining our model and SQL
Alchemy so that SQL Alchemy actually
generates the table for
us in our models.py file let's create
our model for our votes
table and we'll call it votes or just
vote it's going to extend
base and then for our table name uh I
think it just makes sense to call it
votes
then let's set up our two
columns so we're going to have a user
ID and then we're going to have a
postore ID so for the user uncore ID
this going to be a
column and it's going to be a type
integer we're going to set up the
foreign
key and this will be users so it's going
to reference the users table and grab
the ID
field and then the second property is
going to be the on delete which is going
to be set to
Cascade right then we'll set the primary
key to be
true and that's pretty much it and then
I'm just going to copy
this paste it here we're just going to
change this to be instead of users's ID
we're going to be it's going to be post.
ID
and I don't know why I got autof
formatted to a different
line okay okay it looks like that's what
it prefers and so save this and assuming
there's no errors our application should
restart and then if we go to PG admin
and then
refresh we should see a votes
table and I'm just going to go and take
a look at the
properties and you can see that we've
got the user ID and the post ID we've
got the primary key set so it's a
composite key and since it's a primary
key not null is going to be set to yes
we go to
constraints we've got you know once
again both of the primary Keys uh we
should have two foreign keys and then if
we just take a look at one of them real
quick we should see Cascade on
delete and so if we go and View and edit
data Let's test this out 10 21
again oh sorry should be 21 and 10
because the user ID is the First Column
now 21 and 10 let's try saving that good
let's try doing 21 and
N or 21 and
88 should error out perfect and then
let's try 10
and some random number error
perfect now there's going to be a couple
things that we need to take into
consideration when setting up the vote
route so first of all what is the path
we're going to use and I think it makes
sense just to set up a new path called
SL vote uh just like we have for SL
users when it comes to handling anything
with users and we have SL poost for
handling anything with post we're going
to have the SL vote for handling
voting now the user ID the user who's
trying to vote on a or like a post uh
the ID of that user is going to be
extracted from the JWT token so we don't
actually have to extract that from the
body we don't need to include it in the
body however the body itself is going to
contain two pieces of information the ID
of the post we're trying to like as well
as uh the direction of the vote and what
I mean by direction is um do they want
to vote on the post or do they want to
remove a post because like any
application you know maybe you
accidentally clicked on a post to like
it but you realize you don't want to
like it so you click on it again to
remove that so vote direction of one
means that we're going to like the post
and then a vote direction of zero means
we're going to remove our like of the
post now in our routers folder we're
going to create a new file which is just
going to be vote. py so this is going to
handle all the routing for our voting
urls
and what I'm going to do is I'm just
going to copy the import statement from
one of the other
routers and we'll set up our route so
let's set up The Decorator first and
this is going to be a
post and I actually have to import
router we got it let's create our router
instance so we'll say router equals API
router
and we'll set up the prefix to
be SL
vote and the tags we're going to give it
its own
section which is going to just
say
vote and now we can do at router. poost
this is going to be a post operation
because we have to send some information
to the
server and the the URL is just going to
be slash so it's just going to be SL
vote
then and since we're going to create a
vote um by default uh we're going to
send a different status code we're going
to send a uh 201 instead of the default
then we'll Define our function which
I'll just call
vote now there's going to be a couple
things that we have to pass in so since
we expect the user to provide some data
in the body it usually means we want to
define a schema just so that we can
ensure they send us the exact
information so let's set up our schema
for
voting we'll create a class called vote
and so the first field should be a post
ID uhu which is going to be of type int
and then we're going to have a
direction which is going to be an
integer as well so it's either zero or
one uh however I I would like to be able
to validate it to ensure that it's only
zero or one I couldn't exactly figure
out if there was a way to do that in
pantic but one thing we can do is we can
use uh Conant so we'll we'll import that
from pantic automatically so if you want
to see the import that's what it's going
to look
like and we can say less than or equal
to one so anything less than one is
going to be allowed the only problem
with this is it allows for negative
numbers um but that's okay uh you know
if you guys figure out how to just
specify zero and one then um you know go
ahead and replace that and definitely
leave it uh leave that piece of
information in the comments so that
anyone else who wants to set up that
specific restriction uh then we all know
how to do that moving forward
and let's import our schema now so we'll
go up a
directory and let's also import
database models and uh we're going to
have to require the user to be logged in
before uh they can vote on something so
let's import awath
2 and so here we're going to set up the
schema and we're also going to set up
the database
so that we can make
queries and then lastly we'll get the
current user
so once we got all those dependencies uh
looks like we have to import session as
well and I'm actually going to move
this right below the first import not
that it matters
but and so we're going to set up logic
for when the vote direction is one so if
I if vote. dur so we're pulling the the
direction from the vote vote schema
equals equals 1 then we're going to
perform some
logic else if it's zero then we're going
to perform some other
logic so if we want to uh create a vote
the first thing we're going to do is
query to see uh you know does the vote
already exist and so what I'm going to
do is I'm going to say db.
query and we'll grab models.
vote and I'm going to filter based off
of models. vote
_
ID and we're going to say it equals
equals vote. postore ID so we're going
to see if there's already a vote for
this specific post ID however this isn't
enough because remember uh multiple
people can vote on the same post so we
actually have to do a second
check and we can add in a second
condition by just doing a comma and then
providing the second condition so we
have to say models. vote. user ID equal
equals current user.
ID and I'm going to save this and we're
going to call this uh vote query so this
isn't going to actually query the
database yet this is just building out
the query and it's going to check to see
if this specific user ultimately has
voted for this specific post already or
liked this post and I'm actually going
to move this above the if
statement and you guys will see why
we're going to do that in a bit
and we're going to then perform the
query and just save that result under
found vote equals vote query. first all
right and so if the user wants to like a
post but we already found a post that
means he's already liked this specific
post so he can't like it again so what
we're going to say is if we already
found a vote then we're going to raise
an HTTP
exception uh now the status code we're
going to use a new status code I'm going
to use status do and then this is going
to be a
409 for conflict and there's other
status codes you could potentially use I
I just decided that this is probably
going to be the best fit and then for
detail we're going to just pass an F
string and say user and then we pass in
the user which is a get whoops current
user.
ID has
already voted on on post with an ID
of vote. postore
ID all right but if we didn't find a
vote then what we're going to do is
we're going to create a brand new vote
so I'll say models. vote and so the post
ID field is going to be set to vote.
poost _ ID and then we can grab the user
ID
field from current user. ID so this will
set the two properties and we'll save
this as newor vote and as usual to
actually perform these changes or to add
this to our database we have to do a db.
add newcore
vote and then a db.
commit and we don't actually need to
send the created vote back to the user
because it doesn't really provide any
useful information uh we're just going
to send a
message that
says successfully
added
vote now if the user provided a
direction of zero that means they want
to delete a pre-existing vote so first
of all we'll say if not found vote right
we can't delete a vote that doesn't
exist so raise an HTTP
exception status code um I think we
could just send a 404
and for the detail I just say vote does
not
exist but if we did find a vote then we
have to delete it so I'll say
vote query remember this is the query
all the way at the top
I'll say.
delete and then we can just do our
synchr synchronized session
balse and we'll do a db.
commit and we'll just return a similar
message successfully deleted vote
okay and this should kind of sum up uh
all of the logic in our path operation
function and at this point we can just
go ahead and test this out so we'll go
back to postman first of all let's log
in all right so we've logged in and what
I'm going to do is create a brand new
request we'll call this vote
and this is going to be a
vote and in the body we have to pass in
the specific data so let's actually grab
a post um or an ID of a post so in this
case there's an ID of
10 actually first let me double check
who I'm logged in as okay that's fine so
I'm going to grab uh a post with an ID
of 10
so here we'll say postore
ID
10 and then we'll say
dur actually is that what we called it I
actually forgot let's go to our
schemas yeah it's just dur
and this is going to be let's let's this
is going to be a one so that we can
actually like the post and remember this
should be a post request so let's try
this out let's hit
send and it looks like we ran into an
issue so let's
check and uh it says that this specific
route was not found uh and so that's
obviously because we didn't wire up this
specific router so let's go back to our
main.py and let's import vote
and then we can just copy
this and wire up vote.
router yep and once again another
typo all right let's give this a try now
so we'll hit
send it says we're not authenticated so
let me login
user all right now let's try
this and it says say that I'm still
unauthenticated and guys I realized why
we're getting uh not authenticated
that's just because we have a new
request and we have to make sure that we
set the authorization to be beer
token and then we want to pass in our
JWT variable so it wasn't actually
retrieving that so now if I try this we
can see that we successfully added vote
and uh you know just make sure that it
actually did that let's actually go into
our database and take a look at our
votes table
and so we like the post uh and it looks
like um I have some previous ones so
what I'm actually going to do is I'm
going to delete everything uh from our
votes table just so we can make sure it
works cuz I forgot who I'm even logged
in as let's go to
properties okay sorry uh let me just do
a
query and I'm just going to say delete
from votes that's going to delete
everything in our votes table perfect
and then we can just say select from
votes we have nothing in there and let's
try this
again all right and so now run this we
can see that we did like Post 10 and I
guess our ID is uh 24 but we can just
quickly verify that I do select star
from users
and I'm logged in as sanji1 123 so we
can see that that has an ID of 24 so
that works now what I'm going to do is
Let's test to see what happens if I try
to vote on a post that I've already
voted on so I'm going to keep the vote
direction to be one and I know I've
already voted on this post so we should
get user 24 has already voted on Post 10
perfect now let's go and try to delete a
post so I'm going to set the vote there
to be zero and let's see what happens it
says I successfully deleted the post
or or the vote and let's just do a quick
query we can see nothing is there and
then if we try to delete a vote or or a
like that doesn't exist we can see that
vote does not exist all right guys we've
actually implemented all of the voting
logic right there the only other thing
that we need to do is when we retrieve a
post right whether it's through the get
all posts or even I get one post I want
to have my fast API send the number of
votes as a property as a field here so
that uh you know when we load up posts
on our front end application they can
see the number of likes that a post has
that's usually how most applications
work and I would like it to have it
automatically send that information
instead of having to send another query
to our back end to see you know what is
the total number of votes I wanted to do
it automatically anytime we retrieve any
post and uh that's going to be a little
bit more complex uh we're going to have
to learn a little bit more about SQL uh
start digging into some of the weeds of
uh SQL and postgress and then once we
learn how to do it with a regular SQL we
have to see if we can do this with um
SQL Alchemy after I finished recording
all of the uh voting logic or at least
the router that handles voting I
realized there's one tiny bug and that
is that right now there's no logic to
actually detect if the user is trying to
vote on a post that doesn't exist
because if they want to vote on a post
that doesn't exist I want to ideally
send a 404 so what we're going to do is
we're going to implement that logic and
it's going to be really simple we're
just going to query for the Post based
off of the ID first if it doesn't exist
we're going to throw an exception so
just like we've done with pretty much
all of our other routers whenever
someone tries to access a post that they
don't uh that doesn't exist then we're
just going to Simply send a
404 so let's start off by making our
query I'm going to do db.
query we'll say models.
poost and then what we're going to do is
we're going to filter based off of the
post ID so we'll say models. post.
ID equals equals
vote. postore ID and then we're going to
grab the first
one and we'll save this in a variable
called
post then we'll say if not post so if
the post doesn't exist then we're going
to raise an HTTP exception
and the status code is going to be a
404 and the detail will be the usual F
string that says uh
post with ID and then we'll pass in the
ID does not
exist and that's all we have to do and
that's going to fix that little bit that
little tiny bug and you'll see that when
we get to the testing section we can now
test to see if the post doesn't exist as
well up till now we've been working with
very simple queries we've just been
querying a single table however now that
we have more than one table uh and all
of these tables have built out these
relationships you're going to see that
eventually you want to be able to get
information from two tables at the same
exact time and this gets a little
complicated but the way we actually do
that is by using something called a join
so we join two tables together and as an
example uh let's say I want to get all
of my posts so I do a select star from
Posts that's great and all however you
know when we're sending back the the
posts to the user right the or our front
end our front end has no idea what uh a
owner ID of 23 is he doesn't know what
that is and we ultimately want to
display the username or the email uh of
the the user that created that post on
our front end so what we would have to
do if we can only uh you know retrieve
data from one table at a time is we'd
have to then individually go and then
fetch all of these users from the user
table one by one so that we can actually
get the email or or the username and
that's a little inefficient having to do
multiple queries if you ever get a
chance to uh it's better to just do a
single query uh and get all of the
pieces of information that you're
interested in so I'm going to show you
guys how we can join information from
two tables CU I would also like to get
all of the user information based off of
the owner ID field that's on the posts
table so how do we do that well we start
off a query just like this and actually
before we go into this what I would like
to do is show you one of my favorite
websites uh so if you go to postgress
tutorial just search for that in
Google uh you'll see that there's a
website called postgressql tutorial.com
this is one of my favorite sites and I
want you to go to Jo joins right here so
this is how we get information from two
different tables and this this page uh
you know does an absolute marvelous job
of explaining how to actually uh join
two tables and it goes over the
different types of joins because there
isn't just one method uh you've got left
joins you have inner joints you got
outer joints you got right joins um and
I strongly suggest you guys quickly just
kind of read through this just to get an
idea um because I don't want to cover
every single joint I'm just going to
show you the ones that we need to get
the data that we're interested in
so let's go back to postgress and let's
create our first join so here I'm do
select I'm just grabbing all of the
fields and I'm going to grab it from the
post table and what we can do is I can
say left
join and then we specify the other table
we want to jam into my query so now I
want to get data from the users table so
I do users and then we have to find a
field uh in both tables that we need to
match on or join the table on and since
we want to find the specific user
associated with the person who created
this post we need to join on the owner
ID so what we say
is on so this is how we specify what it
should join on and we want to say uh we
grab the first table's name right the
posts table we grab post and then we say
dot and then we grab the specific column
we want to join on so owner
ID and then we just say it equals 2 and
then we grab the second table which is
called users and then we Gra gra the
specific column from the users table you
want to join on which is users. ID so
now if I run this take a look at that it
took all of the user data and it jammed
it right into one single query with the
post and so now I get the entire post
and I also get information about this
specific user because we joined on owner
ID and the user ID uh together so it was
able to kind of take that information
from the other table and match match it
right up to here because we did a star
it's going to grab the columns from it's
going to grab every single column from
every single from both of the tables and
there may be times where maybe you don't
want that maybe we just want a couple of
columns so let's say we want uh the
title
column maybe we want content and maybe
we want
email right and this should allow us to
grab the title which comes from the post
table and the content which comes from
the uh post table and then email which
comes from the user table so let's see
what happens when I run this right you
can see I got the title content and
email now if I remove this and go back
to everything just real quick let's say
I want to get the post
ID and the email well let's see what
happens I'm going to do ID and then
email well it looks like we have an
error it says column reference ID is
ambiguous so what exactly is happening
here well I'm going to remove this and
show you exactly what
happened the problem is is that the post
table has a column called ID and the
user table has a column called ID so
when I just say ID it has no idea which
column I want so that's why it's saying
it's ambiguous so what we need to do is
anytime there's a potential for
confusion we always have to specify the
table name before so I can say posts. ID
and then I can say email
now I don't have to say uh you know
user. email because only the users table
has an email column however if there was
an email column in the post table as
well then we would have to append the
table name first so you only need to do
this when there's confusion however if
you want to just kind of stick to a
certain convention you can just set up
every single property to have the table
name beforehand so that you know which
table it's coming from makes it a little
bit easier to read and so now I got just
the ID and the email
now let's say I want to get every field
from one of the tables I can say posts
do star that's going to grab every field
so it's grabbing the post table and then
the star means hey grab every single
column and so I can do that it's going
to grab everything from the post table
and then I can grab maybe just the email
in this case and so this kind of
ultimately does what we had wanted it to
do um because you know I told you guys
uh we want to be able to get the email
or the username information for each and
every single post and if we want to you
know we can add in some of the other
fields maybe
the maybe the user. ID so the user ID
however that's just going to match up
with the owner ID but just to show you
guys there is some
flexibility and as I mentioned before
there are different types of joins
there's left join there's right join
inner join outer join I don't want to
spend too much on it but I do want to
cover just a few things all right so the
direction references which table so
right now we're working with two tables
there's the first table that's
referenced by uh from and then the name
of the table and then there's the second
table which is referenced after the join
which is right here and so the first
table that's referenced is always
referred to as the left table and the
ref uh the table on the right the second
table that's mentioned is always going
to be the right table so you got the
left table and the right table and so
when we do join what it's actually doing
is well I think this page actually gives
us the best explanation so left
join select data from the left table and
I don't know if this is big enough for
you guys but I'll zoom
in so it's going to select data from the
left table it's going to compare the
values uh between the two columns that
we have selected and for us in this case
it's going to be uh post. owner ID on
the left side and then users. ID on the
right
side and it's going to find where those
values match and if they are equal the
left join creates a new row that
contains The Columns of both tables and
adds this row to the result
set and what's important is in case the
value does not equal the left joint also
creates a new row that contains the
column from both tables and adds it to
the result set however on the right side
uh the the value is going to be set to
null so if we ever had a
post that didn't have an owner ID then
what would happen is we would see the uh
the user information all set to null in
that case or the email would be set to
null however since the way we set up our
table is is that every single uh post
must have a owner ID we're never going
to run into that situation now before we
move any further just to show you guys
what a right join is it's the exact same
thing but in the opposite
direction and so let's take a
look and things look a little bit
different now um because what's
happening is that we're going to is that
we're going to go through the two tables
and find if the owner and the owner ID
and the ID of the user match and we're
going to join it on that and we're going
to do this for every single
entry and then at the end you can see
that user 24 has no information on the
left side and that's because user 24
didn't create any post so the right join
will show you instances where something
exists in the right table but it doesn't
exist on the left table the left join
will show you something that exists in
the left table but doesn't necessarily
exist on the right table but I'm going
to change this back to left join
and now what I would like to do is uh it
would be great if we can uh get the
number of posts by each user right how
many posts has each user created so is
there a way to do that well there is
actually so what I'm going to do here
is I'm going to grab
the users. email actually users. idid
and maybe want the users. email as well
as well actually we'll just get the
ID and here at the end I'm going to say
I want to group
by
users.
ID so we're going to find all of these
entries in our join uh and then group
them based off of the user ID field from
the user column and so once we group
them we can then actually count up all
of the columns uh sorry all of the
entries on a per user basis so if I say
user ID and then we say we can use a
built-in postest
function and here if I put in Star and
I'll come back and explain what this
means we can hit run and we can see that
the user with an ID of 21 has 11 posts
and the user with an ID of 23 has two
posts the only issue is if I actually do
another query right here and do select
star from
users there's actually three users right
and one of them hasn't made any posts
and so that's why we don't see it in
that list and if we want to be able to
see it in that list we need to actually
change our query and like I mentioned
the right join if I actually remove the
count column right
here and we just do a
star this is going to actually uh list
every single user even if the user has
no posts and so if I remove the group by
ID real
quick right you could see down here I
have user 24 with no post that's exactly
what we want and so now I can say Group
by users.
ID and then here I'm going to say select
users. ID and then we grab the
count so let's see if this
works uh and notice how all of the post
fields are completely empty so that's
that's perfectly fine and then we can
run this and you can see that it it
seems to have worked all right user us
21 has 11 posts user 23 has two post and
then we got user 24 but it says that uh
there's a value of one and the reason
for that is that when you do star right
here that means it's going to count null
entries so since we have that one null
entry it's going to count that as one so
instead what we're going to do is we can
actually pass in the name of a column
and so once again I'm actually going to
copy this paste it into here we're going
to remove the group I
and then just do a star so we're going
to get every entry except because we did
Count star it always ends up counting
this as one so that user 24 is always
going to have one entry but that's not
accurate because he doesn't actually
have any so instead of doing count star
we can actually pass in a
column that we want to count and so in
this case we can pick any of the posts
column that we're trying to retrieve and
so I can just say post do idid uh and so
when you pass in a column name it does
not count columns that have a null value
so if the user doesn't have any posts he
won't have anything under post. ID and
then if I just remove this query and
then run this you can see that now I
have successfully gotten the exact query
that I want and I can rename this column
as uh user undor postore count or
something it's a little bit read more
readable and then you know I can grab
any other field that I want maybe I also
want the users.
email and so that way we get just the
information that we ultimately want so
you can see that doing these queries
they do get a little bit more complex
and you have to practice this a lot and
so I definitely recommend you actually
just read through this document set up a
few example tables and just practice
doing your queries um but we're going to
spend just a little bit more time on
these queries so that we can uh figure
out how to get the total number of votes
it is a little bit longer of a process
but I want to make sure that you guys
understand exactly what we're doing all
right guys so let's move on to working
with our posts table and our votes table
so I want to do a join on those two so
let's start off by doing select uh and
then we'll just do star for now and
we'll say select star
from and then in this case post and keep
in mind guys I mentioned that the first
table you reference is the left table
and the second table uh that you
reference is the right table uh it
doesn't actually matter which one is the
left or right uh the only thing that
matters is that you set up the right
direction of the join so if we set up
posts as the left table and we want to
do a left join then if we ever rewrite
our SQL query and set up our um our
votes table to be the left table instead
then we would just have to flip the join
to be a right join so it doesn't matter
which table comes first keep that in
mind so you don't have to start your
query on just the post you could do this
on votes as well and you just change the
direction of the
join but I like to do
posts and then we're going to try a left
join once
again and we'll say uh that the other
table is going to be votes and we're
going to join on well uh if we take a
look at our votes table which I'm
actually just going to cut this out real
quick and save that in my scratch
Pad I'm going to just say select star
from
votes we'll run that right so there's
going to be a user ID and a post ID and
then if I do a select
star from Posts
we have all these fields so I think you
guys can guess uh the exact column that
we need to join on so we need to join on
post. ID and then votes
dot. postore ID so whenever those match
we need to get a result so I'm going to
go into my application and just run a
few uh I'm just going to vote on a few
posts so that we actually have some data
so I'm logged in as a user and I'm going
to vote on Post
10 all right we successfully added add
votes I'm going to get a whole bunch of
other
posts I'm going to vote on post four and
nine all right and um I'm going to log
in as a different user now let's see who
else I
got all right I'll just log in as San I
guess my login
all right we've logged
in and I'm going to vote on Post 10 as
well on this
guy and then we'll grab some random vote
uh
15 okay and so we should have a decent
number of votes now and I purposely made
it so that one of the users didn't vote
just so that we can take a look at what
complications that add all right so we
have all of these votes and we've got
the user ID and the post ID so now let's
set up a join so I'm going to do select
star from
Posts and I'm going to start off with
the left
join and we'll say we want to join with
the votes table and the field that we're
going to join on is on the posts we're
going to grab the ID and the and
wherever this is equal to
votes. postore ID we want to join the
table so let's run
this and let's see what results we get
back all right and so you can see that
hey look uh they post with an ID of
10 it looks like it does
have uh a vote so this is one join right
here but then you'll notice that I if I
go down you'll see another entry so this
doesn't mean in our database that we
have two posts with an ID 10 is just
saying that since we joined them we have
to go down the list see where they match
and then print out a row so it's going
to print out a row for every single time
the post ID matches the postore ID of
the votes table and so since we have two
votes for this same exact post that
means we're going to get two different
entries doesn't mean there's actually
two posts in our table it's just the way
that the joins work and I strongly
recommend like if this is still a little
confusing keep reading that document and
play around with it if you want to see
the opposite
actually before we take a look let's
just take a look at a few other things
uh you can see we've got post with four
and we can see that there's uh one vote
for that because there's no other uh
entries here with for an idea four and
then we can see all of these posts that
have no votes whatsoever so that's what
the left join gives us because uh
anytime we have a post which is the left
table since we do a left join it's going
to list those posts uh and it'll just
put null on the right side whereas if we
change this to a right join it's going
to do the exact opposite
it on with the right join right once
again it's going to look for Anytime the
uh the ID here matches the post ID and
it's going to spit out a row and then
the same thing goes for the post with an
ID of four and then once again you can
see 10 shows up twice because two users
voted on it and then 15 and so on but
then you'll see nothing else and the
reason for that is we did a right join
so it's going to show us all of
the votes and their corresponding post
however it's also going to list out any
votes because it's a it's a right join
that don't that aren't associated with
the post now all of our votes have to be
associated with the post cuz we put in
that constraint that check so that's why
we don't see anything with a null on the
left side because that's just the way
our tables have been set up so hopefully
that didn't confuse you guys we're going
to change this back to left
join and what we're going to do now is
we're going to do um I want to be able
to count the total number of votes for
each and every post so we're once again
going to do the group by so we're going
to group
by
post. ID so we'll group them together
and then count
them and for columns I'm just going to
say uh we'll say post.
ID and then we want the count so we'll
start off with the star and let's see
what
happens okay uh so we can see that that
you know post with an ID of 10 we know
it has two
votes but then everything else has a
value of one this is not correct we know
that a whole bunch of posts don't have a
value of one but like we covered in the
previous lesson uh anytime you have a
value of null then it's going to count
that as one so I'm going to run this the
previous
query remove the group
by and I'll show you guys exactly what I
mean so now if I run this oops this
should be a
star all right look at all of these
posts that have a value of null it's
going to count them all as one in this
case and we don't want that right that's
why that's what happens when you do uh
star in the count field so instead what
we're going to do
is we're going to provide a specific
column to count on so it doesn't count
the null values so what column should we
use uh I mean we can really use any
column I think it makes sense just to do
uh we have to grab one of the columns
that are null in this case so we'll get
votes. postore
ID so now look at that we get the post
ID and then we get how many votes they
have altogether or how many
likes and instead of just grabbing the
ID I'm going to actually grab everything
from the post table we can run that and
this is the exact query that we're
looking for we get the post information
and we get the number of votes and we
can rename this cuz I don't like calling
a account we can rename it as you know
votes or likes it doesn't really
matter and there you go guys and if you
guys want to um query for an individual
post and get the total number of votes
it's actually very simple it's the same
exact query we're just going to provide
a wear condition and so here I can just
say
where post. ID equals 1
well actually I don't have a post ID of
one so I'll grab a post ID of
10 and so now I get my one post and we
can see that he should have two votes
all right and so that's how we do this
with uh raw
SQL Hopefully this wasn't too
complicated uh like I said I strongly
recommend you spend a little bit of time
uh going over joins and practicing it
with your own tables don't just use
posts and votes uh if you can probably
come up with simpler tables to work on
this and and understand it a little bit
better but I think that's going to wrap
up this video and so go ahead and just
save these queries for now uh so that we
can reference them later in the last
video we saw how we can gather
information from two different Tables by
making use of joins and so we saw how to
do that with raw SQL and now we're going
to see how we can perform joins using
SQL
Alchemy and if you go to your post
router we're going to go to the get
posts path operation uh and so we're
going to kind of just take this this
step by step and see how we can slowly
build out this query uh so that we can
actually perform a join and if you take
a look at the current query uh what we
can do is just ignore all of the filter
stuff
first and so really the the meat of this
query is just db. query and then you
pass the model and that's going to get
every single post that we have in this
table and then we perform all of these
filters to kind of drill down so we're
going to start off with the same thing
and I'm going to save this new query as
results or or we could just say postore
votes maybe and we'll just save it as
results and so we're going to start off
with the same exact query we're going do
db. query models
dopost and we're going to perform do
all actually remove the dot
all and the reason I don't want to do
the dot all is I don't actually want to
query the table I just want to actually
see the raw SQL that's it's generating
and now we can do a print
results I'm going to bring this up a bit
and we're going to just send a query to
the get all
posts and you can see the raw SQL that
it generated so it's going to select and
basically select every column and then
rename it uh accordingly and then it's
just going to get that from the post
table so it's getting every single post
that's all so everything is pretty
straightforward at this
point and if we go back to our um PG
admin let's actually take a
look uh let's take a look at what our
SQL query actually looks like and so you
you can see here there's a whole bunch
of things going on but the next thing I
want to do is I want to actually start
to perform the join so I want to join on
the votes table so let's take a look at
how we can do that and to perform a join
with SQL Alchemy I can just say
join and then we have to specify the
table we want to join so this is going
to be the models.
vote and then the second thing is what
is going to be our the uh what is going
to be the column that we perform a join
on so in this case you could see that
we're performing a join on post. ID and
votes. postore
ID and we're going to do the same thing
here I'm going to say
models. vote. postore ID equals equals
and then we'll say models.
post. ID whenever they're equal we're
going to join the table now the thing
about this join is by default with SQL
Alchemy this is going to be a left inner
join and the word inner is going to be a
little bit new for you um and that's
because there's two different types of
left joins you've got left inner and you
have left outer and I don't want to
spend too much time kind of diving into
what's the difference just know that if
you ignore the keyword it's going to by
default be an outer so what we want is
an outer join um however SQL Alchemy by
default uses
um inner joins so to actually set this
as an outer join we have to pass one
more thing which is going to be is outer
equals true so this is going to make
this a uh outer left outer join so we've
got our join at this point and what I'm
going to do now is save this again and
let's take a look at our query so we'll
send something and now we'll take a look
at our query we can see that okay we're
going to select everything from our post
table then we're going to perform a left
outer join with votes uh on the table
votes whenever votes. poost ID equals
post. ID so we're almost there uh the
next thing that we have to do is we have
to group by post. ID
and then we have to perform the count on
votes. postore
ID and so if you can take a guess as how
to do group by we can just dot Group by
and then we specify the specific column
so we'll do models. poost do
ID and then we have to get the count so
we'll go here and I'm going to say well
first all we have to import a function
so what you're going to do is from SQL
Alchemy import Funk and so this is going
to give us access to functions like
count I'm going to say funk.
count and then we'll say models. vote.
postore
ID we'll save this and I'm going to send
this and let's take a look at the query
once again and so we've got select posts
all of the post columns good good good
good uh and then we get to count right
and it's going to perform the count
that's all right however we're naming it
as count one I don't like that I want to
name this something that I will
understand so maybe something like votes
so we have to figure out a way to rename
this column and if you want to rename
this column you just say dot label and
then the name that you want to give that
column so we're going to call this a
votes and so let's test this out one
last time and now we can see that the
column is called
votes so this is exactly what we want
this is the exact query that we
generated in PG admin manually we're
just doing it through SQL
Alchemy and what we're going to do is
well let's actually perform the query
we'll do
all I don't need the print anymore and
we're going to actually return results
and let's see what
happens so now if I send a
query it's giving me a whole bunch of
errors and if we scroll to the top of
the errors uh we can see that these are
all pantic validations uh and so it's
saying that hey there's no title there's
no content there's no ID there's no
owner ID there's no owner all of these
fields seem to be
missing and why exactly is that well
let's take a look at the response model
so the validation is happening because
we use this response model of schema.
poost and so if we go to
schemas and we find our post object or
post class you can see that expects an
ID a create ated at an owner ID an owner
uh and all of that good stuff and it's
saying that none of these have been set
so it looks like there's something wrong
with our query but just to make this a
little bit simpler what I'm going to do
is I'm actually going to
remove the response model so I'm going
to just comment out that remove the
response model so we're not actually
performing any
validation and we're going to see what
this looks like now so when we retrieve
the data I want you to take a look at
what this looks like so this right here
is one specific post and so after our
changes we can see that we've got a
property called post and then within
there we have ID published and so on and
then we've got a property of votes and
I'm actually going to copy this as an
example and I'm just going to create a
new
file and I'm just going to say we'll
just call this example py that's fine it
doesn't really matter we'll delete this
in a bit so this is what it looks like
and when we go back to our path
operation
I'm going to return
posts and we can actually return the
response model just to see what that
looks
like and so now if I do a
query I need to
save right if you take a look at the
query this is what it looks like in a
working State before we set up the
joins and if I go down to my example
where's my example py
file so this is what pantic
expects expects to get an object with a
field of title content published ID and
so on however after I join something odd
happens we have a field called post and
that breaks everything because it
doesn't expect the ID and the published
and the owner to be under this uh this
essentially this dictionary right here
and that's why it's throwing all of
these errors so how exactly do we fix
this well what we're going to do is I'm
actually going to go to my schemas
and I'm actually going to create a new
schema so we'll call this um You can
call this whatever you
want maybe post Vote or I'm just going
to call this post
out and this is going to be a post base
it's going to expend post base and what
we're going to do is we're just going to
try to match this as close as possible
so this is going to represent a post
object and then we're going to have a
field called votes which is going to be
an
integer so here I can just say uh we
have something called post and don't
forget to capitalize it because our quer
for some reason returns it with the
capital P took me a little while to
figure that out I was running into a few
issues but we can go here and we can say
I want to return uh I want this to be of
type and then we'll reference this
post right so all of these fields will
be under a field name post and then we
expect something called votes which is
going to be set to an
integer so let's try this out and we'll
go back to our post post. py and I'm
going to call I'm going to reference
post
out and we're going to return results
again and let's just make sure there's
no errors it looks like it's good and
let's see what happens now all right we
got a little bit of an
issue and it looks like there's a title
content title content a whole bunch of
errors and so the title and the content
are missing for both so what did we do
wrong here this should have fixed our
issue well let's try adding this uh
class config
orm uh I think that might actually be
what's causing this problem and now
let's try
this that didn't look like it fixed it
all right guys so I was playing around
with it and then I don't know what
exactly fixed it but all I did was uh I
had changed this to a lowercase
p and this led to you know us seeing
this specific issue where it says you
know hey this post doesn't exist and
then as soon as I recapitalized
it all the sudden it started to to work
again it starts to work now so I'm not
really sure why it broke in the first
place I didn't change any other code uh
just looking back at my path operation
you can see that I'm now changing my
response model to be schema. poost out
and then we're performing the same
results query and then returning it for
some reason or another it's now properly
working I have no idea what changed I
have no idea exactly what changed but
it's working now so hopefully you guys
don't run into any issues and hopefully
it was just some kind of issue on my
machine but if you do run into the same
issue just try moving it to a lowercase
try restarting the application then
changing it back I have no idea why that
would fix it but seems to have done
something and so now our results are
perfect we get the post information we
still fetch the owner which is fantastic
and then we have the votes and then just
double check to make sure that all of
your votes are all okay uh and so it
looks like they all look good I know
that one had two and then the rest
should all have zero so everything's
looking pretty pretty good the next
thing that we need to do is actually uh
go ahead and add our filters back in so
let's see if I can still filter on all
of these and so I'm just going to copy
this and then before I perform the the
dot all I'm going to paste that in there
oops I forgot
to I forgot to
copy all right and then let's test this
out again right things are still working
but let's just add a few extra uh query
parameters so I'll say search equals
beaches
all right and then it looks like it
should only return post with the word
beaches and then let's try
limit equals
2 remove this search for
now and that works too so it looks like
we get to keep all of the same
functionality that we had before so I'm
going to just write this as posts we're
going to comment this out just for
reference and then we're going to return
post like we normally
do send it one more time and it looks
like everything is still working just
fine
perfect so we finished the uh get
multiple posts path operation or get all
posts and I noticed that we do have to
go ahead and update the get individual
post because right now if we go to get
one
post you can see that we do not actually
get the votes vote count for that so we
definitely want to see that in here and
we're going to have to perform the same
exact join so I'm just going to copy the
previous query all the way way up to uh
before the filter so just copy that
part say post equals paste that in
there and then we can filter copy this
filter at the
end and that should ultimately get us
what we want I'm going to comment this
one
out and keep in mind we have to return
post out instead of post now because we
want the uh the new format with the
votes so now if I hit
send name post is not
defined oh okay misspelled
that and looks like we fixed that one
and then it's really up to you to see if
you want to um you know kind of worry
about creating posts and updating posts
uh to make sure that you know when they
create an update that they uh return the
number of votes but it's ultimately up
to you I I think we don't need it in
those uh this more of just kind of
returning back uh just the main
information about the post and then you
know the queries for updating uh a
specific post and then grabbing the
votes gets a little complicated so we're
going to ignore that for the update and
the uh and the create post functionality
now when it comes to building out the
tables or the database schema SQL
Alchemy has a little bit of a limitation
and that is that SQL Alchemy doesn't
allow us to modify tables it doesn't
allow us to create extra columns delete
columns add foreign key constraints and
that's because when we Define these
models what SQL Alchemy does is it
checks to see if the specific table name
already exist in our postris database
and if it does it's not going to touch
it so if we make any changes it will
never push out those changes
it'll only create these tables if it
doesn't already see a table with that
specific name and so we've had to resort
to dropping all of our tables and then
restarting our application so that SQL
Alchemy builds it from scratch that's
something we can't obviously do in
production that would be an unacceptable
thing to do and just to show you guys uh
in case you've forgotten if we go to my
our post database and we go we can see
that we've got our three
tables now if I add a phone number class
sorry a phone number uh
column to our user class and I'll set
this column to be just a string and this
is really just for demonstration
purposes you guys don't have to do this
if I save this and reload this SQL
Alchemy will not go into postgress and
actually create that column if I refresh
this and then go into users properties
you can see that it is not
here and so that's the limitation of SQL
alamy and so in this section what we're
going to do is we're going to take a
look at another tool that'll allow us to
do a couple things first of all it's
going to allow us to automatically
update the columns based off of the
models that we Define here so moving
forward when we add this phone number
column it's going to automatically
update our postgress database and this
tool is called olymic it is what we
refer to as a data database migration
tool however it's much more powerful
than that right it's able to allow us to
uh you know create incremental changes
to our database and actually track it
kind of like we do with code so uh in
the in this lesson and in the next
coming lessons we're going to take a
look at Olympic we're going to see
everything it has to offer and I'm going
to hopefully get you guys at least a
solid understanding of how to work with
Olympic so that when you guys work on
your projects you can immediately get
Olympic installed running and then
manage your databases using Olympic
instead of having to either do it
manually or or use any other kind of
unusual
workaround now one of the motivations
for a database migration tool is uh came
from the fact that developers can track
changes to their code and roll back
their code easily with Git and they
wanted to be able to do the same thing
for our database models and our database
schema uh and so they went about
implementing what is referred to as
database migration tools and so a
database migration tool just allows us
to incrementally track changes to our
schema and roll back those changes to
any point in time and so as we go
through our project you know we kept
adding new tables and new features uh
what a database migration tool is uh
it's going to allow us to track those
changes and so if we ever want to go
back to a specific point in time so that
we can kind of troubleshoot code at that
point in time it's so easy it's just one
simple command and it's going to
automatically update our database so
that the schema matches what it was at
that specific point in time and so that
tool that we're going to use like I
mentioned is going to be alumic and uh
what's great about alumic is that it can
also automatically pull all of our SQL
alemy models uh and generate the proper
tables based off of them all right so
this is the documentation for almic so
it's just alm. sq.com dog and if you
want to kind of follow along just select
the tutorial right here and this is just
going to give you kind of a quick walkr
of how to get Olympic set up um but I'm
going to show you guys this so you don't
actually have to follow the tutorial so
we're going to do a first of all we have
to install the library so we'll do pip
install
olymic and so that'll get Olympic
installed and what it does is it
actually gives us access to the Olympic
command so if I do almic
d-el and actually before we proceed any
further I want you to go ahead and
delete phone number we don't actually
need that
anymore and then go to your application
and actually close that out stop it so
that it doesn't automatically restart
for any other reason and then also what
we're going to do is I'm actually going
to delete all of our tables so that we
can actually take a look at how this
works so do delete drop and if you try
to drop this table it's going to say we
can't drop it due to the foreign key
constraint that's okay we can just do
drop Cascade and that's going to delete
it and we're just going to do that for
all of
them all right so now let's get back to
Olympic I'm going to make this bigger
for you guys all right and so we'll do
Olympic d-el to see what commands we
have and the first thing that we have to
do is we have to initialize olymic and
what that's going to do is it's going to
actually create an olymic directory for
us so we'll do almic in it
and then I'm just going to do d-el to
see if we need to pass in any extra
flags and then we have to give it a
directory name so when we run this
command it's going to create a directory
I'm going to name the directory almic
you could call it DB database whatever
you want to call it but I'm just going
to call it almic so it's going to create
a folder called
olymic and so you can see that we've got
this folder called olymic and notice how
it gets installed outside of uh the app
folder which is what we want and it also
created this olymic file so we'll take
look at both of those and the first
thing that we want to do is so go up
into olymic and there's really m one
main file it's the EMV py so this is
kind of like the the King Kong
configuration
file and there's going to be a couple of
things that we have to add to this file
to make sure that things work because
almic works with the SQL Alchemy and the
models uh that you build with SQL
Alchemy we need to make sure that it has
access to our base our base object right
here so we have to import this base
object into the env. py file so I'm
going to just go right here and we're
going to say from and what we're going
to do is how do we actually get to that
database file uh that um That Base
object we have to go into app and then
we go into go into database and then
we'll import
base all right and so this is kind of
give us access to all of those SQL
Alchemy models and then for Target
metadata instead of saying none what we
want to do is we want to get base so
we're
accessing this should be a capital
B actually let's just double check that
it's capitalized uh yep it's capitalized
here so we'll go to base and then we
want to make sure we grab
metadata so that's all we have to do to
rig this up to SQL alamy the next thing
that we have to do is if we go to
almic we have to pass in one value here
which is the SQL Alchemy URL uh which is
basically what's the URL to access our
postrest
database and so just to show you what
this is going to look like this is going
to be fundamentally no different than
the URL that we used uh within database.
py uh which is this one right here H and
so I'm just going to write this
out just going to copy this first part
right here because I can never remember
that
and so
here just going to copy that so we say
postgressql and uh optionally with the
URL you can do a plus and then whatever
driver you're using so if you don't
provide the driver it's going to use
whatever the default driver is um but
we're using uh let's see which driver
what is our
driver if I do pip freeze it's going to
be this one right here so this is the
default driver for postest so you don't
actually need a provide it but if you
did you could just say plus Psy
copg2 but like I said it's the default
one so it's optional right then we have
to give it the username so what's the
username um that's going to be using to
log into your postgress database for me
it's just postgress the password is
going to be password
123 uh it's going to be running on Local
Host uh and then if you want to you can
provide the port which is 5432 and then
your database name which is fast API for
me so this is Ultimate
what the URL is going to look like and
at this
point Olympic is set up and ready to run
however you know just like I just like
we did before I don't like the fact that
we're hardcoding this data in here uh
it's gross we're saving our password uh
and if we move into our production
server it's not going to work properly
because they're not going to use these
credentials or this IP so instead of
doing this what we're actually going to
do is we're going to override this value
that's stored in this file within the
env. py file and so under this config
right here I'm going to set a new uh
option under the config object I'm going
to say config do set underscore
maincore
option and then here we can override any
options that we have in here so I'm
going to override this SQL Alchemy URL
so no matter what I put in here we're
actually going to overwrite it and here
you just pass in a string so SQL Alchemy
URL so that's the the value we're going
to
override and then we're going to pass in
our
string so I can just cut this out and
it's okay to just leave this blank
here all right and so we've hardcoded
the string here so we haven't
technically fixed anything but what
we're going to do is just like we have
in our database. py file you could see
that we're using the settings object
right that comes from our config file um
which is making use of this pantic class
where we can grab it from our
environment variable and so what we're
going to do is we're going to do the
same exact thing we did with main right
we imported settings and we're just
going to do that in our env. py file so
we can access all of uh our environment
variables so I'm going to say from
app.config
import
settings and so now I have access to the
settings object I can override all of
these so this is going to be the
username so I can say setting
do
username and actually I don't think
that's what it is it's database
username and then we'll override the
password which is settings.
database
password and in reality instead of just
typing this all out myself um we
actually have this written out in our
database. py file so I can just copy
this this
here and that way we don't waste too
much
time okay so we've got our URL set and
we're not hardcoding any values and at
this point almic should be set to
actually connect to our database and
modify any of the tables generate tables
uh and be able to really perform any
actions that we wanted to moving forward
hey guys I made one tiny little mistake
if you take a look at where we're
importing base I wrote app. database and
if we take a look at that it looks like
we are grabbing our base right here but
this is not the one we want instead what
we want to do is we want to import it
from Models so we want to import base
which is technically getting imported
from that same file but by doing it from
here it'll allow olymic to read all of
these models and if we do it directly
from database it's not going to work so
what I want you guys to do is go to your
uh env. py file and just change this
from app. database to app.
models and that should fix any potential
issues that you could have okay so just
to quickly recap uh we have cleared out
all of our tables so there's nothing in
our postest database we don't have any
tables defined and we're going to do
this all through almic but what I want
to do is I want to kind of go through
this like we would have if we had
already known about Olympic from the
start of our project project and so
we're going to take this step by step
right because when we first started
creating tables in our post course
database we kind of went along with what
we were working on in our app so the
first thing we did was uh we created a
post
table and that's because we didn't learn
about how to actually create users we
didn't learn about hashing passwords we
haven't gotten to the user section so we
originally just had a post table with a
couple of fields and then after working
through our code once we finished all
the crud operations for post we then
learned how to register users and at
that point we had to create a table for
users and then after that the next
logical step was Hey how do we set up
the relationship between posts and users
then we had to modify that and set up a
foreign key and then finally after that
the last thing that we had to do was we
created a voting table or a votes table
and then we set up all of the necessary
foreign keys for that so we're going to
so we're going to do this step by step
just kind of like how we did it with our
uh our project um but we're going to do
this with the database so that you can
see how we would have done it if we had
already known how to work with a lmic
all right so first things first do a
lmic
almic d-el just to see what commands we
have uh and so there's a few different
commands but the first one that I want
to focus on is revision so when we want
to make a change to our database we
create a revision so the revision is
what really tracks all of the changes
that we make uh on a step-by-step BAS
basis so we're going to do almic
revision
d-el and and we'll see the different
options that we have in our disposal uh
the first one is that I well really the
only one that I care about is the dhm
flag so it's kind of like a when you do
a get commit you can add a-m a message
so that you can kind of uh have a human
readable name associated with each
revision so I'm going to say get sorry
not get olymic revision DM and I'm gonna
say this is going to be
uh create post table so the this
revision is going to be responsible for
creating a post
table we'll run that and I want you to
notice something right you could see
that it created this file under the
version so the versions folder under the
Olympic folder is going to contain all
of our
changes and if we take a look at the
revision there's a couple things to note
uh so you'll see that we import op from
the olymic library and then we import
essay from the SQL Alchemy library and
then you can see the revision ID that it
gives it and then there's going to be
two different functions that are empty
at the moment so these functions are
pretty important uh what they are is the
upgrade function when we run the upgrade
uh what it does is it runs the commands
for making the changes that you want to
do so in this case we want to create a
post table so what we're going to do is
we're going to put all of the logic for
creating a post table within this
function and then if we ever want to
roll back right if maybe I create the
table and I realize I messed it up and I
don't want it anymore then we have to
put in all of the logic in the downgrade
function to handle removing the table so
the upgrade just handles the changes and
the downgrade handles rolling it back
but it's all manual you have to Define
how to do all of that so let's go ahead
and set up the upgrade function and
let's configure uh all of the necessary
columns for our post table all right and
if you ever want to take a look at the
documentation for this uh what you want
to do is Select documentation here here
and then you want to go down down down
all the way down to API details and you
want to go to ddl internals so this is
going to show you how to actually um
perform the various operations so if you
want to create a column if you want to
add a column this is the command that
you're going to run if you want to alter
a column if you want to modify a table
drop a column uh create a table all of
these are all listed here so this is the
sheet that you're going to reference on
a fairly frequent basis when you're
working with almic because I can never
remember each of the things but we're
going to go ahead and create our post
table and so we access the op object
from almic and I'm going to say op and
then if you look at the documentation
the way to create a table is you do
create uncore
table and there's going to be a couple
of properties we have to pass in so
what's the name of the table in
postgress well we're going to call it
posts and then we have to Define our
columns and I'm not going to do all of
our post column because it's going to
take a little bit of a while and we
might do it later on but we're just
going to Define two columns so the first
one is going to be first of all we do sa
column so we're grabbing the SQL Alchemy
object and so this column is going to
represent the ID so the name of it is
going to be ID it's going to be type of
integer and I may have accidentally
imported nope that we're good so
integer and then we can set nullable
equals false which means it's required
and then we also want this to be the
primary key so you just do primary key
equals
true all right fairly straightforward
right guys so we can then go in and
create a second column and so this is
just going to follow the same exact
pattern essay.
column and then this one will be the
title it's going to be a type of essay.
string and this is going to be equals
false and I'm just going to stop it
right here so we're going to just create
two columns I don't feel like creating
all of the columns that we had for
post and so the upgrade function is done
however we also have to provide the
logic for undoing these changes so if we
create a table what's the how do we undo
that well we delete the table so we do
op. dropcore table and we just give it
the name of the table so it's going to
be posts all right and so now now we
should be able to make these changes and
then we can roll back because we put the
logic in for downgrading so how exactly
do we make these changes well let's go
to almic
d-el and let's see what commands we have
uh so we've got a couple uh branches
that's probably not it current that's
going to show us what's the current
revision like what version are we on and
if you actually want to see that we'll
see Olympic current
and it looks like it's giving me uh an
error hold on let's go back to my env.
py file and I made a very silly mistake
this should be an F string so it wasn't
actually doing anything that's why it
was kind of highlighted weird so let's
try this now again we're going to do
almic
current and it's not going to actually
really give us any uh useful information
at the moment because we haven't run any
migrations right we're kind of starting
from a clean plate so let's go back and
let's just do a d-el and see what else
we've
got uh so we've got a downgrade well we
don't want to downgrade edit not really
uh heads we'll come back to that history
um that's not going to be useful because
we haven't done anything but if we go
down we want to get to upgrade so this
is what's important so if we do uh
almic upgrade we can just do das dasel
and we'll see what options we have and
so we have to provide a revision number
to tell a limic like hey what version of
our database do we want to go to uh and
so if you actually take a look at this
specific revision it provides a revision
number so if we actually want to get up
to this point where it runs this upgrade
we provide this revision number so I can
say almic
revision and then paste
that so let's run this and see what
happens
sorry not I didn't mean to type revision
I meant Olympic
upgrade and then not Olympic revision so
that's going to upgrade it and so you
can see it did a couple things say
running upgrade and it said it created
post table so let's go to postgress and
let's just refresh this and let's see if
it actually did something right and it
looks like it created two table so
that's interesting so we are we see our
post table and let's just quickly
inspect this we'll go to columns you can
see it created these columns and this
one got set to the primary key and both
are not now so it looks like it did
everything it was supposed to do but
what is this almic versions table well
this is uh this is what almic uses to
kind of keep track of all the revisions
uh and so if we just go to view edit
data all rows you can see that it just
has one column at the moment which has
the revision number uh you can see it's
d18 and that's going to match up with uh
this file d18 so that's all that's doing
so it will create a table for you
automatically so you can keep track of
all of the revisions um but make sure
you don't delete
that okay so that's cool we just got our
first table created through almic and I
think at this point you probably still
don't understand the Brilliance of a
database migration tool and that's okay
because we haven't really done much with
it yet so let's say that you know as
we're coding out our application uh we
realize we want to add a new column to
our database sorry well to our
specifically to our post table well we
can create a brand new revision to add a
new column so let's say if you take a
look at our models you know we have a
other fields that are missing so let's
say we want to add the content column
now I can type in almic revision so this
is going to create a brand new revision
we'll give it a name and I'll say add
content column to post
table all right and it's going to create
a brand new revision for us and once
again we have to put in the logic for
upgradeing and downgrading and you can
see that when we now that we have more
than one revision we can see that
there's also a down revision so if you
want to go down a step it's going to go
to the revision of the previous one so
let's put it in the logic for creating
or adding in a brand new column for
content and the way we add a new column
is we do op. addore
column and then we specify the table we
want to modify so it's going to be the
post table and then we do essay. column
to Define this
column so what's the column name it's
going to be
content and it's going to be a type of
string and we're going to make sure that
it's nullable is set to
false all right and remember every time
you set up the upgrade function you have
to set up the downgrade function so if
we add a column what's how do we undo
that well we dro the column so it's just
op. dropcore
column and then from the post we have to
provide the table that we want to drop
the column from which is the post table
and then we need to provide the actual
column we want to drop which is going to
be
content so we'll do
content okay and so let's test this out
uh first of all we'll run a few new
commands so
almic all right and let's see what the
current revision is so if I do almic
current right we could see that we are
currently on 2D one8 that's the revision
so this is the the revision where we
created the post table
and if I type in the
olymic
heads we can see that the latest
revision is actually 298 29885 which is
that new one we just created so if we
ever want to get to the latest revision
that's what's referred to as the head so
I can say uh if we want to you know
upgrade to that revision I can say a
lmic upgrade like we did before and I
can grab the revision
number like this or because it's also
happens to be the head I can just say
olymic
upgrade head and it's going to do the
same thing so let's try
this all right it said it added a
Content column we'll go and check this
in
postgress and I'm just going to refresh
this table and we'll go into properties
and we can see that we added the content
now let's say that after working on this
for a bit we realize we want to undo
these changes for whatever reason maybe
we no longer want the content column
so how do we actually roll
back well the since upgrading makes the
changes downgrading is going to do the
opposite so we can do
almic
downgrade and then if you want to just
roll back this revision we can see what
the down revision is so we can just say
this and just paste that in
there but we can also do a few other
things we can also say um minus one so
when I say minus one that means I'm
going to go back to one revision earlier
and we can even go as far back as we
want so if I say I want to go back to
minus two it's going to go back to two
revisions earlier um but we just have
one so I'm just going to say minus one
or I can just paste in the revision
number and so if I run the downgrade you
can see that it ran this
downgrade and if I go and refresh
this and then go to properties columns
we can see that we no longer have have a
Content
column and that's how easy it is to
downgrade uh or roll back your database
using a database migration tool like
almic okay so we got our post table uh
we're not going to worry too much about
that uh the next part of our application
was hey let's Implement user
functionality let's make it so that user
can sign up and log in so now we need to
create a user table how do we do that
well let's set up a new revision we'll
do
almic revision
- M and I'll say
add user
table all right so we've got our brand
new revision and we have to set up the
upgrade and the
downgrade uh now for this I don't want
to just type this out you know one by
one it would be kind of slow and boring
for you guys so I've actually I'm just
going to copy and paste this uh from my
notes and if you want to follow along
just uh you know pause the video and
just write this out but we'll just
quickly you know walk through exactly
what's happening so once again we're
using the create table method we're
going to create a table called users and
then we're going to set up all of our
columns so we've got a column called ID
which is an integer set to nullable
equals false you notice how I haven't
set this to be the primary key here
that's because there's two different
ways to set the primary key you know if
we go back to the previous one we set
this to be primary key equals true but
on this one if you actually go all the
way down to the bottom you can see that
we can add in a constraint sa primary
key constraint and then we pass the name
of the column that's going to be the
primary key so they both do the same
thing uh it's just whatever method you
prefer uh we've got the email column
which is going to be set to nullable
equals false same thing with password
then we've got the created at and so
here it's going to be a a type timestamp
and you'll see that this is all coming
from SQL Alchemy essentially because if
we go to our models and we go to our
user table it's same thing type
timestamp time zone equals true nullable
equals false server default equals text
well that's created at but yeah uh and
we're just doing the same thing so
server default and then we grab essay.
text now nullable equals
false and then you can see that we added
a unique constraint under the email
field to ensure that uh we can't have
duplicate
emails and then to downgrade we just do
op. dropcore table
users all right and so once again if you
want to see where we currently are cuz
remember we had originally upgraded
added the content column but then we
downgraded so where exactly are we uh
from a revision perspective well let's
do a lmic
current uh you can see that we're on 218
so we're back on that first
revision and we can also do an almic at
I believe it's history and you can see
the history of our revision so we
created post add content column to post
and then add user table and this is the
head so if you want to go all the way to
the front to the latest you would just
do Olympic upgrade
head and I think there's one more I want
to show you yeah that's okay uh so we're
going to do an
Olympic and uh let's say that we just
want to go and um go up one revision so
adding one rision is going to add that
column back we can do a lmic upgrade and
we can either put in the name of this
revision or we can upgrade one
level uh if we want to go all the way to
the latest which is going to be adding
the user table we can say head we can
also go up to revisions so if I do plus
two that's going to go up uh to add
content column one that's the first
revision and then one more which is
going to go up to the latest in this
case so there's a lot of different ways
to get there I'm just going to go to the
latest so this is going to add the
column back in the post table and then
add the users
table and you can see that it went ahead
and added the users table so if I
refresh
this we can now see that we have a users
table and hopefully all of the
properties are there uh you can see all
of these have been set constraints
primary key is set and anything else
everything else looks
good I guess one thing just to check is
the created at so if we check the
constraints here you can see that we're
going to grab the current time
Perfect all right so after we had added
the user functionality the next thing we
had to do was we had to implement uh the
relationships between users and post so
we had to set up that foreign key that
link the user table to the post table or
post table to the user table so once
again uh we're going to do an olymic
revision
dasm and I'm just going to say add
forign
key
to post
table all right we got our new revision
and what we're going to do is we're
going to first of all we have to add a
column to our post table called owner ID
and that's going to be the one that has
the foreign key constraint so we have to
do op. add
column and we have to specify the table
we want to add the column which is going
to be the post table and this is going
to be essay.
column we're going to call this owner _
ID and it's going to be a type of essay
integer and nullable is going to be set
to
false all right so we've created the
column now we have to set the link
between the two tables uh which is going
to be the foreign key constraint and so
to do that this is a little bit
confusing at first for me um because the
documentation is a little bit hard to
read sometimes so you do create foreign
key then you have to give it you know
some arbitrary foreign key name I'm
going to call this postscore users FK so
this is the foreign key between the post
and the user table and then we have to
specify what is the source table of the
foreign key so this is going to be the
foreign key for the Post table so we're
going to say sourcecore table
equals post
uh then we have to reference the U uh
the remote table which they call a
referent uncore
table and so this is going to be the
users
table and then we have to specify what
is the local colum that we're going to
be using so the column in the post
table and that's going to be owner ID
which is the table uh the column that we
just
created and finally we have to specify
the remote column in the users
table and this is going to be set and
we're also going to set the on
delete to be
Cascade and yeah by the way the remote
column is going to be the ID field of
the user table and yeah we want to make
sure we have the on delete as
well and that pretty much o what
happened there it's a we weird way to
format
things all right well it wants to format
it that way so I'm just going to leave
it like
that let's set up the downgrade now so
we have to undo those
changes we'll do op. dropcore
constraint and then we just mentioned
the name of the constraint which is post
users
FK we have to specify the table that
we're removing it from so it's on the
post table so we do table name equals
post and then we have to drop the column
so we do op. dropcore
column and where does this column sit
it's in the post table and it's called
owner
ID all right and so if I do an almic
current we're on
f52 and almic heads let's see what the
latest one is it should be 296 which is
this one
so let's do an Olympic upgrade head go
to the
latest and I have a typo so this should
be
integer all right looks like it ran with
no issues let's double check that the
foreign key is there now if we go to
Post
Properties constraints forn key you can
see that we have our post user FK and we
can see that it points uh from owner ID
and the post table to ID in the users
table and if you want to you can go
under actions and see that Cascade has
been set to on
delete now in our post table at the
moment uh you know we didn't Implement
all of the columns that we actually have
in our application so I figured H why
not just go in and add it might as
well so I'm going to create a new
revision
all right and then we go to that
revision uh there's really only two more
columns that we have to add and this is
I'm once again going to just copy and
paste from my notes just because I don't
want to waste your guys time too much
but you can see here we're going to do
an add column and we're going to add it
from our add it to our post table and
then here we're going to specify the
parameters of the column so this is
going to be called publish it's going to
be of type Boolean and um nullable
equals false and that's not correct it
should actually be nullable equals
true right it should be actually no it
was
false and then server default is set to
be um true so if we don't provide it
it's going to assume it's true and then
the next one is the um column for
created at so once again at the post
table we're going to create a column
called created at it's going to be a
type timestamp nullable false and then
the default means we're going to grab
the current time
and to downgrade we're going to delete
those
columns all right and let's do a
almic upgrade and we'll just go instead
of doing head we can just do plus one
just to show you guys how it's going to
do the same thing in this case and so it
looks like it ran that and if we go back
to
postgress refresh
this and then go to properties we should
see we've now got our published and our
created at
columns all right and once again let's
say that maybe we want to roll back
right maybe we want to roll back all the
way to uh back when we just created the
post table you know we can once again do
a
lmic downgrade and just provide the
revision number of the specific revision
you want to go to so we can go down to
add user table we can go down to create
post table we can go down to any section
we
want and it's really up to you and so
let's say this time let's just go all
the way down to uh let's go down to add
user table so whatever revision this is
we can do
that all right and so it deleted a whole
bunch of stuff uh looks like it deleted
the last few columns that we just added
as well as the foreign key constraint
and so now if we refresh these tables
you can see that posts uh it doesn't
have the extra columns we added and the
constraints born key no longer
exist but fortunately we can upgrade to
a newer version uh to one of the more
recent versions so I can do a lmic
upgrade plus one so if I do this it's
going to go up one newer revision so
right now we're at the uh add user table
and if you forget wherever you are you
could just do
almic
current all right so we're on uh 32
f52 and so if I do an
upgrade right
we're going to go up to uh I think it's
this
one because you can see that in this one
uh this revision is 296 but the previous
revision is 252 which is the one we're
currently on so I can do AIC
upgrade plus
one all right and so now we've added the
foreign key if I do almic current we can
see that we're on 296 and then if I just
do a lmic upgrade
well almic heads it's going to show us
whichever one's the latest one which is
B7 so we can just upgrade directly to
that by doing
head the last thing that we have to do
now is generate the votes table but I'm
not going to manually create it myself
this time instead I'm going to make use
of the autogenerate feature so this is
what I was talking about earlier how we
can use Olympic to be intelligent enough
to figure out what exactly is missing
from our postgress database and figure
out what needs to be created and the way
it actually does that is it takes a look
at all at all of our models so it's
going to import all of our SQL Alchemy
models and based off of The Columns that
we have set here it's going to figure
out what our postest database is uh is
supposed to look like and regardless of
what the our database is in its current
state we don't need to actually delete
everything and build it from scratch
instead a limpic is going to be
intelligent enough to figure out what
columns are missing what tables are
missing uh what extra columns do we
currently have that we may need to
remove and it's going to figure out
what's the different between SQL Alchemy
models and our post database and it's
going to make the necessary changes for
us and so the way to do that and first
of all I guess just to kind of reiterate
uh the reason we can do that is because
we
imported the models and then we passed
it into this target metadata so let's
run almic and we'll do revision
but if we do d-el you'll see that we're
going to use one of the flags that we
have never used before which is the D-
autogenerate so we'll do D-
autogenerate and then we will run send a
message once again we'll say add votes
how
about autov
vote maybe because it's autogenerated
and I know it's going to add the votes
table because that should be the only
difference that we have so we'll run
that
and so if I go to autov vote let's take
a look at the changes it's going to
make and so you can see here the changes
were it looks like it's going to create
the votes table like I had predicted
it's creating the two columns and then
it's going to add the primary key
constraint as well as the two foreign
Keys as well and it's going to even add
in all of the on delete properties and
things like
that all right and so all we got to do
now is do an almic upgrade head
and now if I refresh this and go to
votes and
properties right we should have the two
columns and then our constraints and
foreign keys look pretty good everything
looks
set and so that's how easy it was so no
matter what state your database is at
any point in time you can all you can
always do the autogenerate functionality
to get it back to a state that your code
expects it to be and the best part about
this is moving forward let's say I want
to go back to my models and I want to
change
something so I've got my user model this
time I'm going to add that phone
number
column and this is going to be
string all right so any changes we make
even on a table that already exists what
we can do now
is I can do a revision autogenerate
now here I can just call it add phone
number all right and then if we go take
a look at that we can see that hey look
we added our phone number column and so
the only thing else we have to do is do
an alic upgrade head and it's going to
push out those
changes so let's refresh this and let's
just double
check we go to users now properties we
can see phone number column is now set
and I think that's pretty much going to
wrap up everything I wanted to cover
from
almic so moving forward now that we have
almic we no longer actually need this
command in our main.py file this is the
command that told SQL Alchemy to run the
create statement so that it generated
all of the tables when it first started
up but since we have a lmic now you no
longer need the this command however if
you want to keep it in it's not really
going to break anything it just depends
on how you want things to work because
if it does create the tables for you
then your first Olympic migration isn't
going to have to do anything because uh
everything is already there but I'm
going to leave this commented out moving
forward because I don't really need it
and it's really up to you guys for what
you guys want to do for the most part
throughout this course we've been
testing our API by sending request from
Postman and postman's a great tool but
there's one thing to note and that is
that when you send a request from
Postman you're actually sending a
request from your own computer and it's
important to understand this because uh
you your API can get request from
different types of devices you can get a
request from a computer or a server uh
whether that's through Postman or even
through curl if you've ever used curl
it's essentially doing the same thing
that postman's doing it just doesn't
have a nice little gooey you can also
get requests from mobile devices but
more importantly you can get requests
from a web browser so when a web browser
sends a request you know using
javascript's fetch API there's going to
be a slightly different behavior that we
have to account for which we can't take
into consideration when sending requests
with Postman because Postman isn't a web
browser so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to show you exactly what happens
when we send a request from a web
browser instead of our own computer
using Postman so what I want you guys to
do is open up your web browser and
specifically go to google.com it's
important that you go to google.com or
technically this is going to work on any
website but I need you to actually go to
a specific website like
google.com and then I want you to right
click on the web browser and just hit
inspect so this is going to open up the
Chrome developer tools and if you are
too familiar with it don't worry it's
just a uh it's a built-in tool to that
we have in in Chrome or any web browser
that allows you to um make it makes it
easier as a web developer to kind of
troubleshoot things um but what we can
do is if you go to console we can
actually send an API request to our API
from google.com or from our web browser
which is on the google.com domain at the
moment and so I want you to just type
this in we're going to say fetch so this
is how you perform an API request uh
from the web browser level and we're
going to send a request to our fast API
so that's going to be hosted on
HTTP col localhost col
8000 and then just type in then so don't
worry too much about this but it it
technically returns a promise so we have
to resolve the promise we just say
re res.
Json and then do another then and just
say
console.log and I forgot one bracket
right here and so all this is doing is
it's sending a request to the root URL
of our API and then it's going to print
out the contents of whatever we get back
from the server so when I run this I
want you to notice something we get an
error it says access to fetch Local Host
colon 8000 from origin and then it has
google.com here has been blocked by Kors
policy so what is happening here why is
it that I can't send a request from the
web browser but if I go to postman and I
just create a quick new
request and we can just go straight to
URL it resolves just fine well it has to
do with this course policy so in this
lesson we're going to take a look at
what exactly this course policy is and
what we can do to ultimately resolve
this issue so what exactly is Coors
Coors is short for cross origin resource
sharing and so Coors allows you to make
request from a web browser on one domain
to a server on a different domain and by
default you know when you configure an
API whether it's in fast API or any
other framework or language uh you will
only be allowed to send requests from my
web browser running on the same exact
domain as your
server and so what exactly do I mean by
that well if our API is hosted on
google.com and our and our website is
hosted on ebay.com ebay.com by default
cannot send a request to an AP running
on a different domain like google.com
it's going to get blocked by
cores however if our web if our website
was also running on google.com and our
API was also running on google.com then
they'd be able to talk just fine by
default and just to prove that to you
guys if we go to our web browser and go
to Local Host colon 8000 you know which
is the the URL that our application's
currently running on you can see that I
get a response back so our web browser
was able to make a by the way when I
when I did this right it did the same
thing as you know going into Chrome
developer tools and actually sending a
request and just in case you don't
believe me I'm just going to actually
just show you guys even on here if I
paste it you can see that it was able to
resolve and we can see the hello world
so the reason why it works on this
website is because this is the same
exact URL or domain name that our API is
running on right our API is running on
Local Host colon 8000 so by default
they're able to talk to one another only
when the web browser domain is on the
same exact domain as the api's domain so
to fix this you know if you did want to
allow people from other domains to talk
to your API uh what you can do is take a
look at the fast API documentation and
just search for
Cores cross origin resource sharing and
you'll see that setting this up is
really simple so the first thing that we
have to do is from Fast API middleware
cores we're going to import cores
middleware
all right and then just copy this
section right
here and I'll explain line by line
exactly what each one's doing and so
under the app right here we'll just
paste this
in and it's going to throw a little
error here but we'll come back you can
actually delete that and change that to
a an array for now um but what we want
to do is first of all we have to pass in
the middleware and middleware is a term
that's used in most web Frameworks um
because it's basically a function
that runs before every request so if
someone sends a request uh to our app
and before it actually goes through all
of these routers it'll actually go
through the middleware and then our
middleware can perform some sort of
operation but what we want to do is
first of we have to specify the origins
that we want to allow so what domains
should be able to talk to our API cuz
right now it's only it's no domains only
if it's running on the same exact domain
are you able to talk to our API so the
way we can is we can put in um we'll
create a list called Origins and I'll
say Origins equals and it's just going
to be a list and here we're going to per
provide a list of all of the domains
that can talk to our API and before we
fill that in I just want to quickly talk
about the other three as well so our
cores policy uh can be pretty granular
so not only can we allow specific
domains we can also allow only specific
HTTP methods so if we were building like
a public API uh where people can just
retrieve data we may not want them to
allow we may not want to allow them to
send post requests uh and put requests
and delete requests so we could
potentially just allow get requests and
then we can even allow specific headers
as well but for now we're just going to
allow all headers and all methods and
we're going to just kind of drill down
based off of what Origins can talk to us
and so you know if we want Google to be
able to talk to us I can just say
https www.google
and so now this course policy is set to
allow people from google.com to talk to
us and so if I go back to google.com I
just hit the up Arrow so I can run this
command again you'll see that I do
successfully get a response back and
there's no cores error however if I go
to a different website so you know some
website on a different domain like
youtube.com and then we go and then we
send the same exact request from the
console right we once again get the
course error and that's because in our
in our list of Origins we're not
providing www.com uh doyoutube
docomo allow youtube.com then we'd have
to do https
colon
www.youtube.com so now if I hit the up
Arrow we can see that it it properly
resolves so you just have to provide
list of URLs that can talk to your
API and if you want to set up a public
API so that everyone can access it then
your Origins would just be a wild card
so this means every single domain or
every single
origin but if you if your API is being
configured for a specific web app then
you definitely want to make sure that
you provide a strict list of Origins so
just whatever domain your your web app
is running on so that no one else can
you know know accidentally reach our
application for some reason or another
it's just security best practices to
really narrow down the scope of the
origins that can actually access your
API um for now I'm just going to leave
this as uh set to everyone so that you
know when we actually go to deploy this
it'll be a little bit easier from a
testing purpose um but feel free to
update this
accordingly in this lesson we're going
to focus on setting up git for our
project so that we can start tracking
our changes as well as set up a remote
repository to store all of our code this
is going to make the whole deployment
process a whole lot easier but before we
set up git there's a couple of things
that we need to do because when you
check your files into git by default
it's going to uh check in all of your
files and there's going to be some files
that you don't want uh to be uploaded to
a remote repository or even into your
git in general and so we have to create
a file called a get ignore file and so
if you go to the main root PRO root
folder of your project I want you to
create a file called Dog ignore and it's
important that you put the dot in front
of it so it's dog ignore and so this
file is going to tell git what are all
of the files and folders We don't want
uploaded to get and so some of the
common things that you would not want to
be tracked within git is going to be uh
your EMV file so this is going to be all
of your environment variables obviously
you don't want to check those in or then
uh you know if this is part of a public
repository then anyone can see those uh
but also on top top that you'll see all
of these random pie cach these uncore
uncore pyh folders so go ahead and add
that in there as well cuz we don't
actually need to check that into get and
then finally we have our folder which
contains our virtual environment we
don't want to check that in as well just
because we have no idea if someone else
who wants to clone our repository is
going to be using a virtual environment
H and if and if they are then they can
create one on their own there's no need
for us to actually upload our virtual
environment it just wouldn't make sense
and on top that our virtual environment
contains all of the third-party
libraries that we've installed so all of
the different uh packages we installed
through pip including fast API itself so
all of the code of fast API is within
that virtual environment folder and so
there's no need to actually upload all
of that because that's a lot of a lot of
files uh that actually take up a decent
amount of space and it just wouldn't be
efficient to actually upload those to
get however this does create one bit of
an issue because uh if we clone the
repository at this point right we have
no idea what packages we need to install
because our virtual environment didn't
get uploaded with it so we need to wait
for other users other people on our team
to know what packages and dependencies
we need our application uh so that our
application actually works and so the
way that we actually do this is well
first of all before we even proceed go
ahead and copy this into your get ignore
file and make sure you have this before
you do anything else because once
certain files get checked in it's very
hard to get them
removed um but but after this what we
want to do is we want to create one more
file and open up your
terminal and what we're going to do is
type in PIP
freeze so pip freeze is going to dump
out all of the different packages and
libraries that we have installed as well
as the specific versions and so this is
the information that we want to upload
to get so that if anyone else uh clones
our repository they'll know the exact
versions of every package they need to
install so what we're going to do is
we're just going to take this output and
we're going to pipe it to a file and the
file name is going to be called
requirements.txt
so this is standard convention uh with
any python application you want to
create a requirements.txt file that's
going to contain the version of all of
the different packages that you have
installed and so if we check this into
git now then anyone else can just take a
look at our requirements.txt file and
then actually install dependencies based
off of what's in this file and so for
anyone else that clones our repository
all they have to do uh instead of going
one by one and in these they can just
type in PIP install dasr
requirements.txt and that's going to
install everything that's in this file
so this does simplify the process and it
prevents us from having to upload all of
those third party packages into git but
we've got everything set up at this
point we've got the git ignore file and
we've got the requirements.txt so what
we need to do now is actually set up and
install git on our local
machine if you don't already have git
installed then in this lesson we're
going to focus on getting installed on
your local machine so just search for
git and then you can either go to the
main page or you can go straight to the
downloads page so I'm just going to
select the downloads page and then here
you're going to see the different
operating systems we can install get on
and so just go ahead and select your
respective operating system I'm on a
Windows machine but forg goodless of
your operating system it's going to be a
fairly similar procedure so I'm going to
select this it's going to download that
all right and then when the wizard opens
go ahead and select next next here and
you can leave everything default here as
well and here and
here now this is the one thing that we
do have to change so this is kind of a
little bit uh of a a nuisance at this
point but uh they used to call like the
main branch the master Branch but I
guess people are offended by that so now
the new term for the main branch is main
so go ahead and override the default
branch and just change that to main
because when you work on GitHub they've
already changed the default Branch to be
main so we're going to want to do the
same thing so hit
next and then you can leave everything
as default moving forward there's a lot
of Windows to go
through and then it's going to proceed
to install
git all right close that out and then
what you want to do is open up a new
terminal
and just type in g-- version and if it
spits that out that means you've got git
successfully
installed in this video we're going to
set up a remote repository so we can
store all of our code on GitHub and so
if you don't already have an account on
GitHub go to the main GitHub page just
go to github.com and just click sign up
and then follow those instructions and
then once that's done just log in and
you should see something similar to this
although you may not see an activity
window if you just created a brand new
account cuz you won't have any
Repository
um but just look for a new uh button a
button to create a new repository you
can also go up here I believe and select
new repository so I'll select new and
then we have to give our repository name
you can give it any name you want I'm
just going to give it a dummy name so
this is going to be example fast API but
name it what after whatever your project
is uh technically I've already set up
git for my project um just so I can
track all the changes I've made
throughout the course um but I want to
make sure that I can walk you through
this if you've never done it
before uh you can give it an optional
description uh and then you can choose
whether or not a repository is public or
private if it's public anybody can see
it uh if it's private then only you can
see it we're going to keep it as public
uh don't worry if you decide to change
it in the future you can change it to
private uh however it does make a few
things a little bit easier when it's
public so I'm going to leave this as
public and then we're going to leave all
of these unchecked they don't really
matter and we'll select create
repository and then you'll see that it's
going to give us a couple of steps to
follow so if we haven't already set up
git for our project these are the
instructions we're going to follow and
if we've already set up git in our uh
project folder then we can follow these
steps uh however you know we haven't set
up git yet so we're going to for the
most part follow along here but we're
going to modify it just a little bit
because we don't need to run some of
these commands so go ahead and open up
your project in vs code like you
normally do then open up your terminal
and we're going to follow these steps
but we're going to ignore the first one
we don't need to read me for now uh but
we are going to do a git in it which is
going to initialize git for our project
and so make sure you're at the root
directory of your project so whatever
this is called right here at the top
make sure that's where you're at and
just do a get in it that's going to
initialize git and uh you may not see
anything uh different about your folders
but I think it's because vs code
actually hides the git folder but when
you actually did a get in it if you open
up this uh your project directory and
you click on view here and then make
sure you select hidden items uh you'll
see that it created a dogit folder so
this is where it stores all of the git
information uh then we're going to skip
this uh get ad read me instead what
we're going to do is we're going to run
get add-- all so this is going to add
all of the files that we have in our
directory into get all right and you'll
get a couple of warnings potentially
don't worry about that those won't
create any issues then we have to commit
our changes so anytime you add a file
you then have to commit it so we'll say
get commit DM so the DM means we're
going to provide a message so you
usually give a a message for each commit
to kind of describe what changes you're
making so we're just going to call this
initial
commit all right and you'll see that we
probably get an error if this is the
first time you've ever worked with Git
and that's okay it's just telling us hey
we need to set up our uh user for our
account on this machine so we're just
going to run this Command right here and
then we're just going to provide the
email that we use to register for
GitHub I'll say git config D- Global
user. email
all right we set that and then it's
telling us to also set our name so we'll
do that as
well then we're going to run that same
command the get commit so if you just
hit the up Arrow a couple times you'll
get to
that all right so we've committed those
changes then what we need to do is we
need to uh set what our branch is so
here this is just going to set uh our
main branch to be called Main and so we
can copy
that paste it into
here uh then we have to set up a
remote Branch so this is what's going to
allow us to store all of our code on
GitHub so we're just saying like Hey
listen this is going to be the remote
git repository and we just provide a URL
to it and so that if you take a look at
the URL it's going to match up with this
and in this case we're naming it origin
you can technically call it anything you
want so we'll add that and then finally
we need to do a get push - origin Main
and so this means uh we're actually
going to push all of our code up to
GitHub and you'll see a popup uh asking
you to sign in and there's a couple
things we can do we can get a personal
access token or we can sign in with our
browser so I'm just going to sign in
with our
browser and we just like authorize right
here right and it says it's succeeded so
we should be able to go back and we can
see that a couple things change so it
looks like a
well that's our authentication and then
you can see that we're pushing all of
the stuff up to GitHub and so at this
point you're pretty much done all of
your code is now stored in GitHub and we
can just verify that by going back to
this page and just select the name of
the repository again and you'll see all
of our Co all of our codes stored on
GitHub now so at this point our
repository is set up and we can move on
to deploying our
application in this lesson we're going
to take a look at the first of two
deployment methods that we're going to
cover in this course so what we're going
to do is we're going to deploy our
application to a platform called Heroku
and the reason I wanted to make sure to
have this as one of the deployment
methods was that Heroku has a very
generous free tier and so we can create
an account for free and we can deploy
our application absolutely for free
without having to pay a single dollar
and we don't even have to provide our
credit cards and I wanted to make sure
to add that just because I know for some
of you guys that isn't exactly an option
and I wanted to make sure that you can
still deploy your application and show
off to your friends and family uh what
you have created and you'll see that
Heroku has made it very easy to deploy
your application and it's very easy to
push out changes to your application
it's a fantastic platform and I think
you guys will learn a lot on how to
actually deploy an application by making
use of a platform like Heroku so we'll
take a look at how we can you know make
use of Heroku learn about the Heroku CLI
so that we can push our application to
the platform and ultimately have anyone
be able to access our
API Heroku has a lot of really good Tut
tutorials on how to deploy applications
on their platforms and they've got one
for python as well so if we go to Google
uh just search for Heroku Python and the
first result is going to be their
tutorial it's going to walk us step by
step on how to actually deploy our
application um but before we do that
there's a couple things that we have to
do first of all go ahead and create an
account on Heroku if you don't if you
haven't already done so it's completely
free uh so just provide your email and
so on uh then there's two other
requirements we have to have git
installed on our machine which we've
already done and then finally we have to
install Heroku itself so if you go to
the setup section right here you're
going to see the installers for all of
the different operating systems they
support so just select whichever
operating system you have and get the
Heroku CLI installed on your machine and
after you get it installed usually you
have to close out any of your
pre-existing Terminals and reopen them
to actually be able to access the Heroku
command uh if you have vs code a lot of
times I've had to just close out VSS
code altogether not just close the
terminals but actually close out the
entire application and then open it back
up but after you've done that if you
want to verify if Heroku was
successfully installed uh just go to
your terminal and just type in Heroku D-
version and if it spits out a version
that means Heroku has been successfully
installed and uh after it's been
installed we want to log in so we do
Heroku
login and then you just press any key
right here and it's going to open up uh
your web browser you can just log in and
then provide your credentials
all right and then once you're logged in
you can just close out this
window we go back to our code and you
can see logging in is done and we've
logged in and then that's my specific
account right
there all right and once that's done
we're going to go back to the
tutorial and we're just going to kind of
follow along so if you go to prepare the
app you can ignore this so they give you
like a demo application uh to kind of
follow through uh the tutorial but we
already have our own app so we don't
need to worry about that if we go to
deploy the app we have to run this
command herok create so we have to
create an app within our Heroku account
so let's run that command but before we
run that I'm going to do a herok create
d-el and we can see that one of the
arguments is going to be the name of the
app we want to create uh and so if you
don't provide a name Heroku just gives
you a random name but I always like to
use a a more familiar name so I know
that what app which app covers which one
of my applications and so I'm going to
call this fast API sanie and keep in
mind these app names are Global so if I
deploy my app as fast API sanjie you
will not be able to create an app with
the same exact name and that's because
to actually access our application once
deployed the URL is going to be the
specific app name embedded in there so
it has to be globally unique so if it
says your your app name is already taken
then just try a different one maybe add
a couple numbers at the end it doesn't
really matter what the name
is all right and once we've created our
app the next thing that we have to do is
well actually before we even do that I
want to show you guys what it actually
did so there's a couple things that
happen behind the scenes uh and the
first thing is if we actually log into
our account I'm going to log in right
here right we're going to see our
dashboard so in the dashboard you can
see the application that we just
created right now there's nothing
interesting nothing's been set up with
it so we don't actually see anything but
the second thing that it also did was if
I type in git
remote this is going to show all of the
remote remotes that have been set up for
our git and we can see there's two now
so there's origin which is the one we
set up originally that's G Hub
ultimately but Heroku added a second one
and so this is ultimately how we deploy
our application because because instead
of doing a get push origin main to push
it out to GitHub we can just do get push
Heroku Heroku Main and that's going to
push out our code to the hoko platform
and then it will then create an instance
for our application so let's go ahead
and do that we're going to do a get push
Heroku
Main and this is going to take a little
bit of a while because it's got to you
know set up python it's got to do a few
other things it's got to install all of
our dependencies before it can actually
get our app up and running so I'm going
to pause this video and then I'll touch
base with you guys once that's
complete all right so our application
has successfully been deployed and
you'll see that in the logs Heroku
actually gives us the URL of our
application so I'm going to copy this
URL and we're going to just open this up
in the browser and if you let this run
long enough you're eventually going to
see an error so it looks like something
in our application is broken and this is
to be expected because there's still a
few more things that we have to do to
actually get this set up because if you
take a look at what we've done we pushed
out our code to Heroku right but Heroku
has no idea how to actually start our
application that you know what is the
command it doesn't it just knows that
this is a python app but it doesn't know
what it is it doesn't know that it's a
fast API up it doesn't know that we're
trying to build out an API it has no
idea and when we deploy to our
development environment we ran UV corn
uh and then you know app. Main and then
app right but we haven't given that
command to Heroku how does it have any
idea that our code is in main.py and
that within the main.py file we have our
app instance stored in a variable called
app it has no idea so what we have to do
is we actually have to create a file
that's going to tell Heroku what is the
exact command that we want to run so
inside your root directory so just kind
of collapse all the folders inside your
root directory so just right click here
create a new file create a file called
proc file so I've already got this in
here it's going to be in the GitHub repo
so you can take a look at it and make
sure you capitalize the
p and actually if you take a look at the
the tutorial and we go to the next one
which is a Define a proc file this is
going to just explain what the proc file
is but the proc file just just tells
Heroku what is the command that we need
to start our application and so here we
give it a process type so since this is
a web application that's going to be
responding to you know web requests uh
we want to use the word web and then we
specify the exact command that we need
to run and so in my proc file a couple
of things have been set up so we run the
came in UV corn app. Main and then app
like we've done before we're not going
to pass in the D- reload flag because
this is production we don't want it to
automatically reload on changes because
there should be no changes we do have to
provide the host IP so this is just
saying that hey we should be able to
respond to request to any IP so whatever
IP Heroku gives us this is going to
accept it then the next flag is going to
be the port flag so what port should we
run this on if we don't provide a port
flag uh then it's it's going to default
to Port 8,000 like it always has however
the thing about Heroku is that they're
actually going to provide us Port so we
don't know what this port is ahead of
time so we have to be able to accept
this port regardless of what it is and
so it's actually going to pass this down
as an environment variable so anytime
you want to accept an environment
variable or reference one you can just
say dollar and then curly braces so
we're really just saying we want to take
whatever value Heroku gives us uh with
the environment variable of port and we
want to assign it here and then this is
just giving it a default value of 5,000
if they don't provide one however Heroku
will always provide a support so I don't
think we even need that and so after you
um make this file you're then going to
have to push out these changes to get
once again and since I already had this
file um there's nothing to change in my
git so nothing will get pushed out so
I'm just going to just change some
random
code I'm going to delete this 1 2 3 4
here so that I can at least have some
changes in my code you guys will already
have changes in your code because you
added the new file so then go ahead and
do a get add-- all so it's going to add
all the changes we're going to do a
commit and we'll give it a message of
added proc
file and then we do a get push and then
what do we push to well first of all you
know moving forward we want to make sure
that this is stored in GitHub so let's
do a git push origin main this is going
to push it to
GitHub and then now we want to actually
push out these changes to Heroku so that
we can actually get our application up
and running so we'll do a get push um
Heroku
Main and once again we have to kind of
wait through this entire
process okay so it's now finished once
again we're going to go back to the URL
it's deployed
at and I'm just going to do a refresh to
see if we fixed our our
issue and the fact that it's still
spinning for this long most likely means
that we did not fix our issue um but I
already know the exact reason why this
is and so we will take a look at exactly
what is causing our application to not
successfully get deployed in the next
lesson anytime your application isn't
working on heroku's platform they have a
really easy way of accessing logs so we
can say Heroku logs and then I'm just
going to do a d-el just to see what
options we have
and so here we could specify the app um
or we can just dump the logs for all of
our apps but what I'm going to do is I'm
going to pass in the DT flag so we can
tail the logs as things
happen so if I do
a-t and we scroll up you can see that
we've got a couple of different errors
and so it looks like there's some issues
with settings which you know is the the
pantic model that we've set up for
retrieving our environment variables and
it's saying that there's a couple of
validation errors for our settings model
and it says that hey look we don't have
a database host name we don't have a
database Port password or any of the
other information so there's some issue
with our environment variables and this
makes sense because in development we
use our uhv file to um provide all of
the environment variables into that
settings model right here and we passed
that by specifying the EnV file however
we did not check our EnV file into G
remember in
git we we use the git ignore file to
make sure excluded that cuz we don't
want to actually check that into G so
how does Heroku know what all of our
environment variables should be well
they have a and so we actually have to
add those environment variables either
through the command line or through the
dashboard but before we can do that we
need to actually get a postgress
database because right now we don't have
a postgress database so what would we
even provide for database host name and
port and password and things like that
if we don't have one so let's create one
and once again Heroku provides us with a
free postgress
instance that we can have access to and
that's what that's one of my favorite
Parts about herok is that now we have
access to postgress so let's go to
Heroku
postgress and I'll just say
tutorial and it's going to take us to
their Dev Center so this is going to
show us actually how to uh create a
postgress instance and so it postgress
is one of their many add-ons if you want
to actually go to their website and see
all of the different add-ons they
support they support a ton if you want
to read us add-on you can get that added
but in this casee we want to create a
postgress a postgress instance so we do
Heroku add-ons create uh then the type
of add-on which means it's going to be
post SQL and then plan name so we are
under the hobby Dev which is essentially
the free one and that's going to
actually create a hero uh a postgress
instance so let's run this and just
contrl C out of
this and let's just do a d Das help real
quick just to see what other flags we
have and that should be fine we don't
need actually provide any other flags so
let's run this and Heroku is actually
going to create our postest instance and
keep in mind that for Heroku to spin up
a postgress instance it does take a
little bit of time um but we can
actually monitor that in our dashboard
so if we go back to my dashboard and do
a
refresh you can see that this is the new
Heroku
instance and I can just click on this
and we can see some more information
it's going to open this up in a new tab
and if you want to we can go into these
settings and here we can take a look at
our database credentials so if I view my
credentials you can see that this is the
IP address my database lives on uh this
is the actual database name so we don't
get to create our own database name or
our own database within postgress they
give us a fixed name and that's
perfectly
fine and then here's this is going to be
the username that we're going to log in
as this is the port it's running on and
then this is our password and they also
provide us the full postris URL if we
want uh to use that so now that we have
have this information feel free to save
this real quick and I'm actually just
going to do a quick
screenshot and save this in my notes so
that I don't have to keep bouncing back
and forth and now let's go back to our
application and if we go under
settings this config vars is where we
actually provide environment variables
to our Heroku instance and by the way
Heroku calls are instance dinos um but
you can use either term you want and so
you could see all of the config
variables that have been set and there
should be nothing except for one so when
you add a postc instance to your
application what happens
is Heroku automatically adds an
environment variable called database URL
and it's going to contain the entire
postrest ql UL uh
URL and so we could go into our
application and then update our code so
that in the database. py file instead of
uh you know breaking things down like
this we can just provide you know one uh
one specific URL and just put it in as
say settings do you know
database URL however I don't like to
change my code I like it just the way it
is so instead of using the the default
environment variable we're going to
actually break this URL out into
multiple different environment variables
so just open this up and take a look at
all of the environment variables that we
expect by going into our config.py so we
need all of these set so we're going to
add one for
database host name
and from the URL if you forgot what the
host name is and actually I'm going to
just open this one up in a new tab and
then open up actually I don't even need
to open up this
one I just need to flip between these
two so the host name uh is right here
and but you can get it from this URL
just by clicking on this icon and then
just grabbing the IP address but it's
such a small little window I hate having
to do that so I'm going to close that
and just bounce between these two
links all right so let's grab the host
name and we'll add this one uh then the
next one is going to
be the database Port password name and
user name so let's just write those out
database
Port database
username datab base
password and then database
name I think that's it database Port
password name
username and then we have to add the
stuff for our token so we got secret key
algorithm and then the last one
and then now we can provide in the Valu
so the database Port we can see from
here it's going to be the default 5432
the
username and then here we'll grab the
password and then the actual database
name
here the secret key I'm just going to
use what whatever we used in development
not actually recommended but I'm just
going to keep things as simple as
possible for now but you can provide any
secret key you want
and I'll say in production it'll expire
after 60
minutes all right and so now we've got
our all of our environment variables set
up and our post postgress instance is
already up and running so I think at
this point our app should work so we'll
try this out
again so now that we set those new
environment variables how do we actually
restart our Heroku instance well let's
do a
Heroku
apps
d-el and let's see if there's a restart
so there's app create
destroy and it doesn't look like there's
a restart so we can't actually use the
apps argument to restart our application
instead we have to do
Heroku ps-
dhel so now um we can see that we do
have access to restart so we're going to
do Heroku PS
restart and that's going to restart our
Dino which is our Heroku
instance and once again I'm going to do
a Heroku
logs DT to tail the
logs all right and so now you can see
those previous errors were gone and we
were now able to successfully run the
startup command and you can see that um
we actually got past a specific Port of
34731 uh and so that's why we ultimately
had to provide the port variable because
this will change every time we restart
it however we don't actually need to use
that
specific port number in the URL that we
need to access so let's get our um our
app URL which I already
forgot and if you ever forget your url
you can just type in Heroku apps info
then the name of the specific app and
then it's going to give you all of the
specific information so you can see this
is actually where the hoko git is being
stored we can see that we have one
instance in this case running the web
and then we have our URL down here so
I'm going to copy
this and you can see that we get message
hello world so it looks like things are
working uh if I actually go to/ dos
Let's test that out and so now we have
access to documents I'm going to
minimize that so it looks like things
are working however if I try to log in
whether it's either through the
documentation or if I actually send a
request from Postman you're going to see
that there's going to be some issues so
here I'm going to actually I can't even
log in I have to create a user first
because this is a fresh deployment so
let's go to users and we're going to
create a user real quick and I'm going
to just try this out and put in whatever
name you
want now so this is sanjie example.com
my password will be
password 1 2 3 we'll execute
it and you can see that we get an
internal server error so what is
happening why can't we exactly create a
user well like usual we're going to go
back to our
logs and we're going to see what
happened all right so we can see the SQL
that's getting inputed in the logs and
it looks like there's some kind of error
with the SQL and I don't know if it's
going to give us a more specific in uh
error that's going to actually help us
uh I think that's all it's going to
provide us in this case but I think you
guys can guess exactly what's happening
we deployed a brand new instance of
postgress um but right now if we
actually connect to our postgress you're
going to see a few different issues so
I'm going to actually connect to this
postest instance and to create a postest
instance just right click here and then
select create server so this is going to
allow us to connect to another postris
and I'm going to call this Heroku d
postgress and then here we're going to
provide the same exact connection
information so we'll go back to settings
we'll get our
credentials okay and so now we are
successfully connected to our Heroku
postgress instance and if I just drop
this down and then go into databases
you'll see a ton of different databases
keep in mind we won't actually be able
to access most of these uh so the reason
postgress is able to oh sorry the reason
Heroku is actually able to provide this
for free is that they have one instance
of postgress and then they give you one
database within that instance that you
can access but only you can access that
specific database and so our database is
d58 and I don't know if there's an easy
way to search for databases let me see
if I can right click this nope it
doesn't look like there's an easy way so
I'm just going to have to scroll down to
D5 and then to the next letters
d58 re
e05 all right so I finally found my
database you'll see it's the one that I
have access to so it's actually colored
and if I just open this up real quick
and go into
schemas public and then
tables there's nothing in there so
that's really the reason why our
application is not working is because we
have a brand new postr instance but we
haven't actually set up our tables or
our schema and so this is where almic is
going to come into play once again uh
you'll see that since we already have
all of our revision set up uh getting
our production database to match our
development database will be as simple
as just running one simple command so
we'll take a look at that in the next
video in our development environment we
used Olympic to manage our database
schema so Olympic was responsible for
creating all of those tables and since
we have all of these revision files
within the almic folder we can
essentially track all the changes that
we make and so to actually get our
development database up to date we just
ran olymic upgrade head and that would
go to whichever one of these is the
latest revision and make sure that our
postgress instance matched whatever that
is in our production database because in
our production database it's going to be
no different we're going to just run a
limic upgrade head on our Heroku
instance and that's going to ensure that
our postgress database uh gets updated
to our latest schema and because we've
checked all of these files into git um
because all of the Olympic folders was
added to git as well uh that then our
Heroku instance has access to all of our
revisions and so when we run Olympic
Olympic can keep track of all of those
changes as well in our production server
and it's important to understand that we
never run olymic
revision on our production server we
only run Olympic revision on our
development server when we're staging
out these changes in our production
server server whenever we want to push
out those changes we just do a get push
so we push out the code all of our code
changes as well as all of the Olympic
revisions to our production server and
we just run an Olympic upgrade head it's
as simple as that so let's do that now
the first thing that we need to do is we
got to figure out how do we actually run
a command in our Heroku
instance uh I think your first guess is
probably going to be do we add another
line into this proc file that we can
kind of call whenever we want to uh not
exactly although maybe you can do that
um but if we go back to our tutorial and
go to start a console we can run a
specific command on our Heroku instance
by doing Heroku run and then the
specific command that we want to run so
let's try that out and you can even drop
into the bash shell so there's a lot of
flexibility but we're going to just do a
Heroku run and then we want to provide
the command that we want to run I'm
going to put in quotes I don't remember
if it's a requirement to put it in
quotes but I'm going to do that just in
case so we'll do almic upgrade
head all right and you see that it's
running that Command right
now and take a look at the logs right
you can see that not only did it get our
postgress instance up to the latest
revision it has all of the other
incremental steps added in as well so we
can roll back to any of them just like
we did in development and if we go back
to PG admin I'm going to just refresh
tables and if we go to our tables you
can see that we have all of our tables
here now and just in case um because I
believe we crashed our application maybe
uh when we try to you know create a user
without having a postgress database or
table set up I'm just going to do a
Heroku
PS restart
again just to restart the instance just
in case and now I want to go back to
here and we're going to just go back to
the root URL to see if that works and
that works that's perfect we'll go back
to
docs we can see that that works now
let's try to create a user and so I'll
do try it
out and I don't even feel like changing
any of these values technically these
should still work so let's just try that
and we got a response back and look at
this we got a 2011 and we can see the
user that was created so it looks like
our application was now successfully
able to access our database if we go
into the users
table right click on this and just do a
view edit all
rows we can see the one user that we
created all right and so that's pretty
much it we've successfully deployed our
application the last thing that I want
to show you guys is how do we push out
changes to our application let so let's
say that I go into my app and right now
I go into
main.py and I see that this just says
message hello world and let's say I make
some kind of change and let's say I just
add a whole bunch of exclamation points
or something just keep it to keep it
simple just to show you guys you know
regardless of what change you make the
steps are going to be identical so we
make some changes the the next thing
that we have to do is we actually have
to push out those changes so first of
all you're definitely going to you know
push out those changes to your GitHub
repository so we'll do get push origin
main so that's going to push it out to
get
GitHub well sorry I forgot to do a get
add-- all so we actually have to add
those changes and then commit those
changes so I'll do get commit
then we'll do a get push origin main so
that's going to push it out to GitHub
and then finally to actually push those
changes out to our production
environment we'll do a get push Heroku
main all right and so that's pushed out
now and if we go back to our
application I'm going to go back to the
route
URL and we can see that we now have the
extra exclamation points so we have
successfully pushed out our changes all
it took was just one simple command and
keep in mind that if you make changes to
your code that's all you have to do
however if you make changes to your
database so you know you go into Olympic
and you create a new revision then we
have to follow the same exact steps but
on top of that we have to do the uh the
Heroku run almic you know upgrade head
so that we actually push out those
changes to the postest instance but
there you guys have it you have
successfully deployed the application
that we have spent building the past
couple of days and so feel free to show
this off to your friends and family uh
feel free to make as many changes and
modifications really start to play
around with it uh try to expand on the
functionality of our
application and just keep learning I
guess for the second method of
deployment we're going to see how we can
deploy our application on an abunto
server and it's important to keep in
mind that it does not matter where you
host your abon 2 server you can run it
on any of the major Cloud providers AWS
Azure gcp you can run it on digital
ocean you can run it on your local
machine if you have virtual box
installed on your computer you can run
it on Raspberry Pi it doesn't matter the
steps are going to be identical as long
as you run it on an auntu server now
what we're going to do in this course is
I'm going to show you guys how to deploy
it on digital ocean just because it's $5
a month it's cheap it's a fixed price uh
if you deploy it on AWS then the price
is kind of it varies and if you run it
all all month long then it could Spike
up well past $5 so this is kind of the
cheapest solution but keep in mind like
I said the steps are identical
regardless of where you
deploy I just want to focus on making
sure that you guys understand the steps
that needs to take place to actually set
up your buntu server to be ready to host
your application uh and so if you don't
have a digal ocean account go ahead and
make one and then once you log in you'll
see this window and what we want to do
is Select get started with the
droplet so we'll select that and what we
want to do is we want to select auntu
20.04 that's the latest version at the
moment if you're watching this in the
future um you could probably grab one of
the newer ones most of these commands
are going to be identical but if you
wanted to make sure that you don't run
into any issues select the same exact
version then for the CPU options you
want to select regular Intel with with
SSD that's going to be the cheapest and
then you want to select the cheapest one
right here which is $5 a month or
0.7 per hour what is that seven 710 of a
cent all right and then uh select your
data center so I'm just going to select
whatever is closest to me I'm on the
East Coast so I'm going to select
that and then nothing else for the most
part really matters we can leave
everything as default uh and then you
have two options for authentication you
can use SSH keys if you're familiar with
how to work with that if you're not then
start out with password for now it's
just a little bit
simpler and you'll see that digital
ocean has some strict requirements for
passwords so uh you're probably going to
have to try this a couple times before
you find one that actually matches their
criteria and then here we can just give
this a specific host name I'm just going
to call this auntu dfast
API it's nothing more than really just a
tag and that's all we have to do we'll
select create do droplet and digital
ocean will create our auntu
VM all right and once the loading bar
finishes you should see a public IP this
is the IP that we're going to use to
connect to our virtual machine and so
we'll take a look at how to connect to
this in the next
video to connect to our auntu virtual
machine we need to open up our terminal
so just search for terminal on Windows
if you're on Mac you can do the same
thing just search for terminal uh and
then on Windows you can select command
prompt I installed another terminal so
I'm actually going to use that but you
can use this one as well you can even
use the built-in terminal within VSS
code it's all going to be the same
thing okay and to connect to a device we
have to use a protocol called SSH so we
do SSH and then we have to provide the
username that we want to connect to to
the device uh and so this is going to
vary depending on where you're deploying
your virtual machine um on digital ocean
this is they're going to create an
account uh for the root user so this is
like the most privileged user this is
where you can ultimately do anything
with the device you have unlimited
access so we're going to do SSH root at
and then you do the at symbol and then
we provide the IP address so I can just
hover over this select copy and then
paste it in
here and at this point you'll get this
you know fingerprint message so just hit
yes and then it's going to ask you for
the password so this is the password
that we provided when we created the
virtual
machine and at that point we are now
successfully logged in and so you can if
you run LS this is just going to print
out the contents of your current
directory and so it looks like we've got
one folder uh in our directory right
here but this is our abunto virtual
machine and anytime you you get a brand
new abun to Virtual Machine the first
thing that we want to do is we want to
update all of the installed packages so
we want to make sure that it's up to
date right just just like installing any
other operating system and to run that
there's two commands that we want to run
so we do pseudo so this is going to give
you well technically we don't need to
run pseudo because we're the root user
but if for some reason you're not the
root user then you always have to use
the keyword pseudo so we do pseudo apt
update and then the second command we
can do two and signs and say pseudo apt
upgrade and then pass in a-y flag the
reason we pass in the- Y flag is because
if you don't pass in this flag what's
going to happen is it's going to do a
few things and then a prompt will come
up or you actually have to hit yes uh
and I always hate having to hit yes when
you pass in the dashy you can let it run
uh and then you can just go do something
else go get some coffee because it is a
fairly long
process if you get this popup it doesn't
really matter what option you choose you
can say keep local version currently
installed or install the package
maintainers version I'm going to select
this one but it shouldn't make a
difference so once all of those packages
are up to date we need to install a
couple of extra
packages and the first thing that we
need to do is well let's actually check
what version of python we're running on
this machine so if I do python D-
version all right so it doesn't look
like Python's installed however if I do
a python 3-- version we can see that we
actually do have python it's just we
have to use Python 3 because a version
three uh of python was installed and so
if you see anything that starts at 3.8
do10 or later you should be good however
if you want to you can always do a
pseudo app inst stall Python and then I
think you could just do a dash and
specify the specific version that you
want but you can you can figure out how
to do that by taking a look at the
python documentation 3.8 do10 or later
is more than good enough for us so we
have python the next thing that we need
to do is we need to install pip and
let's actually double check and make
sure that it's not already installed on
our machine so we can just say pip Das
Das
version we can see there's no pip here
however let's try a pip three--
version and it looks like we don't have
Pip in installed but it's giving us a
little hint on how to install pip so we
can do pseudo app install python 3-
pip and we'll hit why for
yes and once that's done we're going to
use pip to actually install virtual Envy
um because we are going to make use of
virtual environments on this machine as
well so we'll say pseudo pip 3 install
virtual Envy
and so now we should be able to use the
virtual environment
command the next thing that we have to
do is install postgress on this machine
so we'll run pseudo apt install and then
the libraries that we need are
postgressql and postgressql Das
contrib and then we'll do a-y so that we
don't have to hit hit
yes okay so we've got postgress
installed how exactly do we connect to
it uh so what we're going to first do is
before we try to connect to it from our
local machine I want to connect to it
from the actual auntu computer itself
the auntu virtual machine uh and so
we're actually going to take a look at
the the CLI for accessing the postgress
database and so the tool that we use to
do this through CLI is called
psql right and we should be able to have
access to it so if you do psql - verion
you should see that it should respond
back with something so that means psql
is installed and if I do a psql --el
it's going to show us the different
flags that we can pass in um but the
main flag that we want to pass in is the
dasu so we can specify what's the
username that we want to connect
to so let's say psql then- capital u and
then our username and we know that when
we install postgress it's going to
install call a user on the database
called postgress so that's what we
always use to connect to it by default
and see we say postgress and if you want
to you can specify the specific database
you want to connect to I believe there's
a flag it might be- D yep the database
name so you could technically say- D
postest but postest is going to be the
default so you can leave that
off and we're connecting to uh our Local
Host which is going to be the default as
well so we don't need to pass in that
and the port we can also pass that in
the default is 5432 which is what it's
running on so we don't really have to
touch anything else and we're going to
try and connect like this so let's see
what
happens all right and we get this error
it says psql error fatal peer
authentication failed for user postgress
so for some reason it's saying peer
authentication failed and this is a
special meaning right it sounds like a
regular login failure but it's not and
it's because postrest when you install
it on a buntu it has a special way of
authenticating users by default so when
it comes to local authentication and
what I mean by local authentication is
the abtu VM connecting to the database
itself that's what a local
authentication means whereas if I'm
connecting from my Windows machine to
the postris database on this uh on this
auntu VM that is not called that is not
considered local authentication so since
we are on the same machine that we're
trying to connect to our database uh
postgress considers this a local
authentication and on a buntu we have a
special configuration uh called Pure
Authentication
now this is the default configuration
for postgress and what peer
authentication does is it actually takes
the user that's logged in to the abunto
machine and it tries to log in as that
user essentially so even though we pass
in the - flag since I am technically
logged in as the root user all right
postgress is going to error out because
it will only
allow a auntu user called postest to be
able to log in as the user called
postest on the postest database little
confusing right but it actually connects
it actually obtains the username from
the Linux kernel so whoever you're
logged in is that's the only person you
can log in as uh and so what we can do
is first of all um because this is the
default configuration um postgress
understands that so postgress actually
created a user on our auntu VM called
postgress so if you want to see the list
of all the users on your auntu machine
you can do a pseudo cat etcp passwd
and you can see all of the users that
have been installed and you can see that
it actually created a user called
postgress on this machine so I'm going
to change that user so we can do that by
doing
Sue Dash and then the name of the user
so
postgress right and notice how we
changed to this specific
user and so now if I try to do
psql
dasu
postest we can now log into the database
so if you see this that means you're
successfully logged into the postrest
database and while we're logged in here
before we do anything else because first
of all we're going to get rid of that
pure authentication because I hate it uh
we want to create a password for our
postgress user and to assign a password
to this user we can say um backs
slash password and then the name of the
user that we want to assign a password
to so we're going to use the postest
user and then here we're going to
provide our
password all right and so now we should
have a password and I'm going to exit
out of here so to exit out of the
postgress uh console or terminal
whatever you want to call it you just do
backs slash and then Q for quit and then
we're we're still logged in as the
postgress user and so if you type in
exit it's going to take us back to the
root
user there's going to be a few more
things that I want to change to our
postgress installation uh and so anytime
you want to modify the configs for
postgress uh what we want to do is we
want to move to a different directory so
the command to move to a different
directory is CD and then we specify the
path to the directory so we want to go
to/ Etc so generally any application you
install on Linux or a bun machine
usually the configs for that that
package or that application is going to
be in/ Etsy and then here I'm going to
say postgress
slash and then if I hit tab you can see
that it's going to autocomplete so
you're going to specify whatever version
of postgress you ran uh and so in this
case uh I have postgress 12 but if you
installed a version 13 then you would
put in it would be a folder called
13 and then we go to Main and if I type
in LS we'll see all of the files that we
have in this folder and the two main
files that we want to focus on are PG
HPA com so this is where we configure
postgress as well as postgress ql.com
and so we're going to open up postgress
ql.com so I'm going to say pseudo VII
postgressql
com and we want to kind of scroll down
and we want to take a look at the
connections and authentication section
uh and so if you take a look at the
default configuration uh we can see that
under listen addresses it's only going
to allow Local Host to connect to our
database that means only when we're
logged into this auntu VM can we then
log in to this postgress database it is
not going to allow me to take PG admin
on my Windows machine and connect to it
remotely and so I want to change this
and technically you don't have to do
this um but you know if you do want to
be able to connect to it remotely then
you want to change these
configs and so I'm going to put this
config we're going to say listenor
addresses
equals and then here you would provide
the IP
addresses uh and so you know if you
wanted to only be able to connect to
this database from you know uh your your
office then you would put the IP address
or domain name of your office if you
want to allow all IP addresses to
connect to it you would just do a star
so that's what I'm going to do it's
going to allow me to connect to this
regardless of what computer I'm on or
where I am on the network however it
generally when it comes to best
practices you want to really narrow down
the scope of the different IPS and
domains that can access your database
because that's the most important part
of your application you want to make
sure it's as secure as
possible all right so we'll save this
that's the only change we need to make
in this
file then the next file that we need to
change is PG HBA comp so we'll do the
same thing sud VI PG HBA
comp and we're going to scroll
down and we're going to take a look at
our default configuration so I did
mention that uh when we connect locally
it uses a peer authentication so you can
see that uh for local
connections and I forget what the second
column is if we actually scroll up well
I got to go up actually let's see what
the second column
is okay so this is going to be the
format of it so this is going to specify
what type of connection uh then what
database this connection should be
associated with or this rule should be
associated with what's the user and then
what's the method uh well we also have
address and Method if you are connecting
remotely so we want to change this so we
want to say for local users regardless
of you know what database they connect
to uh and what user they connect as we
want to make sure that we do not use
pure authentication we use regular
password based authentication uh which
is MD 5 in this
case uh and so here we're just going to
change this so this is saying uh for any
database this rule is going to apply for
the user postest we're going to say
instead of Pier we want md5 like we have
here we'll say
md5 and we're going to change this one
to md5 as well
and then lastly uh for these two
sections right here um these are going
to be for remote connection so if I want
to connect from my Windows machine this
is the rule that's going to apply so
this is saying that for you know hosts
uh for any database any user right now
the only IP addresses that can connect
to it are going to be 12701 which means
Local Host so that's effect effectively
blocking all remote connections so I'm
going to go here and we are going to
change this
and I'm going to say 0.0.0 sl0 so this
means any IP
address and then just to keep things
nicely formatt I'm going to move that
over there and then we're going to do
the same thing for IPv6 which is what
this line is
doing and I'm going to
say this so this is the syntax in IPv6
for saying any IP address
and that should be all of the config
changes that we need to
make and so I'm going to exit out of
here and make sure to save it all right
and at this point you probably think the
changes have been made however generally
uh when you change any configuration
file you actually have to restart the
application for the changes to take
effect and so to restart an application
you do system CTL restart and then the
name of the application so this is going
to be
postgress Q
all right and it should be running at
this point so let's try this out
now uh right now we are still logged in
as the root user so remember before we
actually had to change to the postest
user on our auntu machine before we can
log in as the postgress user so now
instead I'm going to do psql dasu
postgress and I want to see if I'm able
to log in and so now I have actually get
a prompt for a password so it looks like
things are working so far so I'll try my
password and now we are successfully
logged in to our postrest database
that's
perfect now let's actually try to
connect to it using PG admin on so PG
admin I've got my local machine which is
right here if I want to add a new
machine I'm going to right click on
servers we're going to select create
server give this a name I'm going to
call this uh fast API DPR
call it whatever you want connection
details uh here we're going to provide
the IP address so I already forgot
what's the IP address of our
machine we logged in 13 4122 whatever
that
is we're going to provide
this that's the default Port uh that's
the the the user we're going to connect
as and then if we want to we can put in
a password here as well
all right and now we are successfully
logged in to our production database if
I open this up take a look at the
databases we just have the one default
database that always gets installed till
now we've done everything as the root
user and it's generally frowned upon in
the Linux World regardless of what
flavor of Linux you're using it could be
a buntu Centos Red Hat you generally
don't want to be logged in as the root
user because it opens the door for
potential security vulnerabilities and
it opens the door for you to potentially
break your machine and so what we're
going to do is we're going to create
another user this user is going to have
root privilege so he'll still be able to
make any of the changes but it's better
than being logged in as the root user
and more importantly when we actually
install our API our python application
we're going to have our nonroot user be
the one responsible for starting it we
don't want the root user to start the
application because then we're giving
our application root access to our
machine and that is very risky so
instead we want a non-root user to start
our API
so on Linux to create a new user you
type in the command user
mod sorry not user mod we do add user
and then the name of the user so pick
any name you want um I'm going to do
sanie in this case but you can name it
like Fast API or whatever you
want and then it's going to ask you for
a password so put whatever password you
want and then you can provide your name
but none of that really matters and just
hit Y here here and so we've now created
a user and what we can do is uh if you
want to you can do ae- and then
sanie and then it's going to move you to
the sanjie user um or what you can do is
you can exit out of this connection and
then exit out of here altogether so now
we're back on our local machine and
instead of when you do an SSH route at
whatever you can change this to the new
user that you just created and so that's
going to log you in directly as that
user now this user by default doesn't
have root access so if I try to do um
you know
pseudo apt
upgrade right it's going to ask for
pseudo password for sanie and I'll put
my password in and take a look at the
error that we get it says sanie is not
in the pseudor file this incident will
be reported so anytime you create a user
you have to give him pseudo access or
root access so that he can actually
perform operation that require root
privilege so we're going to have to exit
out of here once again I'm going to log
back in as the root
user and to give a user root access we
you run the command user mod and then we
pass in the flag d a and then capital G
make sure it's capital and we say pseudo
and then the name of the user so I
created a user Nam sanie so I'll just
put that in and so at this point the
user saniv has root access so let me
exit out of here again and we're going
to connect back as the user San
Chief and so now I'm going to run
pseudo apt
upgrade and so if I try that put my
password in you can see the command run
so we now successfully have root access
if you type in
PWD this is going to tell you the exact
directory that you're in so I'm in a
folder called slome sanie so whatever
your username was created as right it's
going to your default home directory is
going to be slome and then your username
and so while you're in your home
directory and if you don't know how to
get to your home directory you could
just say CD and then Tilda so that's
going to take you to your home directory
or you can do CD slome and then your
username that's going to take you here
whoops all right so once you're in your
home directory what we're going to do is
we're going to create a folder for our
application technically you can put this
anywhere on your machine I'm just going
to put it in my home directory so I'm
going to call this um this folder app or
we could call it fast API it doesn't
really matter I'll say MK dur this is
the command to create an app sorry
create a directory I'm going to call
this
app and then to move into that app we do
CD app and within this folder what we're
going to do is just like we did on our
local machine we're going to create a
virtual environment so I'm going to say
virtual
envy and then we'll call our virtual
environment venv
all right and then if I do an LS minus
La let's just make sure I created the
virtual Envy folder then to activate our
virtual environment we'll type in the
command Source then we go into the that
folder the bin folder and then the
activate file all right and then we
should see this little nugget right here
so this is going to let us know that we
are currently in a virtual environment
and if you ever want to get out of the
virtual environment you can just say
deactivate within our app directory
we're going to create another folder
called source so this is going to
contain all of our source
code so we'll CD into the
source and now what we're going to do is
we're going to copy all of our code onto
this
machine and so how do we do that well
since we already have it stored on
GitHub all we have to do is just go to
the URL for our repository so this is my
repository that I created this is the
main one uh called Fast API - course
this is public so any of you guys can
access this but you're going to go to
your specific repository and once you
get to the repository this is going to
be the URL or you can just select code
right here and then this is going to
give you a little link to copy so we can
just copy that and then we can go back
here and we can say get
clone paste that in here and then before
you hit enter hit space and then dot so
that's going to install in this current
directory and it's not going to uh
create another directory that's the name
of my uh Repository which is kind of
annoying I don't actually want a
directory called Fast api. course so
we'll hit that we'll run it it's going
to clone it and at this point if I do an
LS we should see all of our specific
code great now before we do anything
else let's reactivate our virtual
environment so we'll say
Source
VNV lib sorry not lib bin activate all
right we've got our virtual environment
set up again
and we're going to move into our source
directory and if you recall remember we
don't have any packages installed so we
don't even have fast API installed but
we do have our requirements.txt file so
if I just cat that real quick if you
forgot what that was that's going to
tell this machine exactly what version
of every single uh dependency we need to
install for our application to work and
so we can just install all of those with
one command by doing pip install d r
requirements.txt
all right so I got an error and this was
expected on my end because when I was
running through this I ran into this
eror and so if you see this eror right
here you know anytime you see red it's
never good but what you want to do is
you want to go right about here where it
says include and then libpq f.h this is
implying that we're missing a package
that's probably called libpq if you
actually search this error you're going
to get the same result so if you run
into this exact issue or even another
issue just look for the library
mentioned right here where it says that
include line right and just search for
that library and just see how to install
it okay so it's since it said we're
missing this Library I'm going to do a
sorry it's not actually a pip install we
actually have to do an apt install so we
do pseudo apt
install and actually before I even do
that I'm going to
deactivate my virtual environment and
we're going to do a Pudo app
install
libpq-dev
all right so now that we've got that
library that missing Library installed
we're going to then go back into our
virtual
environment and we're going to run that
same command to install all of our
requirements and I have to move into my
source
folder all right and it looks like we
have successfully installed all of our
packages the next thing that I actually
want to do is let's go ahead and try to
start our application so we have access
to UV corn so we can just do UV corn
app. main so this is the same exact
command that we ran on our local machine
and then app we don't need to pass in
the reload flag because this is our
production server so we would never want
it to automatically reload on changes
because no one should be making changes
on our production server so we'll run
this and let's see what happens right
and it looks like we get eight
validation errors which is to be
expected because it looks like we are
missing all of our environment variables
and that's correct we never set our
environment variables so in the next
section we're going to take a look at
how we can set up our environment
variables on our Linux
machine okay so let's get started on
creating our envir variables so what we
want to do is to create an environment
variable on a Linux machine we say
export and then we give the name of the
uh variable uh here this is just a
demonstration so I'm going to say mycore
name and then we set equals and then
whatever value we want to give it so you
can give it anything I'm just going to
say this
is Tangie all right so we'll hit that
we'll run that and then to actually see
if this worked to see all of your
environment variables we just say print
NV and so this is going to spit out a
whole bunch of uh default environment
variables and then to see uh the one we
sent just kind of look down look for my
name and we could see that it was
successfully set so at this point we
could just go one by one and manually
set all of these however that is a very
inconvenient process and I wouldn't
expect you guys to do that um because
you know we've got seven or eight and
any other project could have 10 20 30 so
it's not really realistic to do that you
know one environment variable at a time
so let me quickly remove this
environment variable which you can do
with the unset command and so I can just
say unset myor name and if I do a print
Envy we should see that it's no longer
there and what we're going to do is I'm
going to go back to my home directory
because I don't want to mess around in
my application directory I'm going to go
to CD and then the Tilda or you can do
slome SL and then whatever your username
is I'm just going to do that all right
so this is going to take me back to my
home directory and I'm going to create a
brand new
file and if you want to create an empty
file you can just say touch and then I'm
going to just call this EnV all right so
we should by doing LS minus La we should
have the EnV file right here and I'm
going to open that
up and here I can provide a list of all
of the environment variables so I can
say um and keep in mind this has to be
in the same exact syntax so we have to
say just like we would put on the CLI we
would say export
then the name of the variable so I'll
say you know my name
again equals sanie and then let's maybe
let's do mycore
password which is going to be password 1
3 so I can save this file and I can say
source. EnV so this is going to set all
of those environment variables so if I
do a print NV
now we do have my name
and somewhere along here yep we've got
my password so that's another way of
setting things it's a it's a little bit
easier to kind of keep everything in a
file um but what I don't like is that I
have to put it in this format where I
put export and then the environment
variable what would be awesome is if I
could just somehow get it so that the
environment variable file in my abunto
machine matches with the environment
variable file on my local machine I want
to just be able to put the uh the key
and the value pair like here and so that
way I could just copy this paste it into
my production server and just change the
values there uh and so we can actually
do that it just requires a little bit of
a
modification so let's go back here and
I'm just going to unset both of these
real
quick and we'll just double check it got
removed so they're removed and we're
going to open up
the EnV file and I'm going to just
delete
everything and what I'm going to do is
I'm actually just going to copy this for
now and just paste it in there let's
just see if I can get all of this set
from a file and then we'll change the
values
later and so when you have a regular
file like the one we have right here
where we don't have the word export in
front of it it does require a little bit
more of a complex command but all you
have to do is you run this command so
you do
set-
o all
export then
source and then you provide the path to
the file so this is going to be in my
home directory so it's slome San it just
make sure you swap it out with your
specific username and then we
provide and then we say
set Plus
o
all export all right and so now if I do
a print
NV we can see I've got my database
password my database username I've got
my database Port host name and all of
the variables that I set have now been
set as uh environment variables so
that's what we're going to do however
there's still one minor issue if I exit
out of here or actually sorry not if I
exit if I reboot
and I actually have to do a pseudo to
actually reboot but I'm going to reboot
and I'm going to show you guys that uh
when you reload your machine you lose
your environment variables so we'll give
this about a minute or two to kind of
boot back
up although I find a bunch of machines
boot up fairly quickly so let's just
give this a shot see if we can connect
NOP not
yet all right so I've logged back in
after it rebooted if I do a print EnV
you're going to see that all of the enir
environment variables that I set are all
now gone so how can we get all of these
environment variables to persist through
a reboot because if our machine goes
down comes back up then we lose those
environment variables then our
application's broken well there's a
couple of different ways that we can
have environment variables persist
through a reboot U one of the ways is
let's go to our home
directory we're going to do an LS minus
L and what I'm going to do is we're
going to go into this profile file and
we're going to set that exact command
that we had run to set my environment
variables uh where is that command this
one right here in that file so copy
this and then just do a vi.
profile and then go to the bottom of the
file and below the last line just paste
that command
in and then we can just
WQ all right and and so this is going to
cause anytime we open up a session or a
terminal uh even through a reboot it's
going to run that specific command so
that those environment variables are all
set right now if you do a print EnV you
will see that it's not set and that's to
be expected because uh we were already
connected to it but if I exit out of
here
reconnect do a print EnV we can now see
that the
our Environ variables are set and then
just to prove to you that this actually
persists through reboot we're going to
reboot this
machine all right so it's rebooted let's
do a print EnV and we can see all of our
environment variables are still set so
this is the method that I'm going to go
with keep in mind when it comes to
environment variables there are a
thousand different ways to tackle this
uh and so people like to set their
environment variables in different ways
this is just the way that I've done it
this is the simplest way um but there
are you know a number of different other
methods some of them will probably be
more recommended um better um but I want
to keep things as simple as possible the
one thing I do want to uh kind of
highlight is that our environment
variable is stored in my home directory
it is not in the app directory where all
my application code is and that's
important to me because I don't want to
put it in my application code because I
don't want it to accidentally get
checked into get I don't want anyone to
accidentally see my production passwords
or anything like that because then my
entire application is compromise so I
like to keep it separate by moving it
into a completely separate folder so
that there's no chance that it gets
mixed up in my application code all
right so since we can connect to our
postrest database let's go ahead and
actually create the database within this
machine uh so I'm going to select right
click here and I'm going to say create
database I'll call your database
whatever you want I'm just going to call
it fast API to keep things
simple and so now we have our database
once we click on it and so now it's up
and running and so since we have that
information and we have the information
for connecting to our actual postgress
instance on this machine Let's update
these environment variable files so that
um they are accurate at this point
because I believe they're still pointing
to whatever our production was set
as sorry our development environment so
uh here the host name is still going to
be Local Host uh the port since I
installed uh postgress on the default
Port we can keep that the same uh you
want to make sure you update your
production password I chose the same
exact password just to keep things
simple the database name we just created
one called Fast API uh here this is
going to be the database username if you
want to uh it is recommended to create
another postgress user uh however I'm
just going to keep this as the default
postgress user to keep things as simple
you definitely want to upgra update the
secret key uh the algorithm uh you can
leave that as default uh and then the
axess token I'm going to make this a
little bit
longer let's do 300
minutes all right and now let's
reactivate our environment so I'm going
to go into
Apps and then we'll
do source
VNV bin activate so it's going to
activate our virtual
environment and right now you're
probably notice a little bit of an issue
and that is that we don't have any
tables right now you go to our
schemas and then our we got no tables in
here oh sorry we're in the wrong
database in the fast API we've got no
tables right nothing here uh and so we
have to set up all of our models now
however since we are in our production
environment and since we've set up
olymic you'll see that this is dead
simple and when it comes to olymic it's
important that in your production
environment you never create revisions
in your production environment you only
create it in your development
environment and you check it into G and
since we checked it into git if we go to
source and then go into our lmic file
folder and do an LS and then go into
versions We have all of our revision
files and so what we can do is we can
just sorry I didn't mean to hit exit got
to log back in now all right make sure
that virtual environment's enabled every
time uh I'm going to go into source and
what I'm going to do is I'm going to do
Olympic
upgrade and then head so this is going
to uh set up our database and it's going
to uh upgrade it to the latest
revision all right and take a look at
that it created all of the individual
revisions one at a time so we can we
could still roll back just the same
exact way that we did in development and
with just a click of a button we've got
our entire database schema all set up
and we can just refresh this real quick
and then go into our tables and you can
see that we've got our three tables plus
the Olympic table as well so now that we
have our database all set I think it's
time we try to start our application
again so moving to your apps directory
uh and if you've already and if you
haven't activated your virtual
environment do that again
move into the source directory and now
we're going to run the same UV corn
command that we ran in our development
environment all right so it says it's
running on the Local Host IP address of
this machine on Port 8000 which is the
default Port so let's try to connect to
it so what we have to do is grab this
and we're just going to paste the IP
address into our browser and we're going
to do colon Port
8000 and let's see if this
works and it looks like it didn't work
so what happened well the problem here
is that we needed to make sure that it
can listen on any IP address so when you
just set uh this to 127.0.0.1 that means
only this machine can access it so I'm
going to controlc out of this so we're
going to stop it and we're going to pass
in one more flag we're going to say d D-
host and then provide the I IP of 000000
so we're going to listen on any IP uh
that this machine is potentially running
and if you wanted to if I did a d-el
real quick uh we can also specify what
port we want to listen on so if I do--
Port I can provide a different port so
it doesn't go to the default Port 8000
but I'm going to keep it as Port 8,000
you're going to see that It ultimately
doesn't matter when we actually deploy
because we're going to deploy it in a
way that it's always going to use either
Port 80 or port 443 which is the default
port for HTTP and https so this is good
enough we're going to start it again now
you can see it's listening on any IP and
we're going to refresh and if you guys
can't see that cuz it's tiny we can see
that I got message hello world which is
accessing that root path that we have so
it looks like things are working at this
point however right now you know if we
if this program crashes um or if we
reboot our machine you're going to see
that it doesn't actually restart
automatically uh and so what we're going
to do is we're actually going to use a
process manager so we're going to use
something called
gunicorn so control C out of that
instead of just starting our application
with uorn we're going to use
gunicorn and if you don't if you haven't
already installed it which you probably
haven't do pip
install G
unicorn and make sure you're in the
virtual environment
and so gunicorn is going to be
responsible for starting our application
now I've already got this installed
because I added it to my
requirements.txt file a little bit
earlier um but if you haven't done that
that's fine because I haven't told you
guys to do that so just do a pip install
G unicorn and if you get any errors most
likely you'll need two other packages
you'll need pip uh just you'll need HTTP
tools and so you can just do a pip
install of HTTP tools
and you'll also need one extra Library
which is uh UV tools so if you so if you
hit any other errors moving forward
right go ahead and install those two
libraries HTTP tools and UV tools and
that should fix any errors that you have
so those were some potential errors that
I ran into uh when I was kind of doing a
quick test run um but at this point we
should have access to our to a g unicorn
command so I can say G unicorn and let's
just do a quick qu uh
d-el just to see what options we have
and here what's nice is that you can
actually set the number of workers so
you know if you have if you're on a
multi-threaded machine or or you have a
virtual machine with multiple CPUs you
could set up more than one worker so
that they're all listening all at once
and then it's going to get load balanced
across all of them so we're going to set
up four by default just to show you you
could set up one it doesn't really
change anything so the command is going
to be G
unicorn DW so this is for the number of
workers we're going to say I want four
workers and then we're going to say-
K we're going to say UV
corn.
workers do capital
uvn capital
worker all right and then now we just
specify how to start our application
like we normally do so we go into our
app folder we grab the main file and
then we start app
and then you know just like we did with
UV coin a little bit while ago we had to
start it with the-- host uh and then do
all zeros here with guu vorn sorry G
unicorn we have to use a D- bind and
then we do0 do0 do
zero and then we specify the port we
want to listen on let me drag this so it
looks a little easier to read so we do
that and then the port that you want to
listen on
let's start that and it looks like I got
a couple of Errors so let's see what
happened all right and so if you get
this error UV Loop uh it means we're
missing a library and so like I said if
you get any errors make sure you do the
PIP install HTTP tools I should have
this one already installed and then you
want to do a pip install UV
tools and I realized I've been making a
mistake it's not called UV tools it's
going to going to be UV
Loop all right and so now it's
successful so uh not not UV tools UV
loop I guess I got it mixed up with HTTP
tools and so you can go ahead and if you
actually wanted to uh if you did a pip
freeze you could go ahead and copy this
and make this your new requirements.txt
file that you check in to get this is
going to have uh gunicorn automatically
in there because we already installed it
it's going to have UV Loop and it's
going to have the what is the last one
that we needed HTTP tools which is right
here uh and so you can check this
version into git uh and so that way it's
all up to date and so when you deploy to
other auntu machines or other computers
uh it's going to have all of these extra
packages so you can deploy right away
all right and now let's run the same
gunicorn
command and now it looks like it started
it says it's listening on this port and
notice something interesting look at
this it actually started up four worker
nodes and you can even see the process
IDs so this is probably the parent ID
and then these are the little worker IDs
so if you wanted to we can open up
another
connection and I can do a ps- a pipe
grap we could probably just grip for uh
g g
unicorn yep and so you could see all of
the different processes that were
started and so there should be five of
them 1 2 3 4 five one of them is the
parent uh process and then the four are
the other child
processes all right now that's working
let's just do a refresh just to make
sure we didn't break anything and it's
still working and so if we do a refresh
you can see that we can still access our
application and if I go to SL dos the
documentation should still be there
perfect so it looks like our app is
working we can test it now um by testing
the individual endpoints but we're going
to hold off on doing that because we're
going to make a few more
changes so the first thing is
right now this is this is running on our
specific terminal and so it kind of
locks up our terminal I want this to be
running in the background and more
importantly I want this to automatically
start up on boot because right now if we
reboot our box right we'd have to
manually log into this device and run
this same command so we have to find a
way to kind of automate it so that upon
reboot it's going to run the application
and we want it to run in the background
so that we don't see any logs by default
and we'll tackle that in the next
video all right guys so in this video
we're going to figure out how we can
have this uh command automatically run
upon reboot as well as how can we run
this as a background process so that we
don't hang our terminal so what we're
going to do is just do a contrl c to
stop it for
now and we're going to what we're going
to do is we're going to create our own
service and if you ever run system CTL
and then you know either status or start
uh or or restart and then the name of
some of some application that you wanted
to run you know um that is an example of
making use of a service and so what
we're going to do is we're going to
create we're going to make our own
service which starts this application
here for us and you'll see that it's
actually pretty simple uh if we go to/
Etsy SL
systemd and then system and I forgot to
do a CD to move into that directory
if you do an LS these are all of the
services that have been installed on our
machine and we're just going to create a
brand new one so how do we create that
we have to create a couple of files and
I have actually created them for you
guys ahead of time so if you check my
GitHub repo you will see a file called
gunicorn dos
service and there's going to be a couple
things that we have to change so let me
just walk you through what each one of
these lines mean so under unit here
we're just going to give a description
of what this is going to do so this is
going to be a gunicorn instance uh for
to server API you can put whatever
description you want you can say uh demo
fast API application doesn't really
matter after now the next line right
here where it says after network. Target
what this is going to do is this is
going to tell systemd or our abunto
machine when to actually start this
service and so it's saying that hey we
need our network service running before
we can start our uh API because if the
Network's not up then nothing else
really matter so we're going to wait for
Network to come up before we start the
service then on the service we're going
to figure out uh we have to specify what
user is going to uh you know run this
service so we need this to be associated
with the user I created a user called
sanie so I'm going to update this and
then for group you want to just put the
same exact name as the user then we have
to specify the working
directory and so this is going to be the
directory our service is going to be
launched in so um go ahead and update
this to point to the directory your app
is running in and if you don't know what
that is remember just go
home uh then move into Apps and then you
can go into the source folder if you
want and just type in PWD so that's
going to get you the exact path that you
want and so I have to update this with
my
username and then the environment so
because we want this service to run the
G unicorn command uh which is right here
we needed to run in a virtual
environment so to actually set the
virtual environment through this script
we have to say environment equals and
then we set this path variable and we
just point it to the exact path to our
uh Bin folder so once again you don't
know how to get there just go to your
app folder go into your virtual
environment go into your bin folder and
then just type in PWD and that's going
to get you the
path and so I just have to update this
with my username and you'll just do the
same thing you just have to update the
username uh then we have to specify the
exact command to run so we we have to
provide the path to where the gunicorn
command resides on so it actually sits
in the bin folder uh so if you actually
do an LS here right you can see the G
unicorn
command and so that's going to give it
the path to the command and then after
that well actually I have to update my
username once
again right and after that it's the same
exact command that we ran before so four
workers - k then we have this long
Command right here and then we specify
how to start our application which is
this command and then we're going to
bind it to 0.0.0 and then you can pick
whatever Port that you want and this is
just a default config don't worry too
much about it you you need it but I
don't want to go too far into how Linux
Works to actually explain this just know
that this is just a standard uh
procedure for creating a service so to
actually create the service now what we
do is let's go to/ Etsy
systemd then
system and let me deactivate my
H we don't need to deactivate it's fine
we're going to create our service file
here and so I'm going to do a pseudo VI
and then the name of the the service so
what do you want to call your service so
when you type in uh system CTL and then
start what's the name of the service you
want to type in you get to specify I'm
going to make it so that it's just
called API very simple you can call it
fast API you can call it uh social media
app it doesn't really matter it's up to
you but I'm going to call it
API and since I want to call it API I'm
going to create a a file called API do
service and then what we can do is just
take this copy it and we will paste it
in
here all right and to test out our
service let's do a system
CTL start
API and we're going to have to put in
our password and so this started our
API and if we do a
system CTL status API whoops there
shouldn't be a space CTL status API this
should just give us the status of our
service uh we can see that looks like it
failed that's not good uh and it's going
to provide us some
logs and if we take a look at the logs
you can see algorithm field required
access token expires um field required
so it looks like uh something is wrong
with our environment variables cuz we
saw the same exact are
when we were originally setting this up
before we got the environment variable
so for some reason it's not actually
accepting these environment variables
and the reason for this is that the
service file the service that you create
doesn't have access to users environment
variables and if you actually go back to
our home
directory and then we go to LS uh LS
minus
La remember we created this EnV file uh
and then we loaded it in the profile so
uh the environment variables that get
loaded from profile um aren't accessible
within a service and that's just the way
Services work so what we have to do is
we have to pass in another
field in our service config so that it
knows to pull the environment variables
from that specific file so what we can
do here is uh in this file we're going
to go and just add another line it
doesn't matter where you add the
line but we want to say environment
file make sure to capitalize the E and
the
f equals and then you provide the path
to your specific uh EnV file so mine's
going to be home/
s.v and I'll just copy all of this
again and we'll go back into Etsy
systemd
system and then I'll just do a pseudo
VII api. service
and we're going to replace this file
now all right so now we should be able
to import all of those environment
variables and you there's other way to
to do this you can also set up a config
file for your uh your new service
however I figured it's just easier
because we already have our environment
uh our ourv file so we can just continue
to use that
and now if I do a system CTL restart
API and notice you don't have to type in
api. service uh it's optional you can
you can technically do it like
this and it looks like since we actually
changed the file we have to run this
command
now all right and so now let's do a
system CTL
restart sorry not restart status
API and
uh looks like we got the same exact
error uh let's just do a restart one
more
time and we'll do a status and now it's
up and running perfect look at that so
we've got our four workers uh these are
the process IDs and and let's just
double check and make sure that we can
access our specific website so I'm going
to just Refresh on the SL docs and it
looks like it works let's go to the root
and let's go to the root
URL I'll just change this to the root
URL and see if we get the API response
perfect so it looks like we've got our
application uh up and running there's
just one last thing we need to
do and I wasn't sure if I had already
covered this but there's one last last
thing I want to do and that is I want to
make sure that our service automatically
starts upon a reboot so that way you
know in case our uh machine goes down
whether it's because of a power failure
or something like that or maybe we
perform some sort of upgrade I wanted to
automatically start this service so that
our application is always up and running
if you do a system CTL status API you
could find out pretty easily whether
this service is going to get started
upon a reboot so if you take right take
a look right here under loaded uh and
then right here is the keyword that
you're looking for if you see disabled
right here that means that it's not
going to automatically get started upon
a reboot if you see it's enabled that
means it will automatically get started
upon a reboot so to actually make sure
that it actually does get started upon a
reboot just do a pseudo system
CTL enable and then the name then the
name of the service which is
API and after that if we do a status
again we should see that it moved to
enabled and so now if we reboot our
machine and you guys can go ahead and
test this you'll see that it
automatically starts up the
service right now the way that we have
our deployment set up is that when we
send a request to our server um you know
to the specific IP address of our server
and whatever Port we decided uh to
configure our app to listen on we send
that request directly to the app or
gunicorn in general and this is
technically perfectly fine however
you'll see that in more professional
type deployments what we'll have is a
inter intermediary web server so we'll
have a web server running on our uh
auntu
machine and that web server will receive
the original request and then act as a
proxy and proxy that request to our
specific application or gunicorn in this
case uh and so one of the common web
servers that can be used for that is
enginex there's a couple others like
traffic and ha proxy uh you'll see that
engine X is fairly popular though and
some of the benefits of doing uh this
and configuring our app application
ultimately to be deployed like this is
that engine X is optimized for SSL
termination uh so engine X is a high
performance server and it can perform
all of the SSL termination so when we
when we send an https request uh we can
send it to our engine X server the
engine X server can process it and then
forward it as a plain HTTP packet to our
application because technically we could
configure our application to handle
https it's not optimized for that right
our our app is design to just act as a
plain API when we start adding
responsibilities like performing uh SSL
offload well then you'll see that we
start to see a degradation in
performance and enginex like I said is a
high performance web server it's
optimized for this so it makes sense to
kind of handle that responsibility uh on
engine X instead of our application so
that's what we're going to do we're
going to configure engine X and this is
going to act as the Gateway into our
system so any request we send to our
system uh whether it's https or HTTP
doesn't really matter we're going to
send it to engine X and if we send it as
https what engine X will do is it'll
then take it and send it and forward it
as an HTTP packet to our application and
so I'm going to walk you through how to
set up engine X it's not difficult we do
have one config file that we have to add
but outside of that it's fairly easy to
get this up and
running let's install engine X now to
install a package we can do pseudo app
install and then engine X and then Dy
so that installed engine X if we do a
system
CTL start engine X that's going to start
up the engine X service and so now if
you go to your server IP address you're
going to see that you get this welcome
message so this is just the default page
that engine X loads up for you and we're
going to change this so in engine x what
we want to do is we want to go to/ Etsy
engine X sites and then available it's
important that you do available because
there's also a sites enabled which is
not what you want you want available and
this's this default config file or
technically this is a server block and
if we take a look at
this you can see the default
configuration in this case uh just to
show you what that looks like you can
see that this is handling HTTP traffic
that's why it's Port 80 it's going to
listen on Port 80 and this is going to
act as the default server so all
requests that come here are going to
land on this server block and we've got
the same thing for IPv6 as well uh and
then this is the file that you actually
see so when you navigate to this page
it's actually loading up a file that's
inbar www
HTML and then the server name so this is
going to be the actual domain names
that's going to handle requests for this
is basically saying
everything um everything else don't
worry too much about that but what we're
going to do is we're going to change
that file a little bit and I've provided
an example file
here and so this is what an the example
file looks like we can leave pretty much
everything in place the only thing I
want to change is this location block
and so this is what is going to allow
engine X to act as a proxy uh
specifically this line This is the main
line you don't technically need the
other ones uh those are more of
optimizations but all this is saying is
that any
requests um that match this the the root
path or Beyond essentially is going to
get proxied to Local Host Port 8000
which is what G unicorns running on so
you just specify the IP address and the
port that you want to proxy traffic for
uh and so since gunicorn was configured
to run on Port 8,000 we're just going to
forward it to gunicorn in this case so I
want you to just copy these lines here
and we're going to go in and I'm going
to just open up that default file
now and we can delete these three
lines I'm just going to paste that
in and at that point I can save
this and then we want to do a system CTL
restart engine
X so it's restarted and if I refresh
this right we can now see our API and if
I go to SL
dos it should also work as
well so we got engine X set up and
running the last thing that we have to
do uh regarding engine X specifically
well it's not really enginex specific
but in general is that right now if you
take a look at it you can see our web
browser says not secure and that's
because I can actually copy
this I paste it right we're using HTTP
and not https so we need to set this up
for https so how do we do that well
we're going to tackle that in the next
video um but you're going to need a
domain name uh if you want this to work
with https so uh I'll show you guys how
to kind of grab a cheap domain name
however if you don't have one uh don't
worry uh you can just leave it as https
for now or you can create a self-sign
certificate whichever one works for
you for my application I purchased a
domain name called san. XYZ so if you've
ever watched any of my other videos this
is always the the default domain name
that I use for demonstration purposes uh
you can see that I actually bought axyz
because they're the cheapest so if you
just want to play around just for
learning purposes uh get axyz they're
usually like a dollar for for like an
entire year um but if you get a com it's
going to be a little bit more expensive
however depending on you know what your
domain name is it at most is still well
not at most but it'll you can still find
plenty at $12 per year so it's not too
bad and I happen to purchase my domain
name from names cheap so this is my
domain regar however there's plenty of
other options if you want to use GoDaddy
if you want to use any of the other um
any of the other websites you can even
use Amazon if you wanted to um feel free
to use whichever one you want you just
need to get a domain name I'm going to
be using this one moving forward but
just keep that in
mind and what we want to do is we want
to set up a couple of rules and we
actually have to point our domain name
to digital ocean and digital ocean has
this excellent writeup uh how to point
your digital ocean name servers from
common domain regars and they actually
show you how to do this for a lot of the
main domain registers and they have
names cheap here as well so if you get
one of these you can just follow along
but you'll see that you know any domain
provider um you'll be able to kind of
relatively click around and just kind of
navigate yourself and figure figure out
what's the equivalent because for the
most part the uis are all fairly similar
um but if we go to down to names cheapap
uh you can see that what we have to do
is under the name server section we have
to do custom DNS and then we point it to
the DNS servers of digital oce so ns1
digital o.com ns2 ns3 so let's do that
and I've actually already set that up
for us so you just go under name servers
select custom do uh custom DNS and then
you have ns1 digital ocean.com ns2
digital ocean.com and ns3 digital
ocean.com and there'll be a little check
Mark so just check that there and at
that point it's going to point
everything to our digital ocean
servers then in digital ocean um if you
just select your name here in your
dashboard what you want to do is you
want to go to um manage DNS on digital
ocean and then here you want to enter
your domain so this is going to be
sanjie doxyz We'll add this
domain and the first thing that we have
to do is we have to create a a record so
this is root of your domain so I'm just
going to say at symbol this is going to
create an a record and we want to select
the specific droplet that we created so
this one is ABN to a fast API you should
only have one um but if you have other
droplets make sure you select the right
one and then select create
record and at this point if we do sanjie
doxyz um in our web browser it's going
to take
us to our digital ocean server um
however keep in mind uh the the changes
to DNS usually take a little while to
propagate so you could potentially have
to wait up to an hour or 2 hours names
cheep says it could take up to a day but
it never takes a day so if you don't see
these changes immediately just give it
you know 10 15 minutes and then you'll
see that they work um but I'm going to
add one more and that's going to be for
my subdomain because I don't want to
just do san. XYZ I also want to redirect
www. san. XYZ to my server so I can
create a cname
record and I can say www
and so you can see what this is going to
look like and I'm just going to say at
simpol right here so that's going to
point it to this record
essentially all right and so what this
is what this is saying is that if you
send a request to san. XYZ it's going to
send it to the IP address of server and
then if you send a request to the
subdomain of www. san. XYZ it's going to
be an alas for san. XYZ so it's
essentially just going to follow
this all right and so now if I go to
sanjie doxyz
you can see that we are successfully
able to access our API and if I go to SL
docs once again this should still work
as well and that's pretty big let me
minimize that and if I do the same thing
for my
subdomain of www. Sanji
doxyz this should also work all right so
we've got our domain set up and once we
have our domain we can now finally set
up uh SSL so we can handle secure https
traffic because we don't want to send
our application traffic over HTTP and we
want that nice little lock symbol that
green lock symbol so we'll tackle that
in the next video okay so it's now time
to set up SSL for our application so I
want you to search for certbot so this
is the website for let's encrypt which
is a free SSL
service and here they've got excellent
documentation uh what we want to do is
Select get certified instructions and
then we can just specify what's software
we're running so this is for engine X
and the system is going to be a bun of
20.04 the reason it asked for this
information is that it actually will
automatically reconfigure engine X for
you to handle https because um normally
when you want to set up https you have
to change some configs in engine X and
it gets a little
complicated and so the it's saying the
first thing that we have to do is we
have to install snapd uh if you
installed a buntu um you know from
digital
ocean snapd should automatically be
installed for you so you can do snap d--
version I
think or is it snap D- version I think
it's snap version yeah okay so it's snap
Okay so we've got snap installed that's
perfect and then what we want to do is
we want to
install with this Command right here so
just copy this and we're pretty much
just going to follow this website
because I to like I said the
instructions are fantastic so we'll
install
cbot all right cbots installed then we
want to do this
command so you have two options you can
either just generate a
certificate or you can have cbot
automatically configure engine X for you
we're going to have cbot do the work for
us and so we can just paste this
in all right and then we have to provide
an email address so this is going to be
whatever email you want to use
and then we got to agree to the terms of
service uh you can do no for this
one right then we have to specify what
domain names we want to generate a
certificate for so we want to generate a
certificate for sanjie doxyz in my case
and then
www. sanie
doxyz all right and it looks like it did
some magic to our default config file
that we were the we were originally
changing so if we actually go to the
sites available folder which we're
already at and just do a cat
default you're going to notice some
changes to this file and that's because
surf bot actually made a whole bunch of
changes and the main change is uh where
where are these
changes uh not here not here here we go
so This Server block is for SSL
configuration and so these are the
changes they made so we're going to
listen on Port 443 so that's the default
SSL or https Port that's good and I
guess that's for IPv6 this is for ipv4
these are going to be the two
certificates that were
generated and then there's a few other
configs that it added and we also have
this server block right here which is
going to actually redirect HTTP requests
to https so we can never even use HTTP
anymore it's going to ensure that our
clients always use https and it'll
redirect them to https and you can see
that right here you know if host equals
www. san. XYZ we want to send a 301
redirect to https and then host request
right here and we're doing the same
thing for just the sanjie doxyz and so
that's all done by sbot and so now if I
go
here and I
do sanjev do oops
doxyz take a look at this we got the
little green lock that means connection
security that means we're using https
and you can see the https here and if I
hardcode it to be
HTTP look at that it still has the lock
because it redirected to
https and let's just make sure that the
docs work
now and it looks like the doc still
works so we now have https setup on our
engine X server and just like we did
with our service we want to make sure
that engine X has been set up to
automatically start upon reboot so we
could do a system CTL status engine X
and let's just quickly verify if it's if
it has been set up to do so and I can
see that on mine it's set up to be
enabled so it will automatically start
upon reboot which is what we want um and
I think this is the default
configuration when you uh install and
set up engine X however if you see
disabled here just go ahead and do a
system CTL uh enable engine X and that's
going to make sure that it will be moved
to an enabled state so it'll get started
upon a
reboot the last thing that we need to do
to complete our deployment process is
set up a firewall on our machine and the
reason we want to set up a firewall is
just for basic security purposes we want
to make sure that we only open up ports
that we're going to be using uh cuz
right now you can access this box on any
port and we want to make sure that we
really Harden our system so that only
the traffic that should be sent to this
box is allowed to this box we don't want
people trying to connect to different
services on our on our machine that they
shouldn't be so we're going to be using
a the built-in firewall uh called ufw
and if we do a pseudo ufw status right
the ufw is the firewall uh and so you
can see right now it's inactive and
that's perfect and what we have to do is
we have to set up a whole bunch of rules
and we have to tell the firewall what
kind of traffic should we allow to our
machine and we can run pseudo ufw allow
and then we can
specify you know what specific Port we
want to allow traffic on what specific
IP addresses should we should be able to
talk to so since this is a public API we
want to make sure that technically
anyone can access our server uh from
HTTP and https so we're going to do
allow HTTP so this going to allow HTTP
traffic and you can see it created an
ipv4 and an IPv6 rule we want to allow
https traffic and keep in mind we have
to SSH to our machine so we can access
it so we have to allow SSH as
well and if you wanted to you could also
allow 5432 so that's going to be uh to
allow postgress graic now uh the way
we've set things up you don't need to
actually allow this port because
technically our app right our fast API
is running on the local machine so it's
not going to be hindered by this
firewall so it can access the database
because it's running on the local
machine so if you wanted to make it so
that no one from the outside world can
directly access your database you would
not want to allow this and that's what a
lot of people do because it can be a
little risky opening up your database
Port because then people can potentially
access your database so it's up to you
however if you want to be able to you
know go to PG admin and if you want to
be able to connect to your box remotely
then you're going to have to allow 5432
so it's just up to you it's your
preference do whatever you want to do
I'm going to allow this just for
demonstration purposes so I can show you
that hey when you allow 5432 we can
connect remotely so I'll add that rule
and then finally we have to start our
firewall so we do pseudo ufw
enable and it's just going to tell us
that we could potentially lose
connection because we're starting up a
firewall that's fine and we've started
up a firewall so if I do a pseudo ufw
status you can see that it's active and
you can see all the rules that it's put
in place so it's saying we allow Port 80
traffic from uh anywhere we're going to
allow that that Port 443 we're going to
allow from anywhere and same thing with
SSH and 5432 and all of the IPv6 rules
as well and then everything else is
dropped and blocked and let's just
double check that we can access the
docks and it looks like we can and just
to make sure it's not cached or
something like that still works and now
we've got our
firewall and the firewall will start up
automatically so you don't actually have
to configure anything else uh if you do
want to delete a rule you can do pseudo
ufw
delete allow and then whatever rules so
you can do HTTP or you can do
5432 whichever one you want to
delete so now that we have our
application deployed one of the common
things that you're going to have to do
is um make changes to your application
and then push out those changes so I'm
going to show you guys how we can do
this in a manual process ultimately if
you're developing an application it's
best to set up a very efficient cicd
pipeline but that's a little outside of
the scope of this course so I'm going to
just show you how to do this manually
and you'll see that it only requires a
couple of
commands uh so go ahead and make your
changes uh you know whatever code
changes so I'm going to say uh hello
world couple exclamation points all
right we'll save that and what we're
going to do is we're going to do a get
add-- all again and we're going to do a
get commit DM give it some meaningful
message
changed the
world all right and then we're going to
do a get push
and before we do that if you type in uh
yeah just do a get push uh then we
provide origin which is the name of our
remote and then the branch that we're on
so we can say
Main and that's going to push it up to
our GitHub
repository and at that point once it's
there you can just quickly verify if you
want but I'm going to assume that it's
there and then what we're going to do is
we're going to go into our application
folder
which is in our home directory then we
go into Apps and then
source and then here we're just going to
do a get pull so it's going to pull all
the changes that were made so it's going
to grab the
latest changes and
we'll all right so we've pulled all of
our code
now and keep in mind you know if you had
changed the requirements.txt file then
you definitely want to do a pip install
uh you know pip install dasr
requirements.txt
if you did but we didn't change any of
that so we don't need to do that uh and
what we can do now is we can we have to
restart our application because if I
just refresh this you can see nothing's
changed there's no exclamation points so
we'll do a system tudo system CTL
restart
API and let's try this out
now and we've got all of the exclamation
points now so that's how you push out
changes through a manual process but
like I said it's best to set up a cicd
pipeline in this section we're going to
focus on dockerizing our application I
originally wasn't going to do anything
on Docker but I figured I would just
make a quick video uh just to show you
guys how we can quickly set up our fast
API environment within a Docker based
environment and I'll also show you guys
how to set up a postgress database
within Docker uh this is going to be a
fairly quick run through of Docker I'm
going to assume that you guys have a
basic understanding of Docker I'm going
to assume that you already have Docker
installed on your machine so we're going
to get right to it and get started on
setting up our fast API within
Docker so I have Docker Hub open which
is just you know a public repository of
different uh images that we have access
to you can create an account if you want
to you don't have to create one at this
stage uh the only time we'll need to
create an account for this course is if
you want to push an image up to a you
know a repository hosted on Docker Hub
if you don't want to do that then you
don't need to go ahead and create an
account um but what we want to do is we
want to figure out a image that we're
going to use for our fast API Docker
container uh and so just go ahead and
search for Python and what we're going
to do is we're going to use the official
python image so select the official
python image and you'll see that um
there's a couple of different options so
you can uh scroll down you can see the
different versions of python and we're
actually going to use version 3.97 in
this case but you can see that with the
um default python image we have uh all
of the different versions that we could
pretty much ever want and then they got
slim images they got the Alpine images
as well but we're going to use just the
standard image now if we use this
specific image the problem with this is
that this is just a basic image with
python there's nothing else on it uh and
um at that point if we just have a basic
python container then we have to do all
of the work of copying our source code
onto the uh Docker container and then we
have to install all of our dependencies
and set up our application and that kind
of defeats the purpose of Docker because
the main idea behind Docker is that we
actually create an image that has
everything that we need to run our
application so we just start up the
image or I guess we technically start up
the container which is made from the
image and that should just have
everything it needs and it should just
start working right away so that's
exactly what I want to do and to
actually get that to accomplished we're
going to have to create our own custom
image and all custom images need to
start off with the base image so we're
going to start off with this base python
image and we're going to customize it by
doing a few things uh including copying
our source code into it uh and
installing all the dependencies and
setting up a few other details so to
actually create a custom Docker image uh
we're going to go to our project
directory and we're going to create a
file uh that's referred to as a Docker
file now this Docker file is going to
have all of the steps necessary to
create our own custom image and the
first thing that we have to do is we
have to set up uh or specify our base
image so we're going to use this uh
python
3.97 uh image as the base image so what
we do is we say from and then the name
of the image so this is the python image
and then if we want to we can also uh do
a version so I'm going to do
3.97 and if you're wondering where I'm
getting this from this is all from the
documentation you just say from the name
of the image which in this case is
Python and then you could see the
different tags so if you want 3.97 slim
Bullseye you got that and if you want to
see them going over that in an example
we're kind of basically just following
this
essentially the next step is going to be
an optional step but I always like to do
this we're going to use the
worker FL and this is going to set the
working directory so I'm going to say
this is going to be user Source slapp
now how do I know that there's a uh
folder called user Source I've actually
run the python image myself and I
checked to see where I could actually
set up my application so I found that
there is a path here and then I want to
create a folder called app and this is
where I'm going to store all of my
application code and once again you can
take a look at the documentation and it
does the same thing so um if you ever
lost just take a look at the doc and
it's going to help explain things but
like I said this is the optional command
in this case because what it really does
is it's going to tell Docker this is
where all of the commands are going to
essentially run from so it's like doing
a a CD into SL user sourcea and then
anytime we give it any instructions it's
always going to do do everything in that
directory so it's just going to help
simplify some of the later steps but it
is technically optional uh the next
thing that I want to do is I want to
copy our requirements.txt file from our
local machine onto our Docker container
so we use the copy
command and we say we want to copy
requirements.txt
and then we have to specify the
directory within our container or image
that we want to copy it to so I'm going
to say do slash so where does this
exactly point to well remember we set
our working directory so everything is
going to be with regards to that
directory so when I say the current
directory that means this
directory now if we didn't have this
line right here then we would have to
specify the full path to that directory
so you can see that it's kind of
simplifying things for us because then
we can just kind of Say Hey I want to
use the current directory because that's
what the working directory is and the
next thing that I want to do is run a
command which is going to be uh
responsible for installing all of our
dependencies because we have our
requirements.txt file copied into our
Docker container so we're going to do
pip
install - R and then requirements.txt
and if you want to we can also specify
the--
no-- dur if you wanted to as
well and so that's going to install all
of our
dependencies then the next thing that
I'm going to do is I'm going to to do
copy dot dot so what does this mean this
is going to copy everything in our
current directory uh so all of our
source code and then it's going to copy
it into the current directory in our
container so what is the current
directory well that's the one that's set
by worker and once again if we don't
have this defined then we would have to
specify the full path of SL user Source
slapp now one thing that you might
notice that's a little unusual is the
fact that um we copy all of our source
code at the end right
here which is going to include
everything in our directory including
the requirements. txt file so you might
be wondering well why exactly do we copy
just the requirements.txt file up here
well this is a little bit of an
optimization uh that doctor that Docker
provides us so when Docker runs when we
build images from a Docker file it
actually treats each one of these lines
or steps as a layer of the image so kind
of Builds an image by running the first
layer then creat in the second layer the
third fourth and fifth layer and it
actually caches the result of each step
so this is important because when you
cach the result if nothing changes then
we can just use the cache result so
let's say I you know run this image or I
create an image from this
file it's going to take a certain amount
of time because it has to it has to um
do a pip install requirements.txt where
it's installing all the dependencies
which does take a decent amount of time
but if I run this again right and
nothing changes well then it can just
use the cash result because it knows
nothing's
changed and this is important because um
when I change my source code here maybe
like my database. py file it's going to
see what steps changed right and so if I
change my source code uh does that
change the base image no we're still
using the same uh base image does it
change the working directory that we
used nope still the same did it change
the requirements at txt file nope still
the same uh did it change any um of the
dependencies that we installed
absolutely not it only changed the final
step so this causes Docker to be able to
use the cast result of Step uh one two 3
four of step four and it only has to
rerun step
five but if we change requirements.txt
this file right here then it knows that
this step changed here so it's going to
have to rerun this step then this step
then this step right and so this gives
us an advantage because anytime we
change our source code we only have to
run this last step and if we change our
requirements. txt then we have to run
all of these steps and keep in mind that
this step is the longest step and so if
I had actually like uh if I can comment
this out so if I didn't have this line
and instead I copied all of my source
code right here what would happen is
every time I changed any code in any of
my files I would have to rerun a pip
install every single time
and that would cause us to have to rerun
the longest step in our build process
and so that's why we have this
optimization that's why we copy the
requirements that txt file so that we
can cash that result and so anytime we
make any changes to that file uh sorry
anytime we make any changes to our
source code that's not in that file we
don't have to rerun a pip
install all right and then finally we
have to give it the command that we want
to run when we start the comp uh the
container
so we'll say
CMD brackets and so the command that we
want to run is UV corn app. main app and
so the way we actually specify the
command is we we um break out each word
of the command so here we do UV
corn and then we say app. main
app and then here we're going to pass in
the the host flag and the port flag like
we did on our buntu machine so we do D-
host
Z and we do
d-port that's going to be
8,000 okay so it's basically anytime you
have a space between the commands you
just split it up into a different string
uh within this list that's just kind of
the syntax that you have to use with
these uh Docker files but it's it's the
same thing as running UV corn app.
main app and then D-
host d-port 8,000 oops
8,000 so it's just going to essentially
run this in our container we just have
to provide it in this format all right
and so now our Docker file is complete
and we can actually build our image so
what we're going to do is uh I'm going
to do a Docker and then the command to
build our image is build and then we'll
do a d-el so we can see all of the
different
flags and most of these don't really
match the only one I really care about
is a tag so I want to give this a name
so I'm going to say Docker
build- T and I'm going to give this
image what a name that I think is uh
reasonable I'm just going to call this
fast
API and we have to pass in one last
argument uh which I forgot which is
going to be the um the context uh you
could think of the context as just kind
of the directory where the docker file
is so it's going to be in the current
directory because we can see the docker
file is in the root uh of our folder
structure so I could just say
dot and so now it's actually going to
build
our our image and if I do a Docker image
LS we can see all of our Docker images
and um you'll see that I've got a whole
bunch um but we've got my fast API right
up here and so now we can go ahead and
use this image for um actually building
out a container and we can run a whole
bunch of of Docker commands like Docker
run and then specify the IM image that
you want to use and then pass in all the
flags but I don't like doing that I
don't like working with Docker run
instead I want to use Docker compose and
if you have never worked with Docker
compose Docker compose does the same
thing as running Docker commands on the
CLI we just provide all the instructions
on a file so that we don't have to
remember all of these long commands with
all of these extra Flags we literally
write out the flags in a file and then
we can just say Docker compose up and
it's going to bring up all of our
containers so we're going to take a look
at Docker compose in the next video and
see how we can get that set up all right
so we're going to learn about how we can
use Docker compose to automatically spin
up our containers with the desired
configuration and it's you're going to
see that it's so much easier to use
Docker compos than just running Docker
run whenever you need to because we can
spin up multiple containers all with one
command and we can also tear them down
all with one command and to use Docker
compose we have to provide the set of
instructions uh using a file called
docker-compose
yml and so this is a yaml file and if
you don't know too much about yaml um
it's just a I guess it's technically
like a markup language I guess um but
the most important thing to understand
is that spacing matters so this is kind
of like python where you need to make
sure that the tabs and the spaces are
just right and everything lines up or
then it's going to start to throw
errors and the first thing that we need
to do is specify what version of Docker
compost we want to use so we say version
and I'm going to say just version three
it's not the latest it's just kind of
most common one
if you actually go to the docker
documentation for compos file you'll see
the different versions that you can
specify and you can actually take a look
at the documentation and see what
feature was introduced in what version
so you can figure out what version you
need to perform all of your operations
we're not doing anything special so uh
version three is just fine for
us then within Docker composed we have a
concept of services and so a service
really at the heart of it is nothing
more than just a container so if you
want docker osed to spin you up a
container you have to define a service
if you want Docker compos to spin up
four containers we're going to have four
different Services pretty simple so we
have to give each service or each
container a name so we're going to have
one container for our fast API and I'm
just going to call this container uh API
or this service
API and the first thing that we need to
do is we have to specify either the
image that we use so I could technically
say like image and then we can point to
like the python image or I can specify
build
where we can essentially do the same
thing that we did before in the previous
video uh where we ran Docker build and
then provided the location of the docker
file but we can just specify that uh
here within Docker compost so that
Docker compost will automatically build
the image for us if it doesn't exist so
we'll say Docker uh build and then uh we
specify the the context or the path to
the docker file which is the current
directory based off of where the docker
composes so they're in the same
directory so I just say current
directory and then we have to specify um
a port that we want to open up because
this is an API so the outside world
needs to be able to to reach our
container but by default all containers
can't talk to the or Sorry by default
the outside world can't actually talk to
your container so we have to open up or
poke holes on our local machine uh to
open up some ports so we say ports and
this expects an a an array uh of ports
and so there's two different ways to do
an array uh with a yaml or with a docka
compost file can do you know just an
array like this where we just provide a
list of things or we can also do it like
this where we do a dash and then provide
you know something and then a dash for
the next entry in the list so I'm going
to use this syntax because I kind of
like it
better uh but to open a port there's a a
specific format that we're going to use
so what we say is there's going to be
two numbers there's going to be the uh
port on Local
Host and then we do that and then we do
the port on
container all right so what's
essentially happening is we're telling
Docker um if we receive traffic on our
local host on this port this port
specified here we're going to forward it
to this specific port on the
container so the second number is a
little bit easier to set up because it's
going to be whatever Port our
application's running on so if we take a
look at our Docker file we can see that
our container is going to be listening
on Port 8000 so we want to set this
second number to be Port 8000
and keep in mind you could choose to use
any other value so if you decided to use
port 80 here then you would just change
it to Port 80 here but I'm going to
leave it as 8,000 just for Simplicity
sake then the second number that we're
going to use is going to be the port on
the local machine or on the Local Host
which in this case is my Windows machine
but if it's on like a production server
it's going to be whatever um machine or
or IP of that specific server is and so
here we could specify any port so if I
you can literally pick any port that's
open so if I said Port 4,000 what that
means is that you know if I go to
my um my Postman this would be the
equivalent of doing Local Host calling
4,000 right which is that first number
and so anytime we send traffic to that
specific port on a local machine it's
going to Route it to Port 8,000 uh in
our container which is what port our
applications listening on um but if I
change this to Port 8,000 as well then
our request would be Local Host Port
8,000 so I always like to have the two
numbers match up because it's just
simpler but sometimes that's not an
option so uh just pick a open port on
your Local Host machine it doesn't
really matter what it is just make sure
that you remember what it is and I'm
going to leave it like that and I'll
delete this line right
here and for now I think this is good
enough and what we're going to do is
we're going to try to run this and see
what happens so I'll say
docker-compose up and then if I do a
d-el we can see some other flags that we
may need and the only flag that I really
need right now is the Dash D so this is
going to run the containers in in the
background so that we're not
automatically connected to it so I'll do
dash dash oh sorry just-
D all right and so you'll see uh if you
take a look what's happening is we're
rebuilding our image so because we
specified the build right here it's
going to build our
image and then it's going to start our
containers so you can see that it's
creating fast API _
api1 uh and so the the naming syntax
comes from the project directory so it's
called Fast API right so that's why the
first word then we do underscore then
the name of the service so I called this
service API so then it's API and then it
has the number one because there's one
instance but if I told it to spin up
four then I'd have 1 2 3 and four so
we've got our container if I do a Docker
PS we should be able to see
nope oh we can see it's down and that's
because if I do a Dr ps-
a and we can see that this one right
here looks like it stopped 43 seconds
ago and so it crashed for whatever
reason and that's okay um what we can do
is I think we can actually see the logs
after it goes down so if I do Docker
logs fast API
1 we can actually take a look at the
logs at what caused it to go down down
and we can see a couple things um but we
can see that we get the penic error uh
for um our settings object which is all
of our environment variables so
obviously a container is like its own
separate machine so it needs all of the
environment variables passed to it or
then our application's going to
crash so how do we pass an environment
variable in uh Docker pretty simple we
just pass a environment
field and then here it's going to
provide you need to provide an array of
an environment variable so I do Dash and
then here we just specify our
environment variable so I'm actually
going to copy and paste this section
right
here and so these are all of our
environment variables um keep in mind uh
if you don't want to actually write out
all of your environment variables we can
actually use Docker to point to aemv
file or a environment file on your local
machine and if you want to do that it's
pretty simple here we would just specify
the um
n Vore
file and then you can actually provide
multiple files but in this case you just
provide the path to the file so it's
going to be in the current directory and
it's going to be EnV so you can do
either one or a combination of both um
I'm just going to use this format so
that we can see all of the environment
variables and I'm going to just comment
this out for now just for documentation
purposes and now what we're going to do
is we're going to do a Docker compose
down just to to tear everything
down and I'm going to bring it back up
and
detached and notice this time it didn't
build the image so why exactly didn't it
build the image well Docker composer is
very simple all it does is it goes to
Docker image basically just runs a
Docker image LS and it looks for the
image that it would have created and
there there's a very specific format
that he uses which is going to be the
name of the the folder or the directory
and then underscore and then the service
so since it the image was already
created previously it doesn't recreate
it however if you obviously make changes
to your um to your Docker file and you
want to make changes then you would have
to do Docker um up and if you look for
the flags there should be a dash
dash uh let's see build this is going to
force it to build a new image so keep in
mind anytime the the image has to change
um and you've already but the image
already exists then you have to to pass
in that flag to force Docker compost to
let it know that hey I made some changes
I need you to rebuild it for me because
Docker compost can't detect
that all right so now if we do a Docker
PS we can see that it's running now and
it didn't crash and
um we should be able to access it on
Port 88000 so if I actually go here and
just do local host 8,000 with the get
request looks like it's working
okay so now that we can actually access
our API which is running in a container
the next thing that I want to do is I
want to set up our postgress database
and you might be thinking well we
already have one installed on our local
machine why are we setting up another
one well couple things first of all if
we're already dockerizing our
environment it makes sense to set up our
postest database especially from a
development perspective within a Docker
container because it's so much easier to
set up a database in a container than it
is to install it on our local machine
because we just spin up a pre-built IM
and that's it so even if you don't
actually want to dockerize your
application from a development
perspective I strongly recommend you
make use of Docker containers so that
you can spin up a quick database just
for testing purposes but since we
already have a Docker based application
now we're going to just use a post
database that's running in a Docker
container instead of on our local
machine because if we take a look at the
environment variables that we pass to
our container we provide a value of
Local Host and so Local Host means that
the container is going to or or the API
running in the container is going to try
to access a database running locally on
that container which it's not so let's
create a brand new service which once
again is nothing more than another
container for running our postgress
database and so I'm going to go down
here and we're going to create another
service called
postgress and here we're going to
provide a image flag right because here
we did build cuz we're building our
Custom Image here we're going to use the
pre-built default postgress image so if
we we go back to dockerhub and search
for postgress you'll see this is the
official postgress
image and this is going to contain all
of the documentation for setting up
postgress um but the main thing is
there's a couple of environment
variables that we have to pass so first
of all the password that's going to be
used for our database uh we can give an
optional postgress user but it's going
to default to postgress if we don't
provide it and then we also want to give
it a postgress database name so we'll
call it fast API like we've been using
in our development environment and that
should be all that we have to do for the
most
part so here I'll say
environment and we'll do uh
postore
password equals and then um we can give
this anything we want so password 1 2
three and then we want postgress DB so
this is going to be fast
API all right the next thing that we
want to do is um when it comes to data
within a container that data doesn't
persist as soon as the container go goes
down right so when you delete the
container you lose all of your data
right and so from a database perspective
we don't actually want to lose our data
we want that to persist even if we kill
off the container so how do we actually
save that data we have to create
something that's called a volume and um
that's what allows us to save data from
a container onto our local machine so
that if we kill the container we can
always spin up a new container and just
point it to those
files and there's a couple of different
volumes that we can use or types of
volumes in Docker there's Anonymous
volumes named volumes and I think bind
mounts is the other one we're going to
make use of named volumes uh and so to
create a named volume here under the
postgress database section or service
we're going to say
volumes and then we say Dash and then
provide a a name for the volume so you
call it whatever you want I'm going to
call this postgress
ddb right and then we have to specify
the path in the container that we want
to actually save so what directory do we
want to persist on our local machine
and the path that the postgress
container or image actually stores all
of its data we can actually take a look
at the documentation to figure this out
so if you search for volume and so right
here this gives us an example and this
is going to tell us what we need to know
so we want to save SLV bar/ lib post SQL
slata so that's where it's going to save
all that data so we'll copy that and
once again this is the path in the
container that postgress is going to
write to so that's where all of our
tables all of the entries are going to
get stored so we want to copy that
essentially and save it on our local
machine and the last thing that we want
to do is anytime you use named volumes
we have to create another volume section
globally and then just pass the
name uh that we created so whatever is
here you just put it down here and the
reason we have to do this is because
named volumes are designed so that
technically multiple containers can
access them so you define it down here
first technically and then multiple
containers can reference them by just
calling that all right so we've got this
set up and actually I realized I left my
containers running so what I'm going to
do is I'm going to comment this out for
a second save this and I'm going to do a
Docker
compose down so that's going to delete
everything then we'll uncomment our
postr
service then the next thing that we want
to do is we have to figure out you know
what is the host name or what's the IP
address of our postgress database and um
you know there's a couple different ways
to do that um but what's awesome about
Docker is when you use Docker compos it
creates a custom Network and a Docker
network uh uses DNS so we can actually
say to reach the postgress database
instead of like looking for the IP
address of that container we can use DNS
and I can just say if I try to reach the
name
postgress right it's automatically going
to resolve to our postgress service so
whatever our service is called we can
just reference that and this is going to
allow this container to know that when
you want to talk to the postc database
this name here is going to resolve to
the IP address of this
container and so networking with Docker
within Docker is so simple because
that's all we have to do and then the
rest of the things the default Port the
password the database name the database
username those should all be okay and we
can just leave as
default and now I can then start this
up and it looks like image something's
wrong with the image I forgot to give
the image so what's the image
name it's just post gu so that's just
whatever this name is that's all you
need all right and so now we can see
that it started up
both uh let's just quickly test our API
so we didn't break anything so that
works and then let's go to create user
make sure it's point to Port 8,000 in
this case and if we create
user right you can see that we have
successfully created the user so it
looks like we can now access the um the
database from our fast API
container now what I'm going to do now
is delete everything again so docka
compos down deletes everything and you
can see I'm essentially able to destroy
both of my containers with a single
command and that's kind of the power
behind docka compose and ideally we want
our postgress container to start up
first because our API is dependent on
the container so uh for our API we can
pass in another opt
and I can say depends
on and here we can specify a list of
services in this case just postgress and
so this is going to tell Docker I want
you to start the postgress container
before the API container
Starts Now technically it's not going to
wait for postgress to actually fully
initialize it'll just start the
container so you still want to put in
checks in your code to make sure that um
you know if you can't access the
database because it's not initialized
you want to keep
retrying and so once once again we can
bring this back up with a single
command and if you take a look at the
order you can see that we started up the
database first so now you'll always
start up your database first and then
start up fast API and then you'll stop
fast API first before stopping the
database because we set up the
dependon when it comes to working with
doer containers we do experience a few
extra challenges uh especially from a
development perspective and I'm going to
show you how those challenges actually
work uh or what those challenges
actually are and uh if I actually go
back to my my test request wherever that
is where I'm just going to reach the
default URL so if I hit send you can see
it says hello world pushing out to auntu
right and that's because in my main.py
file it just says hello world pushing
out to auntu now if I save
this or change this and then save this
and then I send a
request right we still get the same
response I don't get the the new text
that I added so why is that well there's
a couple things that are happening but
the the easiest way to figure this out
is to actually poke around in your
container and figure out what's
happening so I'm going to do Docker
PS and I want to see what the file
system of fast API container actually
looks like so to do that we do Docker
exac dasit so that's going to um enter
into interactive mode we specify the
container name and then we type in the
word bash so what we're doing is we're
entering interactive mode and we're
going to over ride the default command
of the container so the default command
is specified right here from the docker
file so we don't want to run that we
just want to run bash which is going to
allow us to access the file
system that's the image name so the name
of the container is fast api1 so let me
add the
one so now you can see that we're we get
a Linux prompt so we're in the Linux
file
system and if I go into app
and then go into um if I do cat which is
going to print out the contents of a
file we'll take a look at the main.py
file and you can see that it just says
hello world pushing out to a buntu so
when I made these
changes uh and added these extra
characters it didn't get pushed out to
our container and if you're trying to
figure out why that is it's pretty
obvious right because what we did was we
created a image which copied all of our
code here at that point in time and then
when we did a Docker compose up
it created the image and then that was
it right nothing else changes right
afterwards we went in and change the
code but the image was already created
so whatever is in the image nothing
changes after that point so any changes
we make will not get copied over to our
container so what do we do in this case
how do we get around this
limitation well what we can do is we can
make use of a special volume called bind
Mount and a bind Mount is a special
volume because it allows us to sync a
folder on our local machine which with a
folder in our container so this app
folder which has all of our application
code what we want to do is we want to
sync this folder in our container with
this folder here so that if any changes
get made here it's going to get copied
over to our container and so under
volumes in our API we're going to define
a volume here and I'll say uh
volumes right just like we did with
postgress very similar except we're
going to use a different syntax CU this
is a bind Mount so a bind mount we have
to first provide the path uh of the
folder that we want to sync on our local
machine so this is our current directory
so we can just do
slash for current directory but if you
wanted to sync just one individual
folder maybe like the app folder then
you can do slapp up to you but I'm going
to sync everything and then we have to
specify the path in our Docker container
which is going to be this folder right
here and that's going to automatically
sync the the two folders and if you
wanted to add some extra security you
can do ro this means read only so what
this does is this makes it so your
container can't change uh any of these
files because only we should be changing
the files not the container itself so
this just adds a little bit of extra
security if you wanted to but it's still
technically
optional and let me exit out of here and
now we'll do a docker-compose
down and we'll do a Docker compose up
again and now
let's just change this together all
together so um bind Mount works so if we
see
that that means everything's working so
let's save it and if I send we can see
that I get the old one now right uh so
whatever I changed here doesn't get
copied
over so it looks like we didn't fix the
issue so let's actually take a look and
see what's happening and so how do we do
that we'll do the docker exec command
again to go into the file system let's
go into the app
folder and let's cat that main.py file
and this is interesting because it looks
like the bind Mount did work because we
can see that the code got updated and if
I make another change again uh this time
let's just add
um sort of
and if I cat this again we can see that
it's in there so the bind Mount is
working and it's syncing the code with
our local directory and our container
but there's one issue and if I go back
to my Docker file you can see that I
have my command right here but this
doesn't have the-- reload flag which is
what we need to restart the application
so anytime we make changes to our code
we need to automatically reload uh when
it detects any changes so that we can
actually see the new application and we
didn't provide that in the docker file
and so so that's why it's not working so
this is actually a pretty simple fix we
just add the D- reload flag so let's
tear everything
down and we have a couple options so I
can go here and say-- reload and that's
would work just fine but instead of
doing that what I would rather do is I
like this default one because this is
the one you technically use in
production because you don't want you
don't want Dash uh Dash reload and
production um but in our Docker compose
file we can actually overwrite it so we
can provide another um flag called
command and here we can provide a
command to overwrite that uh from the
docker file so I'll say uh
Docker sorry UV
corn app.
main app-- host
d-port 8,000 -- reload
all right and let's bring this back
up let's just see what it is currently
right now so we got whatever it is now
and let's make a quick
change and I'll just delete all of this
and change this back to hello
world and let's test this out and we can
see that it does successfully update and
so now our bind Mount works and we
automatically restart a code so our
development environment more close
closely matches up with what was uh what
we had before before we move to Docker
okay so if you haven't already done so
go ahead and create an account on
dockerhub it's a free account but I want
to show you guys how we can set up a
repository on dockerhub so that we can
actually store our images here and so
Docker Hub is kind of like the uh the
docker equivalent of GitHub where it's
kind of acting as a repository um but
instead of a repository for our code
it's a repository for our images so we
can upload our images anytime we make a
new image we can actually upload it so
that we can track changes to our images
over time so make an account and then we
want to go into
repositories and we want to select
create
repository and then give this uh a name
it doesn't really matter what you want
to call it I'm just going to call it
fast API and then we're going to do
public because you only get one private
repository and so now we have a private
repos well it's a public repository and
so this is the UR to the repository
which is going to be your username this
is my username and then this is the name
that I gave it so fast
API uh and so now what I want to do is I
have an
image right if I do Docker image
LS we can see that I have my fast API
API uh this is going to be the image
that I want and so how do I actually
upload this image to um uh to Docker Hub
well there's a command called Docker
push right so if I do a Docker push
d-el you just pass in Docker push and
then the name of the image so let's try
doing that we'll do Docker
push and then the name of the image
which remember yours is going to be a
little bit different because it's going
to be based off of your uh your
folder let's try
this and it says requested access to
Resource is denied so the first thing
that we have to do is we actually have
to do a uh docker login so we have to
log into our account so you do Docker
login here it's going to ask for your
credentials so we'll do sloppy networks
in this case for me and then it's going
to be whatever it is for you
guys and then now let's try to push it
again and once again we get a access to
Resource is denied so what exactly is
happening here well when we want to push
up a image right there's a very specific
naming convention that we have to use
right we have to name it uh exactly like
like this sloppy networks fast API and
we even see an example right here so you
do Docker push uh the name of your email
or your account name then the name of
the specific repository and then you can
give it an optional tag name so what we
got to do is we got to rename our image
so how do we do that I think it's Docker
image I think uh well let's do d-el just
to see if we can figure it
out uh we
want tag so this essentially copies an
image and renames it for
you so let's do Docker image tag-
dhel and here we just provide the The
Source image and then the target image
so what is my image called again it's
going to be this one right here and we
just do Docker image tag then the image
that we want to rename and then we give
it the new name which has to be your
account slash then the repository and
then you have an optional you know tag
uh the default is just going to be
latest so I'm just going to leave it
without a
tag so I do that and if I do a Docker
image
LS we should see the new one right
here and so now I can do a Docker
push it looks like I didn't copy that so
let's try this one more time
and now it looks like it's pushing
something so let's give this a minute or
two and then once it's done let's take a
look to see if we have successfully
pushed it to our
repository all right so it looks like it
successfully pushed so now if I go back
to my Docker Hub page and do a refresh
we can see that last push was a few
seconds ago so now we've successfully
pushed it to our Docker Hub and so you
know if we set up an actual production
Docker environment we could just pull
the image from this specific URL or this
specific uh repository now before we
wrap up the docker section of this
course uh there's one last thing that I
want to show you guys and that is that
if you take a look at what we have right
now we have a identical clone of our
previous development environment but
we're now developing within a Docker
container so our Docker container
environment is a exact clone of our
previous development environment the
issue is is that you know when we move
to production assuming that you're using
uh Docker and production which is kind
of the main idea behind is that uh your
development environment and your
production environment are almost
exactly the same because you're using
the same exact Docker images and
containers but if we try to use this
Docker compost file in production
there's going to be a whole bunch of
issues first of all um obviously these
environment variables would need to
change and we can't hardcode them uh we
wouldn't want the Das Das reload flag
and you certainly don't want a bind
Mount because the code shouldn't be
changing and then uh the ports that we
use could also potentially be different
so even though Docker or so even though
the docker environments uh from our
production and development environment
should be roughly similar there are
going to be some differences and so we
need to account for that uh and so what
I like to do is I actually like to
create two different Docker compost
files one for development and one for
production so that's what we're going to
do but first of all let's do a Docker
compos Dash
down that we can just tear everything
down for a second
and once that's down I'm going to copy
this and paste
it and we're going to rename these files
so this one is going to be called docka
compose ddev so this is going to
represent our development environment
and this one is going to represent our
prod environment
all right so we've got our Dev and our
pad environment the dev doesn't need to
change because we had already set that
up for development environment the
production one is going to change a
little bit so first of all the command
right we don't want the Das Das reload
so we can specify the exact command we
want which is the one without the D-
reload uh and that should be all that we
need however keep in mind this is the
default command from the docker file
right so we could technically just
remove this or or just comment it out
and so I'm just going to comment it out
in this case but if you wanted a
specific custom command for um for
production you can just provide that
here the whole idea is that this file is
going to represent all the changes for
our production
environment uh then maybe we want
instead of listening on Port 8,000 we
want Port 80 so that we can use our web
browser uh most of the things can stay
the same the environment variables
definitely need to change
uh and so uh with a production
environment uh we first of all we're not
going to hardcode the values we usually
want to grab these uh these values from
the environment variable set on the host
machine so instead of actually
hardcoding these in instead we can
reference environment variable so to
reference an environment variable what
we do is we do
dollar curly braces and then the name of
the environment variable so um it's
going to look on the you know Linux
machine that it's running on for a
environment variable called dat base
host name so I figured we would just
have the match just to show you what
that would look like and then we're
going to do the same for all of these
and I'm just going to copy and paste
this once
again so it's going to look like this so
it's just grabbing the data um the
environment variable from the local
machine keep in mind they don't
technically need to match um but it just
makes it easier for troubleshooting
purposes and then uh for the Post Crush
database right we would want the
password to be the same environment
variable
and then we would on the database name
so that we're not hardcoding that one as
well and we don't want the bind Mount so
we will remove
that and that's about it so that's all
you have to do so this just gives us
both a development environment and a
production environment uh we'll save all
of that now starting up Docker uh compos
is going to be a little bit different
now because uh we don't use the default
Docker Das composed yaml file name so if
I do a Docker compose if I can find the
up Docker Das compose up all right
you're going to see that it throws an
error right because it says it can't
find a Docker composed. yaml or yaml
with an A or compose yaml or compose
yaml with an A so it looks for only
these file names so when we have a
custom file name we have to do
docker-compose and then we pass in the
Das F flag for the file name and so we
provide the path to the file so it's
just in the current directory so I can
just do docker Das uh compose ddev yaml
and then we just do an up and then-
d and then we can start it back
up and if you want to bring up a
production environment then you would do
das dashr that's the only difference so
you don't really have to do anything
else other than running the different
specific uh Docker compose
file and uh the last thing that I want
to change is actually um in your
production environment you don't
actually ever want to build the image in
a production environment instead what's
recommended is that when you're done
developing you push the brand new image
to Docker Hub right and then in the
production environment we just pull this
image from Docker Hub so how do we pull
this image from Docker Hub easy we
change we remove this build option
remember this is going to be in the prod
file and we set this to be a
image and here we just set this to the
name of the repository so we just do you
know your username SL fast API Das oops
not Dash app just fast API so whatever
is essentially right here and then if
you want a specific image with a
specific tag then you would add the tag
as
well and so that's all we have to do
feel free to stop your containers now if
you
want and even when you do a a down you
want to make sure you do
a-f so it knows which file to actually
look for
and I misspelled
that and that's going to conclude the
docker section of this course and so I
think this is going to give you a solid
foundation on how to dockerize your fast
API now currently whenever we make
changes to our code whether it's
implementing a new feature or modifying
the behavior of a previous feature or
even fixing some bugs that we happen to
catch right we have no idea
uh if the changes we make break other
functionality in our code and so
normally anytime we make any changes we
then have to you know go into Postman
and essentially manually test out every
single scenario to ensure that things
are working and this isn't a very
scalable solution uh it's going to
result in a lot of wasted hours for
every single time you have make any
changes to your code you're going to
have to test everything because you
don't know what uh what code you've
broken by making those
changes and so this is where uh you know
an automated testing Library comes into
play where we can define a whole bunch
of tests to test a majority of the
functionality of our code and so that
way anytime we make changes to our code
we can run our test to see if we've
broken anything and keep in mind you
know obviously we can't test for
everything but we can at least test for
enough things that we can catch some of
the more obvious
bugs and so this section of the course
is going to be dedicated to getting
started with testing and really
understanding the concepts of testing
and seeing how we can get started with a
library like py
test um but I do want to provide one
little disclaimer before moving forward
I wasn't originally going to post uh a
section on testing for this course and
the reason for that is that I don't have
much experience with testing it's not
something I do a lot of or and or at all
really uh and so I want to make sure
that you guys understand where I'm
coming from when it comes to testing and
that is that um you know since I am not
super proficient at testing you know I
don't really feel too qualified to
actually teach it uh and so what I want
you guys to do to take it what I want
you guys to take out of this section of
the course is just to how to get started
with testing how do you set things up
and what's the main ideas behind a test
I may not necessarily be teaching the
best most efficient way to test I may
not be test uh using the most efficient
way of testing and there may be
scenarios where I may not even be
following best practices but I want to
show you guys how we can at least get
some integration tests set up and then
at that point what you guys can do is
you can just forget everything else that
I've taught you when it comes to testing
once you at least have the groundwork
then you guys can you know do your own
research figure out how you ultimately
want to implement testing with any of
your projects and then go ahead and just
run with that so with that in mind uh in
the next video we'll get started with
get getting P test installed and writing
our first test for testing the library
that we're going to be using is py test
so if you do a quick Google search you
can just search for py test and the
first result is going to take you to the
documentation page for the pest library
and so I recommend you guys take a quick
look at this just to see how it gets set
up uh and if you want to do a little bit
of reading before we actually get
started writing our first test
definitely go ahead and do that um but
once we've got that opened up what we
can do is we can install pie test so we
can just do pip install pie test just
like we would with any other package
then once that's done uh we have access
to the P test command so just go ahead
and run P test and see what happens so
prints out a few things you notice that
we can see that the test session starts
so this is when we start testing I
prints out some information about the
platform that we're running on and
that's okay we can ignore all of that
and you'll notice that it says collected
zero items we'll talk about this in a
bit but the more important thing to look
at is it says no test ran in 04 seconds
and this is expected you know we haven't
created any tests so obviously it's not
going to be able to run any tests but to
run our testing all we have to do is
just run this command and then you'll
see that P test will um go through all
of your tests run it to verify uh you
know that they all pass and if there's
any errors or anything like that it's
going to report that so it really is as
simple as that but let's go go ahead and
create our test and I want to store our
all of our tests inside a directory
called tests so inside the root
directory of your project just create a
new folder we'll call it
tests and technically you can put this
folder anywhere if you wanted to put
this test directory within your app
directory you absolutely could it's a
matter of personal preference I'm just
going to keep it outside of the app
directory for now and within here I'm
going to actually create a
file and this is going to store our
first test I'm just going to call this
my test.py for now all right and we
obviously need to test a part of our
code whether that's uh a route or a path
operation or a function or a class we
need to test something and right now our
code is a little Advanced and when I say
Advanced I don't mean Advanced because
anything we've done is super Advanced so
far it's Advanced from the perspective
of testing where we're coming in from a
background of no knowledge of testing so
we want to start out with testing the
simplest functions so I'm going to
actually create a brand new module and
essentially create the simplest uh
module or function that I can possibly
think of so I'm going to create a new
file call it whatever you want I'm going
to call this calculations because it's
essentially going to be a bunch of
functions that we use to perform certain
calculations and I'm going to define the
world's simplest function which is
called add and I think you can guess
what this function is going to do it's
going to take two
numbers which is going to be of type
int and it's is just going to return the
sum of them so we just say return num
one plus num
2 right and the reason once again is
because this is going to be very simple
uh when it comes to testing so you guys
can at least have an understanding of
how to actually perform these
tests so we've got this module defined
inside our app directory and then in our
test folder we've got our my
test.py and we're going to Define our
first test so what is a test well it's
really just a function it's either
function or a method within a class uh
we're going to start off with just doing
functions because it's just a lot easier
and we're going to call this function
testore add why did I give it that name
uh well it's testing the ad function so
I think that makes sense and technically
the name the naming does matter but
we'll come back to that in a bit now how
does this function actually work from a
testing perspective well it's very
simple you know P test will run through
all of our tests and when it runs
through this specific ific test what
it's going to do is if it runs through
it and there's no errors get thrown that
means the test has passed it's succeeded
that means our code is good if our
function throws an error of any kind
it's going to consider our function uh
or our test as failing then the test has
failed so how exactly does that work
it's a simp it's simple we use something
called
assert and if you aren't familiar with
what the assert command does in Python
uh anytime you assert a true value
nothing's going to happen the code just
runs however if you assert a false value
that means it's going to throw an error
so it's it's no different than raising
an error or throwing an error in Python
it's just a simple way of doing that for
testing purposes if it if we return
something that's true uh then the assert
won't do anything if we return something
that's false then it will raise a python
error and I'm going to show you exactly
how that works so if I just say assert
true and before this I'm just going to
do a
print testing ad
function and then down here I'm going to
just call the testore
add function right here and I'm going to
just run this uh as a normal python
module so we're not going to even treat
it as an actual test or anything like
that we're not even going to use py test
so I'm just going to call
Python and keep in mind the commands
python on on Mac but it's p-3 on Windows
and then we're going to go into the test
directory and we're going to call my my
test.py and I'm going to show you what
happens all right we can see it says
testing add function which is from this
print statement and then you can see the
assert did nothing so it just ran and
and everything's fine and that's
expected because like I said assert only
does something when we return a false
value so if I say false now and I run
this code take a look at what happens
hey look python throws an error so Asser
is simple as that true means nothing's
going to happen false means it's going
to throw an error and we don't have to
just say true or false we can actually
pass it a condition so if I say 1 equals
equals 1 that's going to return true
right so technically an assert of true
won't do anything however if I say 1
equals equals 2 that's going to be a
false statement and if I run that we can
see that it asserts and it throws an
error so that's how we make use of
assert within our testing functions so
I'm going to remove
this and we're actually going to test
out our code now so to test out our ad
function the first thing that we have to
do is we actually have to import it into
this file so we're going to import it so
we'll say from and we have to go into
the app directory and the calculations
model module so we'll say app.
calculations import
add and now what we're going to do is
we're just going to call the ad function
like we normally do and we need to give
it some test data so I want you to think
of two numbers uh that you want to use
for testing add them up and what is the
result should it be so I'm going to say
I'm going to do five and three and I
know that this function if it works
properly should return a value of eight
cuz 5 + 3 equal 8 and so I can just take
the sum store that in a variable called
sum and what we can do is since I know
sum should ultimately be equal equal to
8 I can assert that and that should
there should be no e there so I can say
sum equals equals 8 so that means if if
our code runs fine sum should ultimately
equal 8 and if we assert 8 equals 8 that
means it's going to return true and
nothing should happen uh or Pi test
should consider it as uh passing however
if I mess up my code and for some reason
the ad function returns a value of 20
then when we do assert 20 equals 8 well
that's going to be false and it's going
to throw an error and it's going to
consider that as a failing test because
an error means a fail test so that is
the main idea behind a simple automated
test within P test right you just
provide you run the code with some test
data and you know what the result should
be because you created this test data
and you just make sure that the result
of the code matches with your expected
result so let's actually run our test
now so I'm going to do p test and let's
see what happens right and you see the
same exact thing we saw before once
again it says it collected zero items no
tests
ran and so why exactly is this happening
well if we go to our
documentation and you scroll down to
this feature section you go to the
autodiscovery
section and so this autodiscovery
section is going to explain how pest
finds all of the tests in your code
because it does have a autodiscovery
functionality where it can actually go
through all of your code all of the
directories and packages and recursively
look through them and find the tests but
it looks for specific
keywords and you can see in these
directories it looks for any files that
start with
test so you have to do testore and then
some name or some namore
test.py and if we go to our code right
we name this my test this does not match
what it's going to look for and that's
why it doesn't actually find any test
from that so let's change this I'm going
to call this let me rename this and I'm
going to call this how about testore
calculations
all right and so now if I run
this you can see that it throws an error
but I realized that you know within my
test package I do need to have the usual
uh uncore init.py to actually make it a
package so I'm going to do the same
thing I'll doore uncore
init.py because of that it wasn't able
to actually import the file properly so
let's let's save that and let's try this
again so now if I run this you can see
that hey look we collected one item so I
think it's safe to say that this
collected one item probably means we
have one test so the number of tests
equals items and then we can see that
inside the test package we have a module
called test _ calculations. py and then
there's a little dot so the dot
reference um represents one individual
test and a Green Dot means means good a
red dot means it failed right green is
passed red is fail and so if you have
two tests then you would see two dots
and then if if the second test passed it
would be green if it failed it would be
red simple as that and so now we have
successfully ran our first test and just
to make our code a little bit
simpler right I could just instead of
having the sum variable I can just cut
this out just paste it into here just to
make it a little bit cleaner and then we
can remove all of this
and just to make sure I didn't break
anything let's run our test again and we
can see that once again it worked just
fine now when it comes to the auto
discovery of files uh a few things to
note you don't necessarily have to
follow this convention of testore
calculations if I actually rename this
and I call this you know mycore what
what did I call this my
test.py right now if I obviously run
this it's not going to find any tests
but I can pass in the specific path or
the specific module that I want to test
so if I do my
test.py then it is able to find the test
but I like to have um Pi test be able to
automatically find all my tests so that
I don't have to specify this so we'll
rename this and go back to
testore
calculations because it ultimately is a
module that's going to be testing my
calculations
module and another thing to note the
name of the test within the module also
matters if I call this um you know maybe
something like testing add take a look
at what
happens whoops I wanted to Auto find it
now and I forgot to save it now if I run
this looks like it still works but let
me change this
to just something
random right and so now we can see that
no tests Ran So the naming of the
function absolutely matters when it
comes to autodiscover tests and you want
to stick to the standard of testore
something and I think somewhere in this
documentation it's going to go over here
we go test from those files collect test
items so a test prefixed test function
or method outside of a class or a test
prefix test function or method inside a
test prefix test Clause so it's got to
start with test essentially it doesn't
necessarily have to be test underscore
that's why testing underscore add worked
just fine it does have to start with the
word test that's why if I said add test
I don't think this will work actually
shouldn't based off of their description
and it doesn't so uh keep in mind that
the naming does matter and I recommend
you stick to the Convention of naming
all of your testing modules test
underscore then the name of the module
that you want to test and then your
functions test uncore and then the name
of the function that you want to test or
the functionality that you want to test
now a couple of things to note I'm going
to run this test again and you'll see
that it doesn't really give us much
detail as to what's happening but we can
pass in other flags to get a little bit
more detail or to change the
functionality so if I do p test d-el
you'll see that there's a lot of options
but I think something that would
probably be helpful is like a-h V for
verbose and I think we should have that
in here so let's see if I can find that
here we go Dash V is increased verbosity
so uh we'll just do p test- v and let's
see what happens uh and so now instead
of just having a DOT it's actually going
to list out the specific test that's
running so I think that's a little bit
more helpful and I usually like to run
these tests with a little bit of extra
verbosity uh just so that I know what's
happening however maybe in an automated
environment you don't really care about
that and the other thing to note is that
we have this print statement here but
nowhere in the output do we actually see
anything get printed out I don't see
testing ad function anywhere in here and
the reason for that is that by default P
test will not actually print out any of
your print statements we have to pass in
an extra flag to do that so to see the
print statements you have to pass in - s
so now if I run this we can see that we
ran this specific test and it ran
testing ad function and so keep in mind
any time you want to print something you
got to pass in the dash s
flag okay guys so testing really is as
simple as that um but before we go on to
more complicated tests I want to just
make sure that we fully understand how
this works so we're going to create a
few more dummy functions that we can use
for testings and if I go back to my
calculations. py I've already written
this out so I'm just going to paste it
in here not to waste your time but
you'll see that they all essentially do
the same exact thing they just perform
some sort of mathematical operation so
I've got the subtract function which
just subtracts two numbers I've got the
multiply which adds two numbers and I've
got the Divide which just divides two
numbers so let's test this out now uh
the first thing that we got to do is
well let's import all of those so there
subtract multiply and
divide and let's define our function
for uh
subtracting all right and so just like
before um I'm just I'm going to do a
oneliner so I'm just going to say assert
and we'll say subtract two numbers what
numbers do I want to subtract how about
9 and four oops 9 comma 4 and we know
that 9 minus 4 should equal 5 so I can
do aert equals equals
five all right and if I run this
again right we can see that both tests
pass and just just to make sure that you
know our testing actually works let's
actually go into our code and let's
essentially create a bug so if I want to
add two numbers right we know that it's
going to be num one plus num two but
let's say you know one of our
colleagues went in and added one which
is ultimately going to cause our
function to break and so ideally if
everything works fine in our testing it
should be able to catch this because if
we add 5+ 3 it's going to do 5 + 3 and
then it's going to add that extra one
it's going to return 9 9al equal 8 is
going to assert to a false which is
going to throw an error so if we try
this out
now right we can see that it did in fact
fail and because we set this to be a
verbose we can see exactly what happened
so he ran the test ad and what happened
was it asserted add 5 comma 3al equal 8
so it's asserting 9al 8 and that's going
to throw an error and so that way we see
one failed one pass so the subtract
function still pass
because we didn't touch the code for
that so I'm going to go back and fix our
bug in this
case and we're going to just set up a
couple more test functions um for
multiply and
divide and I can just really just copy
these
actually and I'll just change this to
multiply
divide and we'll just select a couple of
numbers so let's say uh
and I realized looks like that's a typo
this should be multiply with an
L all right and we'll say uh four and
three so when we multiply 4 * 3 that
should equal
12 and for divide we'll change the
function that we're calling to be divide
and we'll do
20 5 so 20 divided 5 should equal four
and so now if I save everything we
should ideally see all four of our tests
pass let's try this out again and you
don't have to use the- V or the- S flag
if you're not printing anything or you
don't want to see it you don't need the-
s and maybe you don't want the verbosity
so you could technically remove those as
well and we can see that we get four
dots which means all four of our test
functions have
succeeded if you're like me the first
thing that you may have noticed is that
you know testing with one set of numbers
doesn't seem Ultra reliable right that
doesn't necessarily assure us that the
function that we wrote actually does
what it's supposed to do I would ideally
like to test with a couple of different
sets of numbers and the way to do that
is well you know I'm sure if you just
took a guess right you're probably
thinking well maybe we just copy this
function paste it well that should be
back here and then maybe just call this
test ad to maybe we don't need this
print state anymore and then you provide
the other sets of numbers so maybe like
four and two should equal six and then
you try this out and you run this and we
can see that that worked and technically
you can do that but P test provides us a
simpler way of doing this so I'm going
to delete this because we don't need
that I'm going to show you how we can do
this using something called
parametrize so I'm going to import P
test so I'll say from
actually I'll just say import py
test and we're going to add a special
decorator from the pest Library so we
say at py test.
mark.
parameterize and so here we can
essentially provide a list of numbers
that we want to use for testing and then
provide what is the expected result uh
and so you know our function takes two
inputs five and three and we also need
to provide what is the result so these
are all the values that we're providing
we have three values for this specific
function so we're going to tell this
specific decorator what are the three
things that we want to provide for each
test case so in quotations we'll do num
one num
two and then um the expected value now
what you call these doesn't matter it's
up to you right but these are going to
be treated like variables essentially so
you can call them what you whatever you
want you can call this x you can call
this why you could call this
result it doesn't really matter um but
I'm going to stick with num one num two
and
expected and more importantly take a
look at how this is set up right your
instinct is probably to do the end quote
here and then quote here quote here and
then quote here like that that's not
what we want that is not how it actually
works which I don't know why they
decided to do it like this but that's
just what they've chosen so instead you
remove these
and everything should just be one big
string so that's the first argument into
this
decorator the second thing is going to
be a list and it's going to be a list of
tupal and each tupal should represent
one specific test case so the first
Tuple we're going to provide our test
case values so we want what is the value
of num one so in the first test let's
say we want three for Num one what's the
second one that's going to be num two so
it's going to line up with what we've
put here here so we'll say 3
2 and then what is going to be the
expected value well 3 + 2 should equal 5
so we just say
five and so that's our first test if we
want to add a second test just do comma
add another tupal and let's just add
another set of number so let's say num
one is 7even num two is 1 we know that
should equal
eight and just one more
test and here I'll say 12
and four should give us
16 all right and so now what we can do
is we can pass these variable names into
our testore add
function so I'll say num one num two and
expected right so you want to make sure
these match up with what you've placed
here uh because if this was called X
then you want to make sure that this is
called
X but we'll change that
back and now in our codee we want to
replace all of our test values with
these variables so this is going to be
num one this is going to be num two and
this is going to be
expected and so now if I run this and
we'll just do A- V just to see more in
detail what's happening take a look at
what's happening now we can see that
test ad ran and it ran with 325 which is
the first test case it passed then it
ran the same exact test with these
values 718 that passed and then it ran
with these values and that ran and it
passed just fine and then finally all of
the other functions also passed as well
so this is one way of running the same
test over with multiple values without
having to just Define three four five
functions than just copying and pasting
it's a little bit cleaner doing it like
this so till now we've just tested some
simple functions and you'll see that
when it comes to testing anytime you
want to test a function it's actually
pretty easy however when you're working
with classes it gets a little bit
trickier and it usually involves having
to write a little bit more code so I've
created a simple dummy class in this
case called bank account and this
represents a person's bank account and
I've already written this out because I
didn't want to waste your time writing
this out so if you want to pause this
video and just copy down the code so you
can follow along go ahead and do that
but let me just quickly walk you through
what this specific class is
doing um but like I said this represents
a bank account so first of all we've got
the Constructor so when we create a bank
account we uh can create a bank account
with a spefic specific amount of money
which is going to be referenced by the
starting balance value and then it's
just going to set the balance property
of the bank account class to be whatever
you provide if you don't provide a
starting value it's going to default to
a value of zero then we've got three
different methods we've got deposit
which means we're going to deposit money
into our bank account so all we're doing
is we're going to pass in a value and
then we're just going to add it to our
total balance withdraw is the opposite
we're going to subtract a certain amount
from our balance and then uh collect
interest is uh simple we're just
collecting interest so here we just take
our balance and then multiply it by 1.1
which I guess would represent a 1%
interest rate uh and so those are the
three or four functions U methods if you
want to count the Constructor method as
well that our bank account class has so
I want to go ahead and test this out now
so we'll go to our test
calculations and first of all we want to
import our bank account
class so let's create a test for our
bank account
and the first thing I want to test is uh
let's create a brand new bank
account um where we set the default
value uh the initial amount to be 50 so
here I'll say um
test and I'm just going to call this
maybe test
Bank set initial amount I want this to
be as descriptive as
possible and so here what we're going to
do is first of all we're going to create
a brand new bank account instance
and since this test is going to test to
ensure that we have actually created a
brand new bank account with a certain
amount of money I'm going to provide a
value doesn't matter what value you
decide to use but I'm going to use 50
and we'll just store this in a variable
called bank
account all right and so to test if our
function actually worked or the
functionality of our Constructor method
actually worked what we're going to do
is we just say
assert and we want to check the bank
accountbalance
property equals equals 50 cuz we set the
default value to be 50 and if we just
quickly go back to our code you can see
that we set the starting balance um or
we set our balance property to be
whatever the starting balance is it just
happens to be a default of zero if we
don't provide one but we are providing
one and that's what we're testing so we
can test this let's run our code now and
let's see if this worked
we can see that it did in fact
work and just to introduce a bug maybe
we set starting balance to
be uh you know minus one right so we
broken our code now if we run this one
more time all right you can see it
failed because we subtracted one so
we're asserting 49 equals equals 50
which throws an error which means we
ultimately fail the
test let me remove that
bug all right the next thing that we
want to do is Let's test to make sure
that the
default starting balance works as well
so I'm going to create another function
and I'll call this uh how about test
bankor default
amount so in this case we're just going
to create a brand new bank
account and we're not going to pass in a
value so it should default to zero if
our code works and we'll store this in a
variable just like we did before and
then we'll assert
I can copy
this but now it should equal
zero okay and let's test this out
now right and it looks like it worked so
great and let's just quickly go ahead
and test our last two functions out
sorry we got three more actually so um
let's test the withdrawing functionality
so we'll do testore withdraw
and here we're going to initialize
another bank account instance because we
have to do that every time we want to
test it I'm going to give it a default
value of 50 it doesn't have to be 50
once again you can choose whatever
number you
want and we'll store that in a variable
called bank
account and we'll call the bank account
withdraw method and we're going to
withdraw you know let's say $20
so we start out with 50 we withdraw 20
we know that the result should be 30 so
if I just copy this assert statement
once
again I can just change this to 30 and
it should be no
problem run this once again all of our
tests have passed uh let's try the
deposit functionality now so I'll create
a test to test
that and I'm actually just going to copy
all of this code because it's pretty
much identical you'll see that testing
can become a little rep uh repetitive
we'll start out with an initial value of
50 doesn't really matter we'll change
the method to be
deposit maybe we want to deposit
$30 so 50 plus 30 should equal
80 we test this
out looks like everything's
working and the last thing that we want
to test is the collect interest method
so let's create a function for that
we'll do testore collector
interest and once again I'm going to
copy this
code and we'll just use it here we're
just going to change the method to
interest or collect
interest okay so we start out with the
value of 50 uh and so what should the
interest be well if I take a look at
what my method actually does it just
takes the number multiplies by 1.1 so
that should give us 55 right
1.1 * 50 should be 55 so I will
say this should be 55 and let's see what
happens so if I run this and we can see
that we did have one test failed and I'm
assuming it's going to be the last test
the one we just created and we can see
the uh the test collect uncore interest
failed and the reason for that is that
it looks like bank account. balance
returns a value of
55.1 which in Python is not the same
thing as 55 so this isn't necessarily an
issue with our code it's just the way
that um you know we're comparing numbers
in our test so this is an issue with our
test in this case because it's not
accounting for some of the the different
rounding and the way that calculations
occur within python so what we're going
to do is what we can just call the round
method right here and we can round it to
uh you know five or six decimal places
depending on how accurate you want it to
be so it should now round it to you know
this value however many decimals is five
or six and then convert it to an integer
so then we can compare these two because
this is an integer this is technically a
float so uh not exactly they're not
going to be equal in that case so now if
I run this we can see that it did
successfully pass so that's just
something to keep in mind that's why I
added that little extra t test case just
to make sure that especially when it
comes to those calculations you got to
make sure that you're comparing the
right two
numbers if you look through all of the
test cases for the bank account you'll
notice that there's some repetitive code
all right for every single test case
that we have for testing our bank
account you'll notice that we always
have to initialize a bank account
instance right and you can see that
right now look at that we are repeating
our code across all of our tests and
when you get to more complex classes
more complex test case scenarios right
you might have 50 tests for a single
class and we're in this case just
repeating the same exact code for each
one of them and so when it comes to
writing these tests you know Pi test
does provide us with some tools that we
can use to minimize the amount of
repetitive code and one of those is
called
fixtures and a fixture is a very simple
concept it's nothing more than a
function that gets run before each one
of your tests or at least the specific
test that you want so we can create a
function which does nothing more than
initialize a bike account and then
return it to our function that's about
to run so I'll show you how we can do
that right the first thing we have to do
is let's create our fixture and I'm
going to we can put it anywhere I'm just
going to put it here for now but
generally you want to put at the top of
the file actually I'll stick to the best
practice I'll say at py test.
fixture and then here we create a name
for our fixture so I'll say um this is
going to you know give us or initialize
us a bank account with a zero initial
value so I'll call this zore bank
account and so all we're going to do is
we're just going to return an instance
of bank account with an initial default
value of
zero and then we'll create one more
fixture and this one is going to return
a regular bank account with an initial
value and what value we want to give it
we get to decide so I'll just say return
bank account and in this case
50 all right and so now what we can do
is uh for all of these tests I don't
need to initialize them here because I
can have these guys reference the
fixture so to assign a fixture or have a
fixture get called for a function we
just pass it in as an argument so for
test bank account sent initial amount
we're going to reference the uh zore
bank
account fixture so what exactly happens
is when pest goes to run this test case
because it sees this as an argument into
the function it's going to oops that
should be a zero okay but what it's
going to do is it's going to call this
function before it actually runs the
test case so it calls this function and
then whatever we return here which is
the bank account gets passed into a
variable called zero bank account and so
now in instead of creating a bank
account instance I can remove this and I
can reference this variable which is
zore bank
account but let's test this out let's
see if that broke
anything if we run
this oh sorry guys let me undo this I
didn't mean to use this function this is
going to be for the the test bank
account default amount so we want to
remove this one
my apologies and we don't need that in
this
one and then this will be zore bank
account but now all test should
pass all right so everything passes but
if you're still a little confused as to
the you know what exactly is happening
behind the scenes or what is the order
of operations I'm going to add a few
print statements so I'm going to
say uh testing my bank
account and then I'm going to put in a
print statement in inside my fixture as
well which is um say creating
empty bank
account and so now if we run
this I want you to take a look at the
code and I realize I have to pass in the
- s flag to see the print
statements all right so here we go we're
going to test Bank set initial amount
sorry no test Bank default amount and so
you'll see that um when we start this
test first things first is we create an
empty bank account that's that print
statement for the fixture so before the
test even runs we call the fixture
because we've defined that here by
saying uh where is it that it's going to
be a argument into the default amount uh
test case then after the fixtures run
which is just a function we then run our
actual test case and then we get the
print testing my bank account right
after that so once again just to really
drive home this point a fixture is just
a function that runs before a specific
test case that's all but the great part
is we can use the same fixture for all
of our other
tests so let's go to the next test which
is setting an initial amount and in this
case we have this fixture right here
which is the bank account one and so I'm
going to say this is going to go to bank
account so this will call the bank
account fixture and then we can remove
this line
and we can just keep this here because
it's referencing this variable now and
this should work now so we run this once
again all test pass and I can just do
this for all of them so I can just call
the bank account
fixture and I can just remove that line
everything else can stay the same and
the same thing here as well
and finally for the last one we can do
that and so now you can see that we have
saved us ourselves a couple of lines of
code for each function and if I run this
you can see that all the tests
pass so at this point you're probably
thinking you know this do this didn't
really look like it saved us a lot of
code or a lot of you know coding out
however there's going to be certain
things that you want to do that you want
initialize before every single test of
your uh of your entire application so
maybe something like setting up a test
database right you'd want that to be set
up for each single test um having to
manually do that for each test case
would become very cumbersome and then
the lines of codes that you repeating
start to become a serious problem and
that's really one of the best use cases
for uh for using fixtures is something
like setting up a database or setting up
you know some sort of email service or
something that you're going to use uh
across a lot of your tests and then
having to initialize that manually for
each test is going to be uh is going to
require a lot of work and so that's
where fixtures really help save us some
time okay what I want to do is I want to
create one more test and this test is
going to be a little bit different I'm
going to call this uh test
about Bank transaction Maybe
and so this is going to test us both
depositing money and withdrawing money
in one test case so that we can have a
couple of different actions on a bank
account uh and so just like we've done
before uh when it comes to setting up a
fixture so that we can retrieve an
instance of our bank account class I'm
going to do the same thing but we're
going to use the zero bank account so it
starts out with no
money and then what we're going to do
here is we're going to reference the
zero and we're going to start off by
depositing money
and let's say I'll deposit
$200 and then we can also then withdraw
certain amount of
money so now we're testing both in one
specific test case and I'll say I'll
withdraw 100 and we know that we should
ultimately be left with $100 so we'll do
assert zero bank account
dot balance
equals equals
100 so let's test this
out and let's see how this
works and that works as well but what I
wanted to do is uh for this specific
test case I wanted to show you that we
can we can use fixtures and parameterize
so we can test multiple values like we
did for this specific test case so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to copy
this so that we don't have to type this
all from scratch and we're going to
create a couple of different test
scenarios for this specific
function and in this case we're going to
have a
deposited we're going to have a
with and we can have the expected amount
and keep in mind you're not limited to
having three variables you can put as
many as you want it just happens to work
out that I only need three in this
case and then we can provide some test
data uh so how about
the same one we have right now we're
going to deposit 100 200 sorry withdraw
100 and we expect 100 in the
end uh we can do the same thing how
about deposit 50 withdraw 10 and we
should end up with
40 and then we've got our high roller
which is sitting there with a whopping
$1,200 and he wi through about
200 and he's going to end up with 1,000
bucks at the end so now we can pass
deposited
withdrew and
expected and now we can use deposited
here withdrew here and then we know what
the expected is going to be so let's try
this
out all right and we can see all three
test cases run and in this case all
three test cases passed so I just wanted
to show you guys that you can use this
um with our fixture so it's okay if
you're using a fixture you can still use
the
parameterized uh decorator in this case
to test multiple scenarios if we go back
to our bank account class and you take a
look at the withdraw method you'll
notice that right now we're not
performing any check to make sure that
the user has enough money and that's not
really how A bank account works because
if you have 100 bucks and you withdraw
500 the bank's going to be like we can't
do that so it just makes sense in our
code to actually perform some sort of
check and so usually um you know
something simple is we'll say hey if
amount that you're trying to withdraw is
greater than your
balance well what are we going to do
well we're probably going to raise an
exception so I'll say
raise and we're just going to raise a
standard python exception and we'll just
say something hey in sufficient insu
insufficient funds in account
right however if we do have enough money
then we will actually perform that
operation so this is all good if we go
to our test
calculations um and we just add one more
scenario in this
case but this time we deposit let's say
only $10 and we try to
withdraw um I don't know 50 uh well what
is the expected scenario uh the expected
value and it doesn't really matter what
we put in because this is ultimately
going to uh you know
break uh break our code because we're
raising an exception so if I try to run
this right it's going to
fail because we're raising an exception
right and remember anytime you throw an
error that's going to automatically make
the test fail so what do we do well
first of all let's remove this test case
because for scenarios like this where
you expect to receive an error we need
to create a different test case so I'll
call this uh uh how about test
insufficient
funds and let's say we start out with uh
instead of using the zero bank account
where is the uh instead instead of using
this bank account we're going to use uh
the zero bank account and then we'll
just try to withdraw money so that's an
easy way of testing it so we'll say
zero unor bank account so we'll have no
money in our account
and we're going to withdraw some money
so we would do you know actually I'll
just do a regular bank account I don't
know why I want zero so we'll start out
with 50 bucks and we'll try to do a bank
account.
withdraw and we'll try to withdraw $200
so that should raise the exception but
how exactly in our test do we tell
python it's expected to receive an
exception because right now if we run
this once again we're going to get the
same exact error
right
failed so what do we do this is how you
tell python that you accept uh that you
expect an exception you do with and then
you call P test remember we imported P
test all the way at the top right here
so we'll do p
test do raises and then you provide the
exception that you expect so in this
case this is just a regular python
exception so you can just say that and
then you provide the command that you're
going to
run okay and so that way if this command
throws an error or raises an exception U
pest will be told to expect this so then
it would consider the test as passing so
now if I run
this we can see that the insufficient
funds test passed and if we go back to
our code and actually remove this
exception we'll comment out that entire
statement what do you think is going to
happen
here right now it's failed because
it did not raise an exception pest is
expecting an exception and we didn't
raise one so then it considers that a
error in our code because when we expect
an exception we should expect an
exception so I'll uncomment
this and now you know in a in real code
right you wouldn't just throw uh just a
generic python exception you're going to
usually create your own exception
classes so let's say we Define our own
exception and I'll call this
insufficient f fs and this is going to
extend the exception
class and we'll just say there's no
property so I'll just say pass and in
this case I'll say We'll raise an
insufficient fund insufficient
funds all right so if I make this
change uh what do you think is going to
happen you think it's going to break our
code well let's run this we can see that
it passed and that reason why it passed
is because insufficient funds is a child
class to the exception class so when we
say we accept uh we expect an exception
technically we are getting an exception
it's just we haven't specified we
specifically want a insufficient funds
exception and because this is uh
inheriting from this class python says
hey look everything looks good but if
you did want to be as specific as
possible which is generally recommended
what we can do is I can import that
exception so we'll say from app.
calculations we can import insufficient
funds
and now here we can say we we expect a
insufficient
funds and so now if I run
this we can see that it
passes and the benefit of this is that
if for some reason our code raised
another type of exception it would
consider this test as failing so if I go
back to my code and let's say that you
know for some reason something broke in
our code and all of a sudden instead of
raising an insufficient funds error we
get some other kind of exception and I
can just simulate this by doing raise uh
zero division error so if you ever try
to divide a number by zero this is the
um the exception that's
expected and so now if I run
this right we can see that
uh the test failed because we expected a
insufficient funds exception but we got
a zero division
error and so that considers the test as
failing because we've told it we've
expected something but we got something
else so it's generally best to
explicitly Define the exact exception
that you expect so that you can make
sure that you know that nothing else is
broken because technically any part of
your Cod can break and throw an error
and if it throws an error and we just
try to uh if we just tell you know our
test to expect any exception then it may
not be doing what we actually expect it
to
do but we'll change this back we don't
need that
anymore okay so I think we have a good
enough understanding on how to create a
test and I think it's time we actually
started testing our application when it
comes to fast API fast API automatically
provides us a test client so all we have
to do is we just say from fast api. test
client import test
client and then all we have to do is
then just pass in our fast API in
instance which is stored under the
variable app and then we can just
perform any requests to our application
by doing client um which is what we
named the test client and then just
doing a doget or a post or whatever and
then we can get the response and then we
can assert anything that we want just to
make sure that we get the responses that
we ultimately
expect and keep in mind when you make
use of this test client right if you
take a look at the documentation it says
that um you you use this the same way
you would any requests object so if you
ever Ed the uh request library from on
right this is the same exact
object so anything you could do with
requests you can do with the test client
so you can customize the request you can
you know change the HTTP method you can
add a body a payload you can add a
authorization header uh it's really just
doing what postman's doing for us but
we're going to do it through code
instead of manually opening up Postman
and then you know you know figuring out
which request we want to send we're just
going to do it out in Python so we can
do it all in an automated automated
fashion but if you haven't worked with
the request Library
definitely take a look at this just take
a look at how we generate requests it's
not too difficult right it's just
request.get or in our case we're going
to call it client but it doesn't really
matter and then you provide the URL that
you want to run this against uh and then
you know you can add in other properties
like an offhe header or anything like
that so it's just about customizing your
specific HTTP
request and so I'm going to create a new
file and I'm going to call this how
about uh testore users this F this
module represent test for you know
creating users and and uh getting user
profiles information and things like
that and just like it shows in the fast
API documentation let's just copy this
line right
here and then what we want to do is we
want to import from our app uh package
go to our main file we want to import
our our fast API instance so we want to
this app right here so that we can
actually test
it I'll say
from app.
Main
import
app all right so we have our app
instance and we'll just copy this line
right here which is just setting our
test client uh to a variable called
client and so now we can run whatever
test that we want and uh I think you
know just to keep things simple let's
start off with the simple root path that
we have right here just to test that
this works um because that way we don't
have to worry about authentication or or
passing any other data let's start off
with the simplest scenarios so this is
at the root URL so we will go to our
test
users and I'm just going to call this um
test rout
because it's not really a real function
or anything like
that and then here we'll say
client Dot and since we are testing a
specific path operation this is a get
method so we want to send a get so we'll
do client.
getet then the URL so we can just say
slash we don't have to do you know Local
Host because it's not technically a
running server we actually just pass the
actual app instance so we just say the
root
path and then you can pass and other
things like you know what payload and
things like that but we'll leave that
for now uh leave it empty and we'll
we'll store the response under a
variable called res and instead of doing
an assert or anything like that for now
I just want to print
out the
response all right and if I run
this okay so a little bit annoying thing
right now it's going to run all of our
tests and if you just want to test one
test or one module then I recommend you
just do uh the same thing except pass in
the path to just your
specific uh your specific module so that
we don't run all of our tests all over
again so we can just run one in this
case and if we take a look at this uh we
can see that it just prints out a
response object not very helpful but if
you want to see what's the actual
payload we can say Json
to see what the data looks like and so
then I can run this and we can see that
hey look we get message hello world and
if I wanted to
grab the message property I could say
doget and then message and it should
return hello
world let's try this out one more
time and we can see that it prints out
hello world so to test that this route
actually works what we can do is we can
just do an
assert and I could say assert and then
um literally just copy this exact
message and I can say hey the message
should return a value
of hello
world it's as simple as that right it's
no different than what we did before
with our you know our addition function
right we're just performing some action
you know running our Cod and then making
sure that the results are what we expect
them to
be right and so now if I run this
again right once again still passes
because it does return a value of hello
world for the message property and we
can assert multiple things right it's
not just one we can do a second test
case and I can say uh
res Dot and we can access a property
called status code it's even
recommending that so we can say get me
the status code and I could say well I
expect this to be a uh you know if we
don't change what the default status
code is it's going to default to a value
of 200 as per the fast API documentation
so this should be a 200 we shouldn't get
any other values so if I run
this once again everything works but if
I go into my code and create a little
bug let's say
um uh I just add you know an exclamation
point or
something then if I run
this we can see that it fails and that's
because we expected hello world but we
got hello world exclamation
let's change that
back and this time let's create a
different bug let's actually change what
is the status code uh and so I can't
exactly remember how to do that so let's
go to our post
router and we just set the status code
right here like this so if I copy this
and go back to
here and actually was it in The
Decorator yeah it's in The Decorator you
put that in
there and we have to import stat
St and so now if I try this
out and run this once again it's going
to fail and that's because we're
asserting and the response was a 2011
but we expected a 200 as per hour test
which over here says it should be 200
and it throws an error so you can see we
could test a lot of different things you
can choose to test each and every
property that you're interested in to
make sure that the response is exact
exactly what you expect it to
be um but at this point I think we
understand how to send requests so let
me just first of all undo those changes
that I just made just to make sure I
don't break anything else in my
app and we no longer need to import that
so remove that we'll save everything and
let's just run our test one more time
just to make sure that everything's good
and it looks like everything passes
before moving any further I want to show
you a couple of other flags that we can
pass
uh to the P test command so that we can
kind of tweak the behavior of our
testing and the first thing I want to do
is if you take a look at the output you
could see that we get a whole bunch of
warnings and uh you know depending on
how many packages and libraries that you
have installed you could potentially see
a lot more warnings uh and I actually
hate looking at these things so what I
normally like to do is I usually like to
pass in the dash dash I think it's a
disable warnings I think and so now if I
run this you can see that there's no
more warnings and we just see the
testing information so I think that
looks a lot cleaner uh and then the
other thing that I want to show you guys
is until now all of our you know testing
when we've broken a specific function or
class um we've only had one test fail
and I want to show you what happens when
you have multiple test fail so we go all
the way to the top uh in the test
calculations folder and then maybe I
just change you know uh the subtract
function so I'll change this to be six
so we know that it's going to error out
and then also at the bottom I'm going
going to test uh change this test right
here so that it returns 56 instead of 55
and so if we run
this and I'm going to do uh- V so we can
see verbos um but you don't have to do
that but if you take a look at what
happens you can see that you know it
runs the first three tests and then the
fourth test uh fails and then it just
continues running through all of the
other tests and then it fails on the
next one and then it finishes running
all of the other tests so the default
behavior is when a test fails we're
going to continue running all of the
other tests and this may not be the
behavior you want so maybe you've
changed your code and you just want to
see if we've broken anything uh and so
you want your code to ideally you know
run through the test and the first time
it fails you want it to stop so that you
can you know then fix that issue and
then run through the rest of the tests
uh afterwards or or you know you can
manually run it again because you know
right now we only have like 167 tests so
it doesn't take that long but when you
uh start to write a lot more tests and
your code starts to grow these tests can
take you know minutes sometimes more
than that depending on you know are you
using an external API are you using a
database these all add a significant
amount of time to your test and so if
you just want to see if you've broken
anything you may want P test to stop on
the first failure so if you ever want P
test to do that all you have to do is
you have to pass in the dash X flag so
this will tell p test to stop uh after
the first test fails so if I run this
you can see that we get pass pass pass
and then the first test failed and then
we stop and we don't do anything else uh
and so those are just the two flags that
I wanted to go over I don't think we'll
really cover any other specific Flags um
I just wanted to go over these two
because they just happen to be two of
the ones that I do like to use
occasionally but let's make sure we go
ahead and change all of our code back so
I think we changed this one this should
be back to
five and this should be changed back to
55 and just to make sure let's just run
our code once more just to make sure we
didn't break anything in we can see all
16 test
pass so now that we know how to simulate
a request to our API let's create a test
for testing the uh user create
functionality so what we're doing is
we're going to create a user and we're
going to test this specific route right
here where we create a user so let's try
this out uh we're going to do the same
thing I'll call this def testore create
_ user
and here I can say res equals client
like we did before but this time it's
going to be a post
request and the URL that's going to be
SL
users all right and then since we're now
sending a request uh you know to create
a user we have to send data in the body
so to send data in the body you say Json
equals and then you pass in a python
dictionary so this is going to get sent
as the body and if you go back to our
specific
route uh which is right here uh you can
see that we expect the users create
schema so if we take a look at the
schemas uh you can see that somewhere in
here where is user
create here we go we expect an email and
a password so let's send an email and a
password and so for email we'll say this
is going to be
L1 123@gmail.com
and the
password is going to be password 1 2
3 and just to see that it worked let's
do a print and I'll say res.
Json and then the test requirements you
know how do we verify that it works well
let's start off with something very
simple so we'll say
assert and I'll say res. status code we
know that when we create a user we
expect a 2011 and we can just verify
that by taking a look at the path
operation um but I think this should be
good and then now if I run
this and I'm going to run just this file
so I'll say test test
user and let's see what
happens so we see both of them passed
and how do we verif ify that
well I mean it we should see this user
in our database right so if I go to my
um PG admin go to my database and we'll
go to our
schemas
tables and go to users and we'll do a
view edit
all right we can see the hello one 123
so it was successfully created um I'm
just going to quickly delete this again
well actually let me show you what
happens if we don't uh I'm actually
going to do something unique here I'm
going to say well actually let's just do
an assert and I'll say res
do
Json
doget and we want to get one field just
to verify that it's correct so um what's
the data going to look like when it
comes back well we should see a print
but I didn't that's because I forgot to
do the dash s flag but going back to the
route we're going to send the response
as a user route so we expect it to match
this
specific um this
specific model right here so it should
have an ID an email and a created
ad so let's add that in there I expect
the
email to equal equal the email that I
gave
it and you can really do as many you
know asserts as you want want you can
verify each single property has been set
uh you can verify that an ID has been
set I'm just going to keep it simple
we'll just say just the email um we'll
just run that check and so we'll run it
again and I'm going to do the- s flag as
well all right and we see that it
failed and we can see that it failed
because there's a duplicate key violates
unique constraint of email and that's
because this user was already created so
I can't recreate him so let me delete
this and I don't think I yeah if I
select the number and then go to oh no
it doesn't look like I
can there we go now I once I select that
number I can delete this
user and then we can save that to
database and so now if I run this again
we should see it
work and we can see that both tests
pass and we can see that both of our
statements were checked and validated
and they both looked good but instead of
doing it like this we can even take it
one step further um instead what we can
do is I can actually import this user
out schema into my test so I can say uh
from app. schemas import
user out and then I can remove this
print
statement and what I can do is here I
can actually use the
schemas actually sorry um I'm actually
going to change this import I'm going to
just import all schemas so say from App
import
schemas and now I can actually create a
new pantic model and I'll say SCH
do user
out so we're going to create a new
schema save this as a variable I'll call
this um new
user and we can pass in the data that we
get back from the response so I can say
res.
Json and remember we have to actually
unpack the dictionary so it's in the
right format to create a new user out
model and now this is going to perform a
certain level of validation so it's
going to confirm hey do we have an ID do
we have an email do we have a what was
the other thing that we needed uh and do
we have a created at so it's going to
make sure it's got these three things
it's not going to check to make sure
that it's the right email it's not going
to check to see if it's the right ID but
it's going to check to make sure that at
least it has these three properties so
it automatically does some of the
validation for us and it'll throw a an
error if one of those are missing and if
it throws an error then obviously P test
will consider this test a failure so by
doing this we've kind of uh we've kind
of uh saved us a little time and now I
can actually change this instead of
doing this I could say newor user. email
equals this value so now if I run this
hopefully this
works and it looks like it failed and
let's quickly see what happened
here oh once again I forgot
to delete the user beforehand so we'll
delete him and then try this test one
more
time and they passed so I think this is
what we're going to do moving forward
we're going to make use of our uh pantic
models to do some of the validation for
us automatically so that we don't have
like you know 60 or SE well probably not
60 but we won't have 5 10 different
assert statements which you can
absolutely do and you probably do want
to but this will remove some of them
because it's at least checking to see if
some of them are there so before moving
any further you know we need to address
something important and that is that
right now we are are using our
development database uh for our tests
and that's not good I don't want to use
my development database I want to create
my own separate database to perform
testing on so that I don't get in the
way of development or staging or any of
our production databases I want to
create a completely separate database
for testing right now when we you know
import our client right we're going to
be using whatever the database is that
we've defined in the rest of our app
which is going to be our fast API datab
base within PG admin and we could see
that right here and so that's why I'm
having to go in and you know make sure
that it's created and we've already got
some other data which could potentially
break our tests uh and so I want to make
sure that we have a completely separate
database for testing so that it does not
get in the way of anything else so how
exactly do we do that well one of the
great Parts about uh the way we've set
up our database is if we actually go to
our database. py file right you could
see that we've actually set up a DAT um
a dependency so when we set up our
dependency you can see we created this
function called get DB and this get DB
actually Returns the session local so um
this is what allows us to actually you
know make queries using SQL Alchemy and
that comes from this right here from the
session maker where we passed in all of
our uh database connection details and
if we go into any one of our routes it
doesn't really matter which one you can
see that we passing the dependency into
the route and the great part about
having dependencies is that it's very
easy to override a dependency uh in any
environment especially a testing
environment we can say hey instead of
passing in you know get DB we can say
you know something like uh get I don't
know undor testore DB which is going to
be a function that returns a test
instance of our database instead of our
development instance of our database so
I'm going to show you guys how we can
set that up and how easy that
is uh so we'll go back to our test
users and we're essentially just going
to copy all of this right here so I want
you to copy this all the way up to the
URL and we'll have to set up some
imports and we'll come back to that in a
second so let's just create some
space all right so we've got all of this
and we need to import a few things uh so
we'll start off by uh we'll have to
import settings so we'll say
from App
import actually we'll say from app.
config import I think it's settings yep
all right so we've got that cleared uh
we then have to import create
engine uh and so we'll go up here and
I'll say from SQL
Alchemy import create _
engine and then we need our session
maker as well and I think if I hover
over this can I nope it doesn't look
like it'll Auto Import that for me so
I'll say from
sqlalchemy.orm
import session maker
all right looks like we got most of the
issues we still need declarative base
and we'll import
that I'll say from SQL
Alchemy do ext. declarative
import declarative base and if you guys
don't know where I'm getting this I'm
literally just copying this straight
from this file so everything that's here
I'm just you can just copy it as
well and if we go down I think we have
everything right we no longer have any
errors so we've got all of our
Imports and so this is the function that
returns our session local so this is
what allows us to query the database
this is our session object right and
this is how it's set up uh exactly in
the database. py file so what I'm going
to do is I'm going to create another
function but this time I'm going to call
it override
underscore get uncore DB and this is
going to return this session local
instance but I'm going to rename this
just so I don't get a confused and I'll
call this uh testing session local and
then I'll reference
this all right and so that means right
now in our current application we're
referencing the one that we created in
our database. py file but the one in our
test we're going to actually make use of
this new one right here if we call this
override get
DB so how exactly do we override the
database or any dependency really um
well fast API has a section on here and
I think if I search for
dependency testing dependencies with
overrides right to actually set up the
override you just do app. dependency
override and then you provide what you
want to override it with and there's
actually a better example if I go to
testing
database this will actually show you how
to do that so we've got the
overb where we've created a different
session
object and to override it we just do
app. dependency overrides we pass in uh
well we specify the dependency we want
to override which is anything with get
DB and then we want to override it with
override undor getdb so essentially all
that's really doing is uh in the
functions any of our routes right you
can see we've got this depends get DB so
when we run that Command right here this
override all it's going to do is it's
going to swap this out with the function
that we have right here under test users
called override get DB which is just
going to give a different session object
and this session object uh can point to
another postest database that's all
we're doing it's really that simple
that's why we set up that uh that
dependency when we first started
configuring our database so that we can
easily test this during testing because
we can just use the override
functionality that's used within a fast
API so I'm going to copy
this and right here I'm going to paste
it down here and I realized I misspelled
override but we do have to import get DB
now so let's import
that so I'll say from app. database
import getor DB and so it's going to
swap the dependencies
out and since we're still referencing
the app object we're going to pass it
into test client and so now uh anytime
we use this client it's going to use the
new database uh now currently our
database is using the environment
variables which once again is going to
point to our development database so
there's a couple things we can do since
this is testing we 100% could just um
hardcode um our URL because I mean it's
our testing database who cares if our
password and our information is already
out there so we could technically uh do
an FST string actually we don't even
need an F string I could just say
postgress Q whoops this should be a
string postgress Q
col SL SL the then we have the username
right now for my for my database it's
just
postgress and then we have the password
which is password 1 2 3 remember this
would technically be for your testing
database so it's not technically a
problem if you put this in there and
hardcode it however uh you'll see that
we could um just use the environment
variables and make a small tweak but I'm
just going to quickly write this out for
you guys if you wanted to see
it and then the host name is going to be
Local Host Port it's going to be 5432
and then our database name so we could
call this you know my my development
database is called Fast API could call
my testing database maybe fast API
uncore test so whatever my project name
is and then underscore test you can call
it whatever you
want and so I can just hardcode that and
then comment this
out something like that or I could use
this same thing but just do a underscore
test here and so that way I don't have
to hardcode anything it's going to
actually pull it from the environment
variables so whichever method works for
you ultimately that's all that matters
now I technically already have a fast
API test
database so I'm going to actually delete
this for now so we'll say delete
drop all right so I'm now in however
your post Christ instance setup but
since we're going to be using a database
called Fast API unor test we actually
have to create one so I'll say create
database and I'll say fast API uncore
test Okay so we've got our test database
created and we've set up the override
let's now actually test this out so
we're going
to do one last thing and I I realize um
since we have a brand new
database there's no tables right if I go
down to
schemas tables right there's nothing
there so we actually have to build out
our our tables before we actually do
anything so uh easiest way to do that is
just copy uh where's my main file here
we go this Command right here so this
will tell SQL Alchemy to build all the
tables based off of the models we could
use almic as well so I'll show you guys
how we can kind of get a lmic uh set up
in our testing database so that it
actually performs the migrations before
test but for now we're going to keep
things simple and we're going to use
this and so I'll just paste it right
there and we can remove this models I
don't know why that's there and you can
see that we get uh a warning right here
so we don't have anything based so we
actually have to import that from our
database file so I'll say from app.
database import
base and I realize we actually don't
need this line right here so we'll
remove
that all right so now our test database
is completely set up
and when we when we actually run our
first test it's going to run this right
here which should create all of our
tables for
us so let's take a look at our test
create user um everything should be good
we shouldn't have to touch anything and
um our URL should point to fast API unor
test so let's try this out and I'm just
going to refresh this and uh yep we
shouldn't have any tables good perfect
and let's run this now so let's run just
the test users
all right and both of them passed so how
can we verify both of them passed uh
well let's go to our tables I'm going to
refresh this we can now see we've got
all three tables right and that's
because we ran this specif well not that
command this Command right here and if I
do a users and then uh where is it VI
edit a all data all
rows right we can see that our user was
successfully created so we have now
gotten our test database set up so that
we no longer interfere with our
development database and keep in mind
right it do your test database doesn't
even have to run on your local machine
you can run it anywhere you can run it
in a Docker container you can run it on
a remote machine you pass in the details
of your test database uh and then your
testing environment will handle the rest
so now that we've got our test database
and we've successfully ran our tests um
if we run our test one more time take a
look at what happens we get an error
right and we get an error because we saw
this before in our development database
we already have a user so we get this
duplicate key violates unique constraint
because this user already exists so when
we run this again we try to create a new
user with the same exact email and this
obviously causes things to break uh and
so how do we get around this limitation
right I want to be able to run my test
as many times as possible and I wanted
to kind of start out with the Clean
Slate well we can make use of fixtures
so let's take a look uh at our fixture
and if you already forgot what a fixture
was it's just a function that runs
before your test runs so I'm going to
create a fixture and I'm going to have
to do we already import uh pest we did
not import P test so let me import that
in here we say import P
test and I'm going to say I'm going to
create my
fixture call this whatever you want um
I'm going to call this client so this is
actually going to return uh this is
actually going to to return our client
right this is our client object right
here which is the test client which is
what we use to actually generate the
request uh so I'm going to call this def
client and what this is going to do is
I'm going to remove this line right here
and just copy
this and I'm going to say return this
and we can just remove this line at that
point so this is going to return our
test client instance and so now to get
this to actually work I'm going to pass
in our client
and so now this client
object references the client that we get
from this fixture and we'll do the same
thing here so what exactly has this
solved um right now it hasn't really
done anything for us right our code is
going to work exactly the same uh you
know if I save things and run it
again right same exact issue uh and
obviously I can go in and I can delete
this and then run this
right it's going to work just fine but
it is nice because we now have this
function that runs before each one of
these tests that gives us our testing
client and what's even better is I can
actually change this a little bit
because I can change this to be a
yield right when you change it to yield
what it does is it gives us a little bit
more flexibility because now we can you
know run our code before we
return
our test client and after the yield we
can then run our
code actually this should be run our
code before we run
our test and then this is going to run
our code after our test finishes so now
we can put in Logic for you know what
should we run before our code runs or
before our test runs we then yield which
is the same thing as return it's going
to return our test client and then we
can run some code after the test
finishes so what we can do is before our
code runs I
can copy this line right here so before
our code
runs I can create my tables and then
after my code runs I can drop my tables
if you want to drop a table you just run
base. metadata. drop all instead of
create all and it's going to drop these
tables and so now every single time my
test run I'm essentially going to be
starting out with the Clean Slate it's
going to drop all of our tables all the
data in each table it's going to return
the test client we're going to run the
test and then sorry it's I mess that up
so when we when we finish a test we're
going to drop all of our tables delete
our data then the next time the test
runs what it's going to happen is we're
going to create all the tables again
because there's no tables we're then
going to run the test and then just like
we did before we're going to then drop
all of our tables again so what I'm
going to do is first of all I'm going to
manually drop
these and I'm going to have to drop
votes first or then it's going to throw
some foreign key errors and then we'll
drop
posts and then
users okay so now everything should work
uh and I'm actually going to test this
out
so once again just to reiterate we're
going to create our tables cuz we don't
have any we're going to then run our
test right yield just returns our test
client to our create user and then we
can you know perform all this logic
after that's done we'll then drop the
tables again so we start from scratch
the next time around so let's try this
out all right everything's worked and um
if I actually go back to here and hit
refresh tables you can see there's no
tables because we dropped the tables
after we're done and if I run this
again it works we can run this as many
times as we want we don't have to worry
about duplicate users because we're
clearing out our database and there's
one more thing that you can do as well
uh if you wanted to we could actually
take this drop
all and move it up
here so what's the what's the benefit of
doing like this or why would you want to
do it like this well the nice part about
this is right it's going to clear out
anything we had previously it's going to
create our tables and then it's going to
run our
test and then the next test that we run
we're once again going to clear out our
table uh yeah we're going to clear it
out and then we're going to build our
new tables again so this way if you if
your test fails you can you know pass in
the dash you know X flag to stop after
it fails and what's going to happen is
it's going to keep all your tables and
all the data so you can see what was the
current state of your database when the
test failed so that you can you know
ideally have a little bit of better idea
of what's Happening troubleshoot a
little bit more because you have access
to your to your tables whereas if it's
if this is down here right it's just
going to delete the tables after you're
done you can't even see it so it's a a
personal preference but I like to keep
the tables after it's done so that you
know if I do want to stop it and just
kind of poke around and take a look then
I can and if you guys don't want to use
SQL
Alchemy you can do the same thing with
olymic right I can I can import you know
almic doc
config actually it would I think the
technically the import is from almic Doc
config import config sorry not that nope
no it's a from MC import command so what
we could theoretically do is uh in here
instead of using these we could say
something like uh I think it's command.
upgrade so you can
upgrade and then you can go up upgrade
to I think head right so this will build
out all the tables for you and then
after you're done you could then go in
and say command. downgrade to base or
something right you'd have to make sure
you set up a Olympic with all of the
right environment variables and things
like that but that's all you would have
to do if you didn't want to use SQL
alchemy's built-in functionality so I'm
going to just delete that just to keep
things
simple uh we're going to let SQL Alchemy
build the tables for us moving forward
just because it's a little bit quicker
um than having to you know build all of
your revisions and things like that so
one of the cool things uh with fixtures
is that we can actually configure a
fixture to be dependent on another
fixture so we can essentially pass one
fixture into argument of another fixture
and the reason why I want to do this is
I want to have one fixture that returns
my database object so if I want to ever
manipulate data directly and I want
another fixture that returns my client
so this this one is returning our client
so I want that but I also want another
one that returns just our database
object so what I'm going to do is I'm
actually going to create a new
fixture I'll say pest. fixture and we
can call this whatever you want you can
call it you know like DB or session I'm
just going to call it
session and I'm actually going to move
the logic of deleting and creating our
tables up to here because this is kind
of handling all the logic for the
database and you see all of this uh
override functionality what I'm actually
going to do is I'm going to just copy
this section right
here and paste it into here all right so
this session fixture is going to yield
the database object so the database
object that we used to query things and
what I can do now is I can pass in
session this session fixture into my
client fixture and so by doing it like
this what's going to happen is any time
I go to one of my tests and I pass in
the client fixture as a essentially as a
dependency it's going to call this one
and the client fixture will actually
call the session fixture before it runs
so it's intelligent to understand that a
requirement for the client fixture is
the session fixture so we're going to
run all this code it's going to return
the DB object which is going to be
passed into client as the session and
then here we can perform all the logic
that we normally
would and I'm going to once again copy
this override DB right
here and we can remove
this and we can remove that NOP actually
sorry I didn't mean to remove
that just space these out a little bit
so it's part of the override get DB
function and here instead of yielding DB
since there's no DB we're going to yield
session which is the DB so we'll say
session and
then session.
close and I'm going to copy this line
right
here do the override right here and then
we return a brand new test
client okay and the benefit of this is
that uh not only do we get access to the
client if we wanted to we can also get
access to the database as well so I
could say session and then I can go in
here and I can make queries like
session. query you know models. poost
blah right so now I have access to the
database object as well and so I can
make queries and I have access to the
client but if I call just the client
remember the session
database is a input argument into the
client fixture so the session will
always run first and then client would
run because we're calling it right here
and then we just move the override get
DB function into here as well as the
override right here and then as usual we
return the test client so let's make
sure we didn't break anything Let's test
out our code and something's happening
with my terminal so let me open a new
one so let's try this again I'm just
going to do p test test slash and then
testore users nope not test calculations
users all right and two passed so
perfect looks like we didn't break
anything and we've got a much nicer way
of setting up our code we can actually
remove this override that's not within a
fixture we no longer need that and we no
longer need the create all right here
outside of any of the fixtures cuz we're
doing it all within the fixtures
now and once again I just want to make
sure I didn't break anything so let's
test that out and we can see two have
passed Perfect all right so right now
our test users file is a little bit
cluttered with all of this database
information and I would like to move all
all of our database specific code to
another file so under our test folder
I'm going to create a new file and we
can just call this database.
py and I'm going to essentially move all
of my database code to that file and
that includes the fixtures as well so
these two fixtures all of this actually
everything we don't need any of this uh
in our test users file and we can just
paste it into
here now this is going to break things
because um obviously it has no idea what
SCH okay well actually before we do that
we we do need to have schemas in here so
let me find where schemas is and we'll
just cut that
out but the other issue is is that we no
longer have access to the client fixture
so we have to import that so I'll do
from uh current directory database
import uh what is it client I think it's
client yep so now we have client
and remember we don't need to import
actually we may need to import session
let's just double check to see if this
causes any
issues so let me save
everything and let's test this out let's
see if this
works looks like we got two
errors yep and if you take a look at the
errors it says the session fixture is
not found so we actually have to import
the session
fixture uh from this file even though we
don't actually call session in here
because client is dependent on session
because client is ultimately calling
session we need to make sure that
session is also imported so we have to
do session here as
well and so now I think this should fix
our
issue so now if we run this yep both
tests have successfully passed and if
you actually take a look at our test
file you can see our test file is a lot
cleaner it's really just got our two
tests and a couple of imports and before
we move on any further there's one thing
I want to point out and I ran into this
issue when I was you know run doing a
dry run through my code uh if you
actually take a look at your routers um
and we'll go to since we're taking a
look at test create user this is going
to be the SL users so we go to users and
then create user right you can see that
the prefix is/ users so the route you
want to go to is slash users and then
you could see that we have to append
whatever is here so here it's appending
slash now the way that P test works is
that um or actually the way that
anything works is that if if you
actually send a request to SL users it's
a little bit different than SL user
slash and I'm actually going to show you
what happens when we do that so I'm
going to um first of all open up UV coin
set uh so I've start I've started out my
API and if we go to create user
here I'm going to users and not users
slash right I'm not doing slash I'm
doing SL user I'm just doing users which
is uh wait where did it
go is it
here where did I put my the things I
just typed
let's yeah here so what we're doing is
we're sending a request to this one not
the one above it because the other one
above it has a slash at the end we don't
have that trailing slash so if I create
a test user
without that trailing slash hit
send take a look at what happens in the
logs it says that when we get a request
to SL users we're going to send a 307
redirect to SL users SL because
technically the routes on SL users slash
and fast API is intelligent enough to
actually send the redirect to here
however this creates an issue with our
testing because if I just do slash
what's going to happen is when I do this
res. status code check it's going to
check for 307 and not the final 207 the
the final 2011 and I can show that to
you guys so let me go down here we'll
run our test real
quick and you'll see that it fails and
it fails
because well there's a couple of issues
um it fails it's it says it fails
because um our validation for a schema
failed but I'm going to skip that and
comment that out and I'll comment this
line out I just want to take take a look
at the status
code because obviously if there's a
redirect there's no information in there
right and you can see that this fails
because the response code is 307 so
that's why you want to make sure you add
that trailing slasher then you'll run
into some
issues so we've got our create user test
pretty much done uh you can feel free to
customize it however you want if you
want to add a few extra search
statements feel free to do that but
we're going to move on to login so let's
actually handle setting up the login so
I'm going to do def testore
loginor
user all right and this test is going to
be dependent on the client fixture
because we need to be able to send a
request so I'm going to pass in client
and I'm actually going to copy this line
right here we'll change it of course but
all right and so we're going to this is
going to go to slash
login and there's no trailing slash on
this one just because if you actually
look at our specific route uh for login
I think it's under o py um you can see
there's no prefix here it's just SL
login so we don't need the trailing
slash on this one you just have to
figure out how you set Yours up and make
sure it matches
accordingly we do SL login um but in
this case we don't want to send this
data in the body instead remember if you
go to postman and you go to login user
we don't send it in the uh well we do
send it in the body but instead of using
the
normal um normal Json format we have to
send it as form data remember uh and so
to change this to be form
data you just change Json to be
data and we've got the same credentials
so this should work H let's just quickly
just do
a um
assert and what does a login return a
login returns
a it should just be a 200 so we'll do a
assert res. status code equals equals
200 all right and let's test this out
now and it looks like we got an error so
what happened here let's take a look it
looks like we got a 422 as our status
code why would we get a
422 and if we take a look at our logs we
don't really get much information
here so what I'm going to do is we're
just going to
print uh res. Json so we can see what's
going
on right why did we get a 422 is there
any other details that's going to
provide us so I'll do a-s so it prints
it
out and we can see in the print
statement it says oh look at this
there's some sort of validation issue
detail lock body username message field
required type value error missing so
remember the um the field for the email
when you log in is not actually called
email it's called username so we have to
fix that so it's going to be
username all right now let's test this
out once
more all right we get another failure so
let's see this time we get a 403 okay
interesting uh so what's happening why
do we get a 403 let's see detail say say
invalid credentials interesting so if I
go back to my login
route right you could see that we get
a um a 403 if uh the user doesn't exist
which means we couldn't find a user with
that specific email or if the password
um that was provided doesn't match
what's in the database so this is one of
the issues it's either the user doesn't
exist or the email doesn't exist or the
password is incorrect so let's go into
PG admin and if you left
your um your database config so that you
don't drop it at the end instead you
drop it before a test case starts you
should be able to see all of your test
data so I'm going to refresh
this and if I go to users view edit data
all
rows right there's no users well that's
interesting right because if I go to my
code during our test create user we
should have created a brand new user so
why can't we log in as this
user well that's easy to explain so if I
actually go to
my um my database. py we have these
fixtures and the fixtures have a
specific scope which means when do they
run and right now they're using the
default function scope what that means
is they're going to run for every
they're going to run before every single
function that's dependent on
them so that means when we run test
users right we can see that test root
client right since we're passing client
into test root we're going to run our
fixtures before we run this
function then before the next test we're
going to run our fixture again and then
before this test we're going to run our
fixture again as
well so why does that actually cause the
user to get deleted pretty simple um
because we run this test right the test
create user the user in the database
then we start to run the test login user
and so since we're dependent on the
client fixture we go to the database. py
file we can see that the client calls
session session what does session do
well it drops the database or it drops
all the tables at least and then it
creates a all of the new tables so we
get a brand new database every single
test that we
run that's why the user isn't
there and if you want to learn more
about Scopes I recommend you go here and
then I think
if I go to API reference I
think and then
fixtures not no let's go to
examples and go to fixtures right here
and then here I can search for scope
here we can see the different Scopes so
the default right now is that our scope
is functions which means that the
fixture is destroyed at the end of each
test and it's run for every single
function we then have a fixture that's
sets to a scope of class which means
that it'll run once per class and it'll
run all the tests in the class then we
have a fixture module so when a fixture
is set to a module that means for all of
the tests in a specific module right
like in this case all of the tests here
we're going to run the fixture just once
at the beginning and then we're not
going to run it again for that module so
all of the tests will have access to
just that first uh instance run
essentially uh and then we also have it
for package where it's going to run once
per package and then we also have
session where it's going to run
once at the start of the testing session
and it's going to get
destroyed and you can see how we can set
the scope right here you just do scope
scope equals and then whichever one you
want so if we go back to here and we see
this this
fixture right we could say um since the
default is function it's the equivalent
of doing scope equals
function and the same thing goes for
the the session the database one as well
so these are going to run and get
destroyed every single function so at
the end of the function we're going to
delete this test client and then we're
going to create a brand new one for the
next one which causes our database to
get wiped and destroyed so if we want
our login user to be able to access what
was created here we could theoretically
change the scope to be module
instead and I could change this for
both and so now what happens is um at
the start of this module when we start
running the test here we're going to run
the fixture right because the test route
is called calling it so we'll run the
fixture at the
beginning and we're going to just do it
once right so then we'll you know we'll
call this one which doesn't really do
anything uh we'll then create the user
but since we don't ever run the fixture
again we never end up running this
session either so we don't end up
dropping our database or our tables so
we'll actually keep that same fixture
and then we'll run through all of our
tests and only at the end will we
destroy that fixture so we have
essentially access to all of the the to
our database the for the entire module
in this
case and so now if I actually run
this right you can see all of our test
pass because the
fixture will last the entirety of the
module I could even use package or
session both of them would have worked
but this creates a little bit of an
issue because this means that this test
is dependent on this test completing so
if this test fails then obviously this
test is going to fail and it actually
creates issues because if I move this to
the
top right and I accidentally move my
login user to before test create user
then this is going to break our tests
once again because we need to create the
user before we log in the
user and so in general what we've done
is bad practice you don't want to make
tests be dependent on other tests each
and every single test needs to operate
and run independently they should not be
reliant on other tests if they are it is
not a valid test and you're doing it
wrong you want to make sure that all
tests can run independently of one
another so what we've done so far with
this little hack of changing the scope
to be module is not a good solution so
in the next video we'll take a look at
what we can do to kind of overcome this
limitation this issue so that we can
make our login test case independent of
our create user test
case okay guys I wanted to make sure
that you know we really did understand
what uh Scopes are when it comes to
fixtures cuz I feel like I didn't do
that good of a job explaining it so
hopefully this video will help explain
it a little bit more uh and all I'm
going to do is under our session fixture
I'm going to just do a little print
statement right here that says my
session fixture ran and uh this is you
know I'm recording this video in the
future so I've got all of the other
tests that we're going to cover done
already and I've kind of broken it out
into test posts this is testing all of
our post path operations we've got one
for users and one for votes and I'm
going to show you guys um what happens
when we use the default scope which is
uh it's scoped per function right this
is the equivalent of doing scope equals
function which means that we're going to
run this fixture for every single
function that requests it uh and so if I
remove this because once again it's the
default and I run my test I want you to
take a look at what happens
for every single test that we run one
dot represents the test we can see it
prints
out and so it's running through all the
tests in testore poost and then it's
going to run all the tests in testore
users and then votes so you could see
that because this is set to function
we're going to run this entire session
uh fixture this function every single
test that we have or at least every
single test that's requesting this
specific fixture uh that's why we see it
run every single time now if we change
the scope to module the behavior is
going to be a little bit different now
if I change the scope to module what's
going to happen is that for every module
that has um a test that's requesting
this specific session fixture we're only
going to run this fixture one time per
module and so now if I save
this and I'm going to no longer do- V
I'm just going to do just- s so we can
see this get printed out without too
much extra data cuz we're going to see a
lot of test fail and that's perfectly
okay I want you to notice what's
happening so notice how the print
statement ran
here and then the print statement ran
here and I I had to cancel out of that
because usually I end up with a ton of
errors and then I lose my
data but you could see that um the first
module which is testore py we could see
that my fixture ran because it's uh um
because I told it to run because one of
the tests is requesting it right it runs
then one of the tests
runs and then the next test runs and
then the next test runs so you can see
that this is not printing out per test
it's only printing out one time per
module so when testpost py ran for the
first time and the first test required
this specific fixture it ran once then
it didn't run for any of the other ones
that's why we see them all fail and then
the next module loads up and we start
running test from there so we run the
fixture just one time and then we don't
run it ever again so you can see seven
other I think it's six or seven other
tests ran with no other modules uh with
with the fixture not running uh any
other time and then we can see the same
thing for votes we can see that uh my
fixture ran just one time so this means
that it's going to run only once per
module we also have session so if I do
session it's going to be even more
different you're going to see it run
only one time for my entire testing
session so you can see my fixture ran uh
it's going to keep going through which
is perfectly fine uh and then when we
get to the next
module we should see it not run at all
right and so you can see it didn't print
again so it's going to go through all of
the different modules and I'm going to
cancel out of that before I get too many
errors right but now it only runs once
per entire testing session so that's
when the scope comes into play so keep
in mind you know depending on what
you're trying to accomplish you may need
to tweak the Scopes of your fixtures uh
depending on what they're supposed to be
doing um but for our database we want to
keep it set to a function which is the
default value because we want to load up
a brand new uh database by dropping our
tables and then creating new ones every
single time we run our test so the
default works perfectly fine for us now
to make our login user test independent
of any other test so it's not reliant on
a specific order or setting the fixtures
to be of a specific scope uh what we
want to do is before our login user test
runs I want to actually go in Define a
function that'll get called that'll
actually create a brand new user so that
we can actually test the login user out
uh and so you know as soon as I said the
words I want to run a function before
test runs the first thing that should
click in your head is you want to run a
fixture or you want to create a new
fixture so we can actually create a
fixture that'll create a test user for
us
so up here at the top of this file let's
create a new fixture and I'm actually
going to delete this test we don't
actually need it anymore it's just
taking up space or I can at least
comment it out I
guess and I'm going to define a fixture
here and we have to
import py test so we'll say from whoops
import py
test and we'll say add py test.
fixture and I'm going to call this test
user so it's going to be responsible for
creating a test
user and this is actually going to make
a call to our create user route so we
actually need access to client so that
we can actually make that request and
there's two different ways of doing this
right we could just have access to the
session object
we can have access to session object and
we can just you know session do you know
I think what is it actually no it would
be like
models. user and then pass in the data
for a test user and then create it
directly with the database or we could
just make a call to our API and actually
have it run through that so I'm going to
do that because it's a little bit
simpler for now but I'm going to define
a um a uh dictionary with the data that
I'm going to use for my user so I'm
going to have the email
and actually it's going to be a little
bit easier if I just paste this
in so we have the email set to something
and then the password set to
something and I'm going to change this
back to
client and now I can say res equals
client. poost and we'll send it to users
and then the data for the new user can
just be user unor data and just kind of
like what we've done here we can you
know just to make sure that this didn't
error out we can uh do an
assert and just say you know res. status
code equals equals
2011 if that's good I think it's safe to
assume we didn't run into any errors on
on the back
end um but then what I want to do is not
only do I want want to create the test
user I want to actually return the
information about the user so that this
login user will have the correct data uh
to send when he tries to log in that way
if we ever change this data we should
automatically update this
data so what are we going to return uh
well we have access to uh what is it
called uh to res. Json and if I print
that
out we can just quickly take a look at
what that looks like in for now I'm just
going to
return nothing I guess that's fine I'll
just return nothing and here I'm going
to change this to be uh I'm going to
pass in the test user so that also
runs and so now this login user is
dependent on two different fixtures
client and test user and before we do
anything else let's make sure we clean
up the scope we don't need these to be
set to that
anymore and if we run our test
all right the data we get back we get
the user
name oh sorry that's not what I want
this print we get the ID the email and
the created
at so what we'll do is I'm going to
actually take this dictionary and I'm
going to pass in the password as well
because when I actually go to log in the
user I need to make sure that he has
access to what my password is um but
that doesn't get returned returned in
the response so what we have to do is uh
we'll have to add a new field so I'll
say newor user equals you know res. Json
so we get that dictionary and then we'll
say newor user We'll add in a new key
called
password and I'll pass in user data
which is this dictionary up here and
we'll grab the password from here and
what I'm going to do is then return
newor user
and so anytime someone calls test user
or anytime we have a test that's
dependent on that uh it's going to run
this function it's going to return the
new user and so now that we have the new
user what we can do is I can say the
username
is testore user and we'll grab the email
key and then the password will be
testore
user and this will be
password okay and so that way if I ever
change the password up here it's going
to automatically get updated down here
so we don't ever have to worry about
that and one thing to note is that
technically if I deleted this and just
called test user right test user would
technically call client right and that
would go all the way back here and then
client would technically call session so
it would call all of these functions
automatically for us however the one
issue is that in this test we still need
to make a call with clients so we still
have to pass in the client object so
that we can make use of it but I did
want to highlight that because this
fixture is dependent on client it will
run whatever code is in the client
fixture and because client is dependent
on session it will run whatever code is
there within the session so it's all
done automatically for us right so the
order once again is going to be we'll
run session first we'll then run client
and then we'll run this test user
so let's test this out now hopefully
this
works and it passed Perfect Look at that
guys we were now successfully able to
log in a user so that's cool and all but
I want to do a little bit more
validation for the login user route uh
just to make sure that you know we got a
token the token is valid uh and just do
a few extra checks so just like we did
with the test create user we have we can
take use of we can make use of the
pantic model that we use for the
response so if I go into my o. py under
routers and we can see for the login the
response model is set to a schema token
so let's import
token inside our test users. py so here
schemas we already have access to
schemas and so I can
say uh token or what should I call this
I'll just call this
login res which
equals and then we'll call in schemas
dot uh I think it was is it token was it
token or token data I think it was
token well let's just double
check it's token perfect okay so token
and then what we're going to do is we're
going
to spread res.
Json all right so that's going to
perform a little bit of
validation right and then when we get a
token I want to actually valid Val
it so how exactly do we validate it well
we want to decode the token and so all
of the logic that I'm going to implement
here is essentially the logic that we
use within our oo2 py file so when we
want to get the user we want to verify
the access token is valid so how do we
do that the all of the logic is right
here so we're going to decode the token
and we're going to make sure that the
user ID is within that token and that's
all I'm really going to do at that
point so I will copy this
and we have to import
JWT
from so from I don't know if it's Jose
or Josie who knows uh so we'll import
JWT and what we'll decode is going to be
in the loginor res under the access
token property
uh and then we have to pass in the
secret key as well as the algorithm so
the secret key can be accessed with
settings
dot well I have to import my config so
I'll say
from
app.config import
settings so now we have access to our
environment variable so I'll do settings
dot secret key
and then the same thing goes for the
algorithm so I'll set this to settings
dot
algorithm so we're able to deload it uh
decode
it and then I'll remove this check I'll
just say ID equals
does ID equal equal and then is it going
to match the ID of test user so if we
take a look at what test user was that's
coming from this picture and so it's
going to return oh it looks like I did
not no no it should be in there so since
we grabbed the response the ID should be
there so we can just call this uh
testore user and then we can just call
ID so I think that's a little bit more
of a valid check cuz it's actually
decoding the token just to make sure we
didn't break anything there and and one
more
thing uh we can
assert
loginor
res. token type so this should be set to
bearer all right so let's test that out
now and everything worked I think I've
got one random print statement that I
don't want so I'll just remove that and
we have now successfully completed our
login user test okay guys so before we
actually create any more new tests what
I want to do is I want to create a
special file under our test directory
called conf test.py so this is a special
file that pest uses and it allows us to
Define fixtures in here and any fixtures
you define in this file will
automatically be accessible to any of
our tests within this package so it's
package specific so anything within the
test package even sub packages will will
automatically have access to any of
these fixtures and the reason I want to
do this is I want to take all of our
database code essentially or well our
database fixtures and I want to copy all
of
it and I want to move it to
contest uh and so by moving it to conf
test this fixture the session fixture as
well as the client fixture will all be
accessible to you know test calculations
test users any other test files uh
within the test
folder automatically and so now I don't
actually have to import anything so I
don't need to import from contest it'll
automatically do that it'll
automatically have access to
client and it'll automatically have
access to session and what I'm actually
going to do is I'm going to move this
test
user to contest as
well right and so that way um because
I'm I imagine that even for other
modules that I create uh you know
especially like uh for voting uh and a
few and creating posts they're going to
need test users as well so it makes
sense to put this in this compest so
everyone has access to it and I don't
have to go around constantly importing
things around like that and uh now
within our uh test users I should be
able to uh leave everything else uh and
you'll see that we're not importing
client or test user anywhere here but
when I run this we should see no issues
so let's give this a
try and you can see all of our tests
passed with absolutely no issues um
because we are importing those from the
contest file and keep in mind you know
let's say I created a new package um
I'll call this whatever how
about API or something it doesn't really
matter what I call it and I've got a
whole bunch of tests in here you know
testore something
py um because this package is still
within the test package it'll have
access to all of the mod um all of the
fixtures in the conf test py but within
a package I can also create a new conf
test so I can make a new conf test.py
down here as well and when I do it
within this
package then test users doesn't have
access to that one but anything within
the API package will have access to the
fixtures in in the API folder as well so
com test is package specific so every
directory you create you can create a
separate comp test file so that you can
essentially scope fixtures uh or you can
make it so that fixtures are
automatically imported into certain
parts of your tests and not
others but we'll delete that because I
don't actually need that all right so we
finished our successful login user test
the next thing we want to test is for a
failed login so I'll do the same thing
I'll call this um about test incorrect
login
and once again uh a few things need to
happen Let's uh we want the test user so
that a test user gets created so we can
try to log in uh with his credentials or
at least with the wrong credentials this
time and we do need access to client
just because we're going to be making a
request and here I'll say res equals
client.
poost and we'll say
login and for the login
data uh we'll say data equals and then
we'll do a dictionary here the
username uh we can use uh in this case
uh testore
user
email and then for the
password uh we can just I mean we can
just give it any arbitrary password it
just say wrong password because we know
that's the wrong
password uh and so when a user enters in
the wrong credentials we should get a
403 so we'll say assert uh res. status
code equals equals
403 and in the
response uh it should tell us that we
have invalid credentials so I'll say
assert response. Json it will convert it
to Json we will get the
detail
property and that should
equal invalid credentials make sure you
get the capitalization correct cuz it's
going to do an exact comparison
and just to confirm if that's how what
the capitalization looks like it should
be invalid credential so just copy it
directly from
here and this should be res not
response let's try this
out all right and the incorrect login
worked perfect so that means we did get
a receive we did receive a 43 and we did
receive the the message invalid
credentials uh but not only do I want to
test the wrong password I also want to
test a wrong email as well and I also
want to test wrong email and wrong
password and a few different things so
how do we do that well we can use
parameterize right so let's import pest
which we already
have and we'll Define our decorator so
pest. mark.
parameterize uh so what are the
properties that we want to pass we're
going to give it the attempted email the
attempted
password uh and then we can also get the
status
code and we could also you know match on
a specific detail message if you have a
different detail message for wrong
password wrong email but we don't so I'm
not going to include
that and then now we'll just give an
array uh with all of our why does it do
that uh so we here we'll Define our
tupal and I'm going to copy and paste
this part just because I don't want to
have to make you guys sit through this
but I've got a couple of different test
scenarios so here I've got the email
being wrong email at gmail.com with the
correct password we expect a 403 I've
got the right email wrong password I've
got the wrong email wrong password um
I've also got uh no password sorry no
email so if you put none this is
essentially leaving it blank so with
this set To None you'll see that our uh
API actually will send a 422 because the
scheme of validation fails because it
expects a username or a password uh and
then we'll try sending it with a correct
email but no password at all we should
get a 422 in this case because um pantic
uh uh performed its validation and found
that it was missing
Fields so that's what I'm doing here and
then we're just going to update all of
this so the
email uh wait sorry yeah the email is no
longer going to be test
user um it's going to be
well actually we first of all we have to
pass it into our function so email
password and status
code so we'll say
email password is going to be
password and status code is going to be
status code and we'll get rid of this
check uh just because the invalid
credentials won't apply when we get the
let's try this out
now yep and we can see all of our tests
have successfully passed so we have now
finally set up a test for making sure
that when a user does not provide the
proper credentials we get the right
response code and the right data
back and keep in mind guys right in this
case I just set this up to be a very
simple test just to check on the status
code but you could check any single
field that you want want it's up to you
you can make your tests as specific as
possible you can make them a little bit
more generic it's up to you to decide on
what you want to validate yourself and
like I said I'm trying to keep this uh
as basic as possible try to just make
sure that we focus on how to actually
create test and less on the actual
specific test that's all of the things
that I want to do for all of the user
tests let's move on to uh all of the
post test so test when it comes to
creating reading updating and deleting
posts so I'm going to store this in a
separate module just to keep things nice
and organized however you can keep
everything in one file if you really
wanted to but no reason to do that so
I'll call this testor post.
py now when it comes to working with
posts we do have to deal with a little
bit of an extra Challenge and that is if
you take a look at all of our post uh
path operations they all require
authentication so how exactly do we deal
with authentication uh when it comes to
testing
well you're probably thinking you know
we could you know Define a post uh
Define a test and we can call this you
know get all posts or something right
and then here we can pass in
client and then maybe test
user so we have access to that and then
we would just do you know client
dopost login so we log in we get a token
and then after after we get the token
then we
can um then we can make a request to
post and that is technically valid but
what I would like to do is I'd ra I'd
rather set up a fixture that
automatically does this for us but
instead of um but instead of actually
making a request uh to our API I want to
just import the the method the oo 2
method for uh creating an access token
so we can just import this into our test
so that we can actually fake our own
token or create our own token without
having to use the entire API and go all
the way through um back into this same
exact method to get a token cuz that
seems like a waste and we're testing a
whole bunch of other things that we
don't want to test in this specific test
so what we're going to do is we're going
to go to comp
test and I'm going to create a new
fixture I'm going to grab
this and I'm going to call this token so
we'll say token and this is going to be
dependent on test user so we need a user
to get created first before we run this
fixture
and what we're going to do is we're
going to import this
specific uh function right here create
access token from oath
2 and so I'll go from app. oo2 import
create access
token and just to quickly recap on how
that function works we pass in a
dictionary um but I don't actually know
what is in the dictionary uh so let's go
to uh where is this who calls this I
think
it's uh no it should be under users yeah
so create
user No it should be under login so
under login this is where we create the
token so we pass in uh data which is
just a a property called user ID and
then we pass in the ID that's all pretty
straightforward uh so we can do that
so I'll call create access
token and it's going to be a dictionary
and we call this what is it user ID and
we're going to pass in and we can get
the ID of the user from testore user
which is being passed in and we'll grab
the ID
property and we'll just return this so
this is going to return a token and
that's why we call this function token
then what I'm going to do is I'm going
to create another fixture I know there's
a lot of fixtures here but you'll
understand why I want to do this so I'll
do
Def and here I'm going to call this
authorized undor client the reason I'm
calling that is um if we take a look at
our current client this just gives us an
unauthenticated client this new fixture
will give us a authenticated client so
anytime we want to uh deal with any path
operations that require authentication
we can just call this client the
authorized client in of the regular
client so that's going to save us a lot
of
time and this is going to require the
regular client and token because we need
to get a
token all right so we have access to the
original client and what we can do is we
can update the headers um because we
need to pass the token inside the
headers so we do client.
headers and then we have to pass in a
dictionary and what we want to do is we
want to spread out all of the current
headers so we do client. headers and
then we want to add one more which is
going to be the
authorization and this is going to be an
F string because we need to add the word
Bearer before it and then we can pass
in
token and then we'll return this client
so it's basically taking the original
client and then just adding this
specific header that we get from the
token fixture that's all
and so now when we go into uh get all
posts and I forgot to put the word test
before
it instead of client we want to import
authorized
client we don't necessarily need test
user at this point it'll automatically
get called because you know this calls
token token calls test user uh we only
need to pass in uh test user if we want
access to specific user data but we're
not using any of the information at the
moment so I'll do authorized client.
getet and it's going to be
slost we'll set the response equal to
that and we'll just do a
print res. Json just to see what that
looks like
and I believe the status code should be
at 200 because we're retrieving data so
I'll do res. status code equals equals
200 let's just take a look and see what
exactly is happening
here and now it's going to be test
post and we get an error so let's see
what happened authorized client not
found so let's I think I forgot to save
let's try this
again and I forgot to turn this into a
fixture so right now it's just a regular
function so let's make sure I add the
fixture there so it's accessible to
everyone and now if I run
this okay so one passed let's take a
look at the data that we got back so
when I did a
print uh print of res. Json to see the
data I got an empty array and the reason
we got an empty array is that there's no
test data in our database there's no
test posts uh you know so we're going to
have to actually create some test posts
before we run this test so that we can
actually verify that we got what we
expected to
get so just like we did with the login
user where we created a test user before
we're going to have to do this with our
post we need to create a whole bunch of
posts and then verify that we are able
to retrieve those posts so we'll tackle
that in the next video so let's create a
fixture that will create a few initial
posts so that we can uh actually test
retrieving all posts and we can use that
same fixture for performing a few other
tests so things like updating a post
right we would need to have a post in
our database to update a post same thing
with deleting same thing with getting an
individual post so this fixture is
definitely going to be very reusable
across a lot of our tests let's figure
out where we want to store our fixture
we could keep it in our test app posts
testore post file because um all of our
posts uh all of our test posts sorry our
tests for post dat I guess if you want
to call that will require that fixture
probably however there are going to be
other tests in our application that will
need posts initially so when you want to
vote we need a post already in our
database so I'm actually going to put it
in our conf test file so that you know
everyone has access to it well
technically anyone can access any uh
fixture if they import it but having it
in the comp test file makes it simpler
because we don't have to import it so
I'm going to put it in here and I'm
gonna this this fixture is going to be a
little bit different just because we're
actually going to create the posts uh in
the database
ourselves so here I'm going to call this
uh testore
posts and so what we need is a couple
things so first of all we need a test
user because if we don't have a user we
can't create posts because all posts
need to be associated with the user um
since we're going to work with the
database we're going to pass in session
also
all right and let's define some post
data so I'm going to create an
array of dictionaries and I'm actually
going to copy and paste some data just
because I don't want you guys to sit and
watch as
usual all right so what we're doing here
now is we're creating three posts so in
this post data I have an array or sorry
in a list uh and then a dictionary and
then here we're providing the title and
the content and the owner ID all right
so that's going to create a post and
we're grabbing the owner ID from the
test user fixture and we're just going
to grab the ID from that so we're
setting the owner ID and then I'm just
going to create another post here and
another post here so the same user is
essentially creating three posts uh and
so now since we have access to session
we can actually just directly tap into
our database and create that information
for us for those posts
so we can do uh well the when it comes
to SQL Alchemy uh if you want to add
multiple entries into a database we have
access to the add all method so we can
call session. addore
all and then here we have to pass in a
list of user models so we this would be
you know schemas sorry not schemas we'd
actually have to import
models so I'm going to import do I have
models already in here doesn't look like
it uh so I'll import that as well so
we'll say from App dot we just say from
App
import
models and I can say models do
user so we'll create a new user model
and then we have to pass in all of this
data so right we would need to be title
equals you know blah and
then uh then content equals blah and
then we'd have to do another one so I'd
copy this paste this in
here uh and so on and then this would
add it all at once uh now I can manually
hardcode this value uh into here just to
kind of keep things simple and I could
do that and actually I will show you how
to do that just just just to in case but
I'll show you what I did when I was
doing a dry run so I'll copy the title
this is going to be set to First
Title uh the second title is going to be
here
content and second
content and then the owner ID is going
to be the same for both luckily well all
three actually
and that's not in the right
format oh don't do that it should be
equals and the same thing
here and if we wanted to we can copy
this last one and then put the third one
in this will be called third
title third content all right let's save
this the auto formatter did not do much
to help me out here still looks pretty
ugly but that's
okay uh and so that's one way of doing
this so it'll add it all and then all we
have to do is just do a session.
commit and then to get all the data back
I can just do a session.
query and we'll just say models. poost
oh this should be user by the way not
I mean this should be post not user
because we're creating a post and not a
user we'll say models.
poost and we can just grab all of
them now if you wanted to be able to
take this dictionary and convert it
easily to this format uh there's a
couple things you have to do um but
technically you could just leave it like
this and it'll work fine but just to
this a little bit more of python than
anything else if you didn't want to
hardcode it in like this because at this
point we don't even need this dictionary
but if you wanted to take this
dictionary uh and convert it into a list
of user models oh sorry post models what
we can do is we can use the map function
and so the map function works like this
you call map then you call some function
that you define
yourself and then you call the
postscore uh d data list that we have up
here and so this function what it's
going to do is it's going to iterate
through this list and it's going to take
each item in the list which is a
dictionary and it's going to convert it
into a models. poost so how exactly does
that look well let's first of all let's
rename this and I'm just going to call
this maybe uh create user
model and I'll Define a function up
here and I don't know why I keep saying
User it's a post we reading posts not
users create postore
model and this is going to get passed in
some uh some some object but technically
what's going to get passed into this
function is each dictionary so I'll call
this uh postore
data well actually don't call it post
data I'll just call this
post and so we have to put the logic of
converting a dictionary
into a post model and that's pretty easy
all we have to do is just say models.
poost and then we take post and then we
spread it that's it all right so what's
happening here is we're taking the a
dictionary which is what it's going to
get passed into here and then we're
taking it and spreading it so it looks
like title equals blah content equals
blah and then we can just return that
and then this map we just set it equal
to some variable I'll call this maybe um
post
map and I'm forgetting an e okay so then
so that's going to return um so that's
going to so that's going to essentially
convert all of those to user models but
it doesn't return a list it it returns a
map which isn't quite the same thing so
to convert it to a list all we have to
do is then say um posts
equals and we just say list and then
postore map so that'll convert it to a
list and then under session. add all
instead of hard coding those values I
could just say session. addore all and I
just pass in posts and we can just
comment out this line right
here either one works choose whichever
one you like I don't really care um but
this is all we need to do we just have
to return
this so I'll save this as
posts and we'll return
posts and that should create three posts
in our database and so now if I go to
test posts and make this reliant on uh
what did I call it get uh test
post if I then run
this right you can see that we did in
fact
get multiple test
posts and it's up to you to decide what
checks you want to perform um if we go
to our post route and we take a look at
the schemas you can see that it's going
to be a type list of schema. poost out a
list comes from the typing Library so
let's see if we can actually do this I
never actually tried this with this but
I think it should work so I will import
that and then will also import from app
from app
import
schemas and I'll just say
uh posts equals
res.
Json and I'll say actually schemas dot
uh what is it post out yep it's going to
be post
out I don't think that'll work because
yeah I don't think that'll work because
we're this is expecting one individual
post but this is going to be a list of
posts so I don't actually I wonder if I
can do yeah we'd have to do this
manually like we'd have to iterate
through it and then uh basically copy it
out and I think that would just take too
much work so we'll leave this section
out if you guys want to take that as a
challenge you can uh essentially create
a
post uh pantic model for each entry uh
within uh within the response and then
try to validate each single one so
instead I'm just going to do a simple
check I'm just going to say assert and
we'll just grab the length of response.
Json and I'm going to set this equal
equal to length of testore post just to
make sure that um we get three exact
posts
and if we ever change the number of
posts that we have this should
automatically get updated I think that's
a good enough check for this test let's
try this
again and we shouldn't get any errors
and it looks like it passed just
fine all right guys so I figured you
know what let me go ahead and just show
you how we can actually uh do the
validation using our schemas we're going
to use the same exact logic that we use
here when it comes to um performing the
map because we're essentially going to
take a list of dictionaries and convert
it to a list
of schema models so we're going to go
back to our post our test and what we're
going to do is we're going to first
Define a
function that's called um I don't know
we can call it validate and this is
going to receive a
post uh and that's going to be a post uh
that's going to be a dictionary that we
get back and all we're going to do is
we're going to return schemas Dot
post
out and here we're going to pass in the
data we're just going to unpack it with
post so that's all we have to do and
then we can call the map function like
we did before and I'll store this in a
variable called uh post postore
map which equals map we're going to call
the validate function and we're going to
pass in res.
Json and so we have a map if you wanted
to you could technically uh convert it
to a list um by calling list um post.
map but we're not doing anything with
that data however just to show you we
can just print this out real
quick and so now if I run
this and we take a look at the print
statement you can see we've got a post
out model and it does all the validation
so it's going to make sure all of the
properties are set and are there and
because we have it set as a post um as a
post out pantic model uh you'll see that
it's very easy to perform extra checks
with the search statement so now I can
do other checks like uh uh maybe I want
to
say actually let me first save this as a
variable I'll say posts list equals
list of posts map o and that's supposed
to be post map so we have access to this
list and now what I can do is I can just
say
assert and here we can grab postscore
list grab the first
post and we can check certain Fields I
can say like hey does the
ID uh sorry it's going to be the post.
ID does that equal equal
testore
posts we'll grab the first object and
then grab the ID well actually it's
going to be I think I could do just do
ID yeah because test post keep in mind
uh when we do test post this is going to
return uh uh this is going to return a
not a pantic model or a dictionary but
this is going to return a SQL Alchemy
model so a little bit different but we
just call ID and I think this should
work so let's test this
out it did not work what happened here
yep so I accidentally grabbed I see yeah
that so this is expected just because I
don't know the order that we're going to
retrieve the posts in I didn't provide a
uh order
by uh filter criteria uh when it comes
to my uh my get post functionality so it
could be returning any post so right now
it's saying that hey this ID happens to
be two this one happens to be one so it
the order doesn't matter so this isn't
exactly the best way to do it um but if
you want to figure out a way to set up
the order so that you always receive
maybe the post with the lowest ID and
then you compare the two that would be
perfectly fine and then you can check
other properties like what's the uh the
title does it match up with what we
expected to be does uh the content match
up with the content you can put as many
asserts as you can um but by having by
doing this um we are able to perform a
validation to ensure that at least we
get what we expect all the fields are
there and then it's just up to us to set
up the necessary asserts to verify that
the values are
correct but I'll remove that and I think
it's okay just to keep it like this for
now all right so we set up a test for
getting all posts and what I want to do
now is I want to test to make sure that
a unauthentic iated user is not able to
retrieve all the posts so I'll create a
new test and I'll call this test uh how
about
unauthorized user getor allore
posts and instead of using authorized
client because we want to test if a
unauthenticated user uh tries to access
as they get a 401 we'll just use the
regular client which is going to be a
non-logged in user and we want to make
sure that test posts are here as
well and remember because we're calling
test posts that's going to ensure that
because test post is reliant on test
user it will in fact create a test user
as well so just to give you a heads up
we don't actually have to pass in test
user into here because this should
handle that automatically and here I'll
just say res equals client. getet and
we'll just go to posts
again and I'm just going to assert a
simple 401 so res. status code
equals equals 401 that's really the only
check I want to do they're if they're
unauthorized or unauthorized there's no
other things to check
really and we can see that it did
successfully pass Okay so we've tested
the get all posts we're going to now
move on to getting an individual post by
an ID but before we do that I think it's
best to actually test getting an
individual post by ID when you're an
unauthenticated user because we can
essentially just copy this code and I
can just paste here instead of doing a
user get all post this will be user get
one
post and so everything else can be the
same we just have to change the specific
URL and so in this case we're just going
to grab the ID of one of the posts so
here I'm going to change this to an F
string and I'm going to say testore
posts we'll grab the first one and then
remember this is a SQL Alchemy model uh
and so we actually have to convert it to
a dictionary so we have to do doore
uncore dict uncore
uncore sorry the test post is not a SQL
is it a SE I think I could do ID I think
that should work actually never mind I
think we should be able to do that that
should be
fine and this should be a 401 so let's
test this out let's make sure that this
works and that
works and what I also want to do is I
want to test for a post uh test uh to
retrieve a post with an ID that doesn't
exist I guess so I'll call this a def
test
get
one post how about not
exist so this one we're going to need an
authorized
client and then testore poost as
well and I'm going to copy
this but we're going to change this and
I'm going to hardcode some random number
like
88888 and then we'll just assert res.
statuscode equals
equals
404 all right so now we're going to try
to retrieve a post that doesn't exist
and it looks like it passed
perfect so now let's actually try to
retrieve a valid post this one's going
to be a little bit more work so we'll
say def uh test get one
post and we're going to copy these two
and I'm going to copy this one right
here so we're going to retrieve the
first post from test post with an ID of
zero I
think and I'm just going to rename this
to authorized
client and let's just do a print let's
see what this looks like so we'll say
res.
Json all right and that's going to run
and it printed out the post so we can
see what that looks like and just like
we did before we can also do a
validation so I can
say um post
equals
schema schemas do uh what is it I think
it's post out yeah post
out and we're going to pass in res. Json
and do we need to unpack it I think we
have to unpack
it let me let me print out post just to
see what that looks like actually I
could just take a look at what we did up
here yeah we have to unpack
it or spread it whatever it's
called yep so now we've got our post
model uh well it's our pantic model and
so that does some level of validation
and then at this point what we can do is
I can say assert and I can say does
post Dot and then take a look at the
format we have to grab the uh the post
property it's this first one uh
yeah yeah so we'll grab post. post. ID
equals equals then we're going to
compare it to the
ID uh from testore Posts
so it say testore
posts
z.
ID and I think that should still
work all right that works and we can
check a few other things so we can say
uh post.
post.
content and if you're wondering why it's
post. post remember if you actually take
a look at our schemas our post out you
could see that we have to to grab the
information about the post we have to go
into the post property and then from in
there we can then take a look at all of
these
fields so that's why we have to do it
like
that and we'll say testore
posts zero and then let's see if we can
do content I believe this will actually
throw an error because uh this is a uh
SQL Alchemy model so it's going
to oh that actually did work I'm
surprised okay all right that worked so
uh if you guys want to you can also
essentially copy this line and then
check to see if the titles
match you can essentially check every
property if you really want to so we'll
just run that one last time
perfect and I'm just going to remove
this print statement uh and so those are
all of the tests that I want to do when
it comes to retrieving an individual
post I think um I'm sure there's a
couple of tests you guys might be able
to think of so feel free to implement
that but I think that's a good starting
point on this um but in the next video
we'll take a look at creating a post
okay so let's move on to creating a post
I'll create a function we'll call this
test uh create
post and we're going to need an
authorized
client we're going to need a test user
for sure and lastly um this is purely
optional if you want to we could also
set up all of our test posts um if you
wanted some posts in the database before
you created one just to potentially see
if you run into any issues when it comes
to creating posts when there's already
posts but it's
optional and we're going to set the res
and we'll set this to authorized client.
poost and the URL is going to be/
posts and then let's give all of the
data for our new post so we'll say Json
equals uh
title and you know what instead of doing
this uh let's go ahead and set up
a uh py
test dot uh what was it called I already
forgot what it's what do we call
it a parameterize so Mark parameterize
so that we can test multiple different
values mark do why is that not working
okay I have to import P test and we
don't need this line right here so we'll
say import P
test uh and so what are the values that
we need how about uh
title we need title for sure we need uh
content and then we can also give a
published value if we wanted to
and then let's give all of our come on V
Cod don't do that all right first two
pull uh what do we want the title how
about awesome new title o awesome new
title uh what's the content awesome new
content and what do we want published to
be how about true
and we're going to copy this and I'm
just going to put in some new
values favorite
pizza and we'll see I love
pepperoni
ooh
published let's see that's still a work
in
progress allst skyscrapers
all right so we've got some test data uh
let's pass those values
in so
title is going to be set to title
content is going to be set to
content and then finally uh published
will be set to
published all right we get our response
back let's do a little bit of validation
with our pantic model so I can say
schemas
dopost and we'll just uh take the
response convert it to Json of course
and set that to created unor poost
and then we can just run a couple of
checks so uh let's assert the status
code so for creating a new post it
should be a
2011 and then
for uh we can just assert a few extra
values so I could say like res
dot actually I can grab created unor
poost do uh title
should
equal
title and I can just do the whoops I
need two equals and then I can just copy
this a few times we'll change this to
content content and then published
and while we're ated it we can also
verify that the owner ID gets set so I
can say
created
underscore post. owner
ID equals equals and then we can grab uh
test
user
ID all right so I think that's a good
number of things to check so at this
point I think it's safe to say that all
of these should work
all right and all of
those passed awesome so we've got the
create post done uh there's one other
thing that I want to test with create
post because um if you go back to
our um what is it our schemas where is
our
schema I don't know if we have a create
post post create um so that's just going
to be from post base we can see
published is set to a default value of
true so let's test to see if the default
value of true gets
set and we theoretically could have put
this test in here just by doing a none
here but I like to separate this out
into a different test because we are
testing a different functionality in
this case so we'll say test create
post default
published
true I'll do authorized _ client and
test
user once again we don't need test post
but if you want to have it in the
database just just to make sure that
everything's uh not broken when you
already have posts already in there we
can keep that
in and I'm just going to copy
this actually I could essentially copy
all of
this and we can just give it arbitrary
titles and then published we'll leave
out published we don't want that
anymore and I'll just copy these values
here and published should be set to True
by default so even though we're not
passing it it should get set and
everything else should still be just
fine so let's test that out
oh it looks like it failed so what
happen
here oh I just pasted in the wrong
values
all right and then one last thing just
like we did for all the other uh routes
within the post we also want to test if
we're not logged in so I'm going to copy
this
one and just rename it so test
unauthorized
user create post we don't need to have
test user in there but why
not and I'm going to just copy this
right here
and then just change this to a plain
client all right and this should
work all right and that passed as well
so we have got all of the create post
tests done and I think in the next video
we will tackle either deleting or
updating a post okay so let's move on to
deleting posts and the first thing that
we're going to do is we're going to test
a unauthorized user trying to delete a
post we'll say
test unauthorized
oops delete post and we'll have client
testore user and we'll definitely need
test Post in this
case and then we can essentially copy
well I'll copy this one right up here
and uh we'll change this to uh we don't
need the body
anymore and the route is going to be
we're going to pass uh testore
posts uh
zero. ID
all right let's test that
out yep and I realized this should be a
delete actually not a
post that's why I got um other status
code Perfect all right so we got that
one to pass and so now let's test a
valid deletion so I'll say uh test
delete post and ideally I guess we
should be calling like success like we
successfully deleted
it and this time we'll get the
authorized
client we'll get the test
user and the testore posts all right
we'll call this same request
here and just change this to authorized
client
and this should give us a
204 I mean you theoretically could also
you know then fetch all posts again just
to verify that the total number of posts
is one less but we're not going to do
that in this case you could however do
that and that failed so what happened
here a
422 and uh two things so I don't even
know how this one ran with the same
issue we should we need to make that an
F string so I genuinely don't know why
that actually worked little alarming but
let's test both of those
out all right all of them passed so
we've got that
done let's test deleting a non-existent
post so an ID that doesn't exist in our
database
I'll say test delete
post
nonexist and I'll just copy
these and I'll copy this actually I'll
just copy all of
this and I'll just change this to be
some ridiculously high number and this
should be a 404
all right that one looks
good all right so the next one's going
to be a little bit trickier uh we're
going to create a test where a user
tries to delete a post that isn't theirs
they try to delete a post that's owned
by someone else so we'll say test
delete other user post
now there's a couple of issues here so
first of all uh we need to actually have
more than one user in the database and
we need to have um posts owned by
multiple users now so this creates a
couple challenges so how exactly are we
going to set up more than one user well
uh I think it's best to use fixtures
like we always have and ideally I would
have uh set up a test
user um where is it my test I would have
set up a test user uh to actually create
multiple users in our database but I
didn't so I just have one um if we had
set it up so that multiple users are in
the database then this test would be a
little bit easier since I didn't what
I'm going to do is I'm essentially going
to copy this I'm going to copy
this and right above it I'm going to
create just a second one I know it's not
very original probably not the most
efficient way of doing things and it's
going to be dependent on client and
we're just going to put a one or
something it doesn't really matter just
so that we have another user I'll make
this 1 2 3 and so now we have two
users which is perfect uh and uh down
here in my post data what I'm actually
going to do is I'm going to create one
extra
post and we could just copy this data
right
here and here I'm actually going to pass
in an extra fixture which is going to be
testore user 2 so before test post get
created we're going to create the second
user and here I can just grab the ID of
test user to and actually I don't even
need to do that I don't know why I did
that let's we don't even need to create
a post uh owned by that user we'll leave
it like this for
now nope I was right actually we do I
don't know why I'm flip-flopping like
this so so the fourth post 1 2 3 4 is
going to be owned by test user 2 and so
now if I go back to test post here we're
going to be logged in remember
authorized client is always going to be
logged in as user one so we're going to
try to delete that fourth post uh and so
we can do that by uh grabbing the ID of
the fourth post so we'll say
testore need curly braces testore
posts we'll grab the fourth one which is
an index of
three and then we'll grab ID
and this should um I forget what kind of
error it should get or what status
code I think it's
403 uh so we'll do assert res. status
uncore code equals equals 403
and it looks like that successfully
passed uh and so that one's good and
that pretty much wraps up all of the
delete tests that I want uh and then in
the next video we'll take a look at
updating posts all right so let's update
a post I'll say de testore update
post here uh we need an authorized
client and we'll need a test user
and we'll need testore
posts all right and I'm going to define
a dictionary with the values that I want
to update and so here I've got the title
the content and then the ID which I'm
grabbing from test posts and I'm just
going to use the first test Post in
there and I'll say res equals authorized
client dot I think it's
put and then we're going to do an F
string and we'll say SL poost
and this one will be
testore
posts
z.
ID and then we have to pass in the data
so we'll do Json
equals uh
data so we passing in this
dictionary right and uh just like we do
with um
the other routes if we go to the update
post uh technically we're sending it out
with the schema of post so we can just
quickly validate it on our end on the
test as well so I can
say uh updated post equals schemas
dopost and we'll pass in res.
Json and then we can assert a couple
things so we'll say uh res. status
code is going to equal uh what's an
update I guess we use 200 in that case
and then we can assert a few things so
we want to make sure that the new
title uh we can do updated post.
tile equals
equals um data.
updated uh sorry data dot ah this is a
dictionary so
title and we can do the same thing for
the
content and I think that should be
everything that we
need and just to you know just to make
sure that my tests don't take too long
I'm going to start uh commenting out all
of my other code all of my other tests
in this file
just to make things a little bit quicker
but you can see how it starts to slow
down uh just with just a couple of tests
really
so we can see that it did successfully
pass so that's good um we've got the
first update post
test uh the next thing I want to do is I
want to try to update another user's
post so we'll say
update other user
post so this we need to authorize
client uh we need test
user and we need test user
2 and
testore posts so we're going to try to
update that last post and so I'm going
to define a dictionary with the values I
want to update it with uh so same thing
title content the only difference is the
ID is going to be
uh I think it's uh actually three the ID
is going to be of um the third sorry the
the
fourth item in that list and I just want
to make sure it's the fourth one so one
two 3 four so yeah we need a a value of
three and I'm going to copy
this and just change this to
three and we should get a status code
of 403
and let's test that
out
perfect and the last thing we need to do
is a unauthenticated user trying to
update a post actually there's two more
tests um so let me grab
uh unauthorized user this one right here
and this is going to be a
put and that should return a 401 and the
last thing that we need is and actually
I need to update this name so
unauthorized
test update
post we can also set up a test to um
update a post that doesn't exist and I
believe we can just copy the deleting
the post that doesn't exist
um uh Delete post delete post non-exist
so I could just copy this
one and change this to a
put and we'll change the name to be
update and Let's test this
out hopefully everything
works oh one failed what happened
here okay so it tries to validate it um
because I didn't provide any data so I
can just copy this data right here just
so we can give it
something and so we can say uh Json
equals data and that's going to to
prevent us from getting validation
errors and that passed perfect so let's
take all that I'm just going to
uncomment everything else so we can get
all of our tests back and that's going
to wrap up updating posts and that's
actually going to wrap up all of my post
cases uh and so I guess the last thing
that we got to do is set up uh all of
the voting tests and there's only going
to be a couple of voting tests but it
should be
fairly
quick all right so let's move on to
setting of our test for voting I'm going
to create a new file we'll call this
testore votes.
py and let's define our first function
so I'll call this uh test uh vote on
post so this is going to be a successful
vote on a post what do we need we need
an authorized client of
course and we need uh to make sure that
there's some posts already in our
database
all right and now I can do a authorized
client. uh
post and here this is going to be uh the
vote
endpoint and let's just give it some
data so here we're going to pass the
post
ID so this will be postore
ID and we'll Gra grab the first item in
our
list test post.
ID and I forgot my curly braces that's
why it's giving me an error right
now and uh we'll say what is
the oh the direction so we're going to
be voting so this going to be dur set to
one all right and now technically if you
look at what's happening right we're
logged in as user one and test post if
we go back to that fixture where is this
guy that's owned by user one as
well so technically we're voting on our
own post but if you look at our code we
didn't actually put any checks to stop
us from um liking one of our own posts
so it's perfectly fine in our test to do
that just because our our code is right
now allowing it if you didn't want to do
it then first of all we'd have to update
this code to make sure that we perform a
check to verify that hey are we voting
on our own code if so uh sorry voting on
our own post then we should reject it
but we don't have that implemented so
for our test it's perfectly fine because
that's how our application works but
obviously if you wanted to um to make
sure that you're testing someone else's
post um then you could just obviously
pick the last item so the third item in
the array um because that's owned by
test user to you just would have to make
sure that you pass in test user to in
this
case uh just to make sure that he gets
initialized
um but that that's a good uh assignment
for you guys um I would see if you guys
can Implement logic to make sure that
you can't vote on your own post and then
go ahead and create your very own test
to make sure that uh if a user tries to
vote on his own post he gets an error of
some kind um but for us this is good
enough I'll leave it as three just so
we're voting on someone else's post I'm
okay with that and we can just assert
res. status
code equals equals 2011 don't really
need to check anything else
and now I can just change this to test
votes okay so that one successfully
passed all right the next thing I want
to test on is what happens when a user
tries to uh Vote or like a post that
he's already liked so we'll call this a
def uh testore vote uncore twice
poost and so uh we'll need an authorized
client uh we'll definitely need test
posts um but there's one little issue
with this one right we need to have a
post that's already been voted on and we
don't have that right now so how do we
do that well I mean theoretically we
could initialize our uh test post
fixture with some votes but instead of
doing that I'm going to actually create
a new fixture and I'm going to keep it
in this file because all this fixture
will do is it will set up one of our
posts to have a vote on it already um
and I don't think really anybody else in
any other test in our application is
going to need that outside of the voting
file because that's the only one that's
concerned with voting so let's test that
out uh so we'll import py
test and we'll set up our fixture so py
test. fixture
and I'll call this um test vote
maybe and so for this fixture to work we
definitely need an authorized
client actually we don't need an
authorized
client uh we'll need a we'll need test
posts uh we'll need a session because
we're going to just change it in the
database directly and then we'll need a
test
user and so let's uh well we're going to
have to import our models so I'm going
to say
import um import from
App import
models and I'm going to say models. vote
so let's create a new vote uh so we're
going to have to pass in the postore ID
which is going to equal uh testore
user we'll grab the third one do
ID and then we need to pass in the user
ID
which equals oh it looks like we
actually yeah we already have the test
user so I can say testore
user
ID and then I can just do session.
add new
vote and I need to create a variable or
store this in a variable so new
vote and then we can do session. commit
and so down here I can pass in uh
testore
vote and I'll say res equals authorized
client.
poost and then Json equals
uh what is the post ID we'll grab this
from uh test underscore posts grab the
third and we'll grab the
ID and then we'll set
the the
dur to be a
one so we're trying to revote on that
vote and we should get a 409 so we'll do
assert res. status code equals equals
409 all right let's test that
out one error oh man what happened
here that's a key error so something
very simple
happened y and and I see my mistake they
should be test
posts all right let's try that out
now and that worked
perfect all right now let's try
successfully deleting a vote
and so we will need all of these we'll
also need a test
vote and so we do res
equals authorized client. poost once
again G I'm just going to copy all of
this uh so we got that and then the
direction is going to be zero for
deletion and then we just need to assert
res. status code uh this is going to
equal I think we just left it as a
2011 okay so that worked and then now we
want to delete a vote uh that doesn't
exist so unlike a post that doesn't that
we never liked so we'll say uh def
testore uh Delete
vote non
exist uh so we'll need the same exact
stuff right here I'm just going to copy
all of this for now and then we'll
change up the few
details uh Direction zero same
post um but I'll just
grab actually um we don't want the test
vote because we want to make sure that
there isn't a vote so we're going to
remove that
fixture and this should be a 404
or let's try
that that worked and then finally let's
try uh voting on a post that doesn't
exist so we'll yeah liking a post that
doesn't exist so we'll say def toast uh
test vote post
nonexist and uh copy all of these
I copy
this set the direction to one and uh the
ID is going to be
8,000 and we expect the status code to
be uh 404 as
well all right it looks like
everything's good the last thing that we
just want to check is make sure that a
user who isn't authenticated can't vote
so I will copy
this uh test
vote um unauthorized
user and then we want just the regular
client in this
case we'll do uh test posts 3. ID
and this should be what is it a
401 um I can't remember let me go to the
other one it should be a 401
okay all right guys so I think we've
covered uh all of the tests that I
wanted to cover um we don't need this
test calculations py file but I'll keep
it in there in the repo just so you can
take a look at it the database. py file
is absolutely useless now so I'm I'm
actually going to just delete I'll keep
it in there just in case you want to see
it but most of it moved to contest. py
um but just to make sure that
everything's still working I'm going to
run my tests for all o what happened
here nope nope nope oh
oh okay yeah that was
wild all right remove this let's see
what happens hopefully everything passes
and all 46 tests have successfully
passed so that pretty much wraps up all
of the testing section um I recommend
you guys think of different scenarios
that could potentially break our
application um and set up tests for each
and every individual scenario because
that's how you uh successfully set up
tests because you want to make sure you
cover every individual corner case that
you can possibly think
of currently when it comes to adding in
new features and making changes to our
code uh we have to go through very
manual and cumbersome process before we
can get those changes pushed out to our
production environment and so what I
think would be good is for us to set up
a cicd pipeline so that we can do all of
this in an automated fashion so I've
created a couple slides just to kind of
go over what our cicd pipeline's going
to do and I've got the generic uh
definition of cicd and it's probably not
a very good definition and I was
thinking about just leaving out the
slide because it doesn't really provide
much but i' figur I'd just add it just
in case so cic CD stands for for
continuous integration and continuous
delivery so continuous integration is
the automated process to build package
and test your application and then the
continuous delivery picks up where your
continuous integration ends and
automates the whole delivery of the
application so continuous delivery is
responsible for actually pushing out
those changes to your production Network
so those two things make up our cicd
pipeline um but let's actually take a
look at what our whole manual process
looks like right now so that we can see
where a lot of the extren time
consumption and manual process takes
place so our current manual process is
that you know we're going to make some
changes to our code and then we're going
to commit those changes to get right
because you know we don't want to lose
those changes and then after that we
want to go ahead and run P test so that
we can verify that our changes didn't
actually break any known functionality
to our code and if the our tests pass uh
we have an optional step of um you know
building any images so things like
Docker images if we happen to be running
Docker in our development and production
environment if we're not then this is an
optional step however when it comes to
the build phase in this case that some
people referred to uh other programming
languages might require you to kind of
build uh the application at the end to
actually be able to deploy it um python
you don't really need to do that so
that's why it's kind of an optional step
here if you're not using Docker um but
after we do that we then move on to
deploying our application so I just have
one row called deploy here but keep in
mind this um this one little block could
represent multiple steps because
depending on how you actually deploy
your application um making uh any
changes or updating the code in your
production environment could actually
involve uh a very complex process so
with Git or sorry with Heroku right it's
obviously a very simple process because
all we do is we just do a uh a get push
uh to Heroku and that's going to
automatically cause Heroku to kind of
hand all of the the updating of the
processes so that's a feature that's
built into Heroku but we only get that
if we use Heroku um there's obviously a
number of different ways that we can
deploy our
application uh if we uh decide to go the
route of deploying our application uh on
an abunto server then the deployment
process in this case would be us logging
into our server us pulling in the new
code with the changes and then
restarting the service so that our
application actually uses the new code
um but if you're using you know some
other
production environment or you use some
other method to deploy your application
uh this could be an even more complex
process something to keep in mind so
even though it's just one block listed
here it could actually be um you know
numerous
steps all right and so now I want to
show you guys what our automated cicd
pipeline is going to look like after we
set it up uh and so just like we did in
the manual process we're going to make
changes to our code obviously that's a
manual step because we have to implement
the the changes to our code and then
we're going to commit those changes and
with a cicd pipeline or specifically
with the one we're building that's all
the manual steps that we have to do we
are done we don't have to touch our
keyboard or our Mouse um it's basically
hands off at this point and we're going
to let automation take
over uh and so usually when you commit
changes to your code that's going to
trigger our cicd pipeline to run and so
what happens is our continuous
integration phase starts at this point
as soon as we commit those changes so in
the C I phase we do the the first thing
that we do is we pull our source code so
we pull our source code so that we can
actually work with it we then install
any dependencies so this is the
equivalent of uh installing all of the
dependencies listed in our
requirements.txt
file we then run our automated tests uh
so that's running Pi test and then you
know assuming the tests pass we then
build any images this is once again an
optional step for us uh it's only in
that's only needed if we are have if we
use Docker um but that wraps up the
continuous integration phase so once
that's done uh The Continuous delivery
phase is going to take over and so the
continuous delivery phase what it's
going to do is it's either going to grab
the latest code or the new build image
depending on what our deployment model
actually is and with the new image or
code it's going to then have all of the
logic needed to push that new image or
the new code into our production and
make sure that our production is
actually using our brand new code uh and
so these two steps are really the only
manual steps The Continuous integration
and the continuous deliver phase is all
done in an automated fashion through
code essentially uh and so some of the
more common cicd tools include Jenkins
Travis CI Circle CI uh and uh and GitHub
actions now for our course we're
actually going to use GitHub actions
just because it's already integrated
into GitHub it's free uh we don't need
to install anything on our local machine
there's no software that we have to set
up because it's all hosted on GitHub so
it's like a hosted service and it's just
going to make things very clean very
simple and it's free so uh it's going to
make and so everyone will be able to
have access to
it so what exactly is a cicd tool what
does it provide uh and so every time I
heard cicd before I learned what it is
um I always thought it was like a very
complex thing and then when you find out
what it actually is it's actually the
stupidly simple it it is there's no
magic behind cicd it's all very manual
even though it's an automated process
you'll see that when we actually go to
configure it it's not really doing
anything special it's it's doing
everything that we already do but we're
just providing instructions to a machine
so a cicd tool what it does is it
provides us a runner and so a runner is
just a fancy term for a computer or or a
virtual machine it doesn't really matter
um you know what is the underlying
infrastructure they give you a little
machine uh that we can provide a bunch
of commands for it to run right so just
like like in our terminal where we run
commands like pest or uh or pip install
right we provide these commands to a
computer and these commands are usually
configured or provided in a yaml or Json
file or even through a guey depending on
what your cicd tool is but the different
commands that we provide that little
mini computer to run make up all of the
actions uh that our pipeline will
perform and this pipeline or this
virtual machine that we have is going to
run based off of some of event getting
triggered and so like I mentioned this
is usually us either doing a g push or
uh performing like a merge pull a merge
request it doesn't really matter there's
a lot of different events that you can
configure depending on your uh cicd tool
you can also set it up to run every
single night at 2 in the morning uh
there's a lot of different options but
mostly it's going to be based off of a
get push and I wanted to provide just a
quick example config uh of what our CI
uh CD pipeline is going to look like
when we're done so this is just a little
snapshot of it it's not all of it but I
wanted to show you just how simple
setting up a cicd pipeline is so this is
the yaml file that we use to kind of
tell the machine what are the steps that
we wanted to
perform and so you can see here we've
got this section called steps so already
you can tell we're just providing it a
list of steps um now the the syntax may
be a little foreign but you'll see that
it's pretty easy to learn uh you'll see
that the first step that we have is
there's this thing called action SL
checkout so what this is actually doing
is it's telling our machine to pull our
our code so after we do a get push it's
going to pull our brand new code so that
we can actually do something with the
code and then the next step is here
we're setting up python 3.9 so all it's
doing is it's installing python 3.9 for
us and then afterwards we have to update
pip so it's going to run python DM pip
install D- upgrade pip so that's going
to upgrade pip so we have the latest
version then we're going to install the
dependency so that's pip install dasr
requirements.txt so you can see all the
things that we do on our local machine
we're just telling this little machine
to do the same same thing and then
afterwards we then run uh py test so
that's going to first install py test
and then we just run P test right just
like we did on our local machine we're
just telling the machine to do the same
exact thing so we're just telling the
machine a list of instructions that we
have done um by ourselves manually we're
just giving that list to it so it can
run automatically right and so hopefully
you guys see just how simple a cicd
pipeline is there's nothing magical to
it it's just like telling a machine this
is what we want to do I want you to run
this every single time we do a push all
right so hopefully you guys understand
this uh in the next video we'll get
started on setting up uh GitHub actions
so that we can actually build out our
cicd pipeline all right before we get
started with working with uh GitHub
actions I want you to open up a couple
of web pages so if you go to the GitHub
actions uh documents page I definitely
recommend you pull this up uh take a
look at the quick start page and the
reference page just to get an idea of
how to work with GitHub actions um I
will cover everything but you know you
are going to forget some things I cover
so definitely know where the
documentation is um pull up the GitHub
Marketplace as well so this is where we
can look up built-in actions that we can
use uh in our cicd pipeline that have
kind of handled a lot of the more
complex logic and then on top of that
you'll see that GitHub has this uh
example tutorial on how to set up a cicd
pipeline for a python application so
this is what I kind of looked at to um
get started with building out a cicd
pipeline for our fast API and it kind of
covers most of the things we do that we
need so if you want to you could just
follow this and I think at that point
you'll have a good idea as to how to
work with this um but once again like I
said we're going to cover everything
from
scratch um but if we go to the
documentation you go to Quick Start
Right Here Right it tells you that we
want to create a folder called GitHub
and then in that folder we want to
create a folder called
workflows so let's go ahead and and do
that uh so in our main project directory
let me just minimize everything I'm
going to create a brand new folder
and I'll call this a
GitHub and then we want a new folder
within here called
workflows all right and so here we can
Define all of our workflows which kind
of make up our cicd pipeline you can
have more than one you don't need to
just have one in this case but we're
just going to use one because we're
keeping things simple and so here this
is where we're going to create a yaml
file so if you aren't familiar with a
yaml it's just a a certain type of um
markup language uh that's commonly used
for like config files and things like
that because it's very easy to read but
the most important thing to keep in mind
is that spacing matters in yaml so um
you definitely want to make sure that
all the things are lined up very
carefully uh just like it was uh when it
comes to like the docker compos file so
we'll go here and I'm going to create a
brand new file and I'm going to call
this
build- deoy
doyl all right and so we're going to
give this workflow a name so even though
we gave it the file a name we actually
have to provide a name here so we just
do name and feel free to call it
whatever you want I'm just going to call
this build and deploy
code okay and then we have to Define
when should our workflow or in this case
which is our cicd pipeline when should
it run when should it trigger what
triggers our code to run and so like I
mentioned it's usually a either a um a
polar request or a uh get push
so to specify when we trigger this you
pass in the on field and then you
specify you know should this be a push
or a pull request or should it run for
both and so if you want this to run only
on uh get pushes you would just do on
push if you wanted to run on a pull
request you do pull request
here um but if you wanted to run for
both both uh get push and pull request
then you would do push and pull request
and there's a lot of flexibility too so
um the way we have it set up right here
this would happen on every push on every
single branch and every pull request on
every single Branch but there's a
possibility that maybe you don't want
this to run for all of your branches
right maybe you only want this to run on
the main branch and a couple of other
branches and then the rest of the
branches you don't really care about so
what you can do is we can go down a
level and then hit tab in this case and
remember like I said spacing matters so
we'll say push and then here you can
Define all of the branch es that should
run whenever you uh uh do a push so if I
here I pass in
main what's going to happen is that this
workflow is going to trigger every time
we do a push specifically only to the
main branch and no other branches and so
you can provide a list of all the
branches so this is you know another
Branch this is uh you know maybe some
feature Branch all the names of the
branches that you want your workflow to
run on uh you can specify that and this
is one way of providing a list in yaml
uh the other way uh is to actually go
down here and then do a dash and then
provide the name so I would do
Main and then you know some other
branch and so
on and then if we wanted to we could
also customize um all of the branches
that should trigger this workflow on a
pull request as well so if I do pull
request
and then I do uh
branches and this should be moved back
here and then here I do
branches and then I can do a list here
as well and I'll just call this uh we'll
give an example Branch I'll say test
Branch right and so just to kind of read
this through uh anytime we do a push to
either one of these branches it's going
to run our code and anytime we do a pull
request to this specific Branch it's
going to run our code as well so that's
just how to set this up uh we're not
going to do any of that cuz we just have
one branch in this case so I'm just
going to say we're going to have run
this on push and pull
requests for all
branches and if we actually go to the
documentation um I think yeah the
reference
page uh you can go to the reference page
and then select events that trigger
workflows uh and that's going to cover
everything that we just covered so it's
going to go over all of that and you'll
even see that there's a scheduled event
so you can tell it to run kind of like a
Cron job like hey I want this to run
every single hour and there's a few
other like manual events that you can
trigger uh and a couple of like web hook
Integrations as well but we're not going
to do any of that we're just going to
keep things simple for now all right so
once we've defined what's going to
trigger our workflow we have to then
create a job and so if you go to the
documentation the the GitHub actions
documentation says that a job is just a
set of steps that execute on the same
Runner so our runner is just a virtual
machine so when our workflow runs runs
right it's going to we have to provide
it a job which is just a list of steps
that's going to run on that specific
runner in that case and so here I'll go
to jobs this is where we provide a list
of jobs we're going to start out with
just one in this case and we can give
this whatever name we want I'm going to
call this job one uh not a very good
name we're going to rename it in the
future but I want to just keep it simple
for
now and what we want to do is we want to
specify what type of machine do we want
to run this on and so like I said a cicd
tool like gith actions is going to
provide us a machine a computer and we
have to specify what operating system do
we want to run it on uh so we're going
to just use it on on Linux but keep in
mind you can run this on Windows you can
run this on Mac you can even run it on
all three if you want to test all of
them but since our
deployment since our production
environment is running on a Linux
machine I think it makes sense that we
do all of the testing and all of this on
a Linux machine so you pass in the runs
on field and then here we say a buntu l
so this is going to be the latest auntu
version and uh if we go to the reference
page here and go to the workflow syntax
I think and we go to jobs um that's
going to provide us uh all the
information when it comes to um what we
can run this on so you can see here we
can provide Windows
2022 um or you can just grab Windows
latest we've also got and I realized the
text is probably small for you guys we
got different versions of Windows we got
a bunto latest which in this case at the
moment is just going to be the same
thing as writing auntu 20.0 before but
you can grab any one of these specific
auntu versions as well as Mac OS 11 and
some of the other previous Mac
versions but like I said we're going to
stick to just running on a buntu and we
might as well just grab the latest
version and so once we specify the
operating system the next thing that we
have to do is provide a list of steps so
we kind of went over what the steps
would look like when we did the little
PowerPoint demonstration so here we say
steps and then we provide a list of
steps so uh when it comes to lists in
well you just do the dash and then you
provide the
lists and usually when it comes to a
specific step um we give it the specific
command that we want to run as well as a
name right a human readable name so that
when we look through the logs we know
which step is doing what so we can say
like hey this step is installing python
or this step is uh running py test uh
and so here we if we say name this is
where we provide a description for what
we're about to do so the first thing
that we always want to do is we want to
check out our code and so I'm going to
say hey this is uh
checking or I'll just say this is uh
pulling get repo right it's going to
pull our code and then we have to
provide the uses so this is the actual
command that needs to run on our machine
to pull our
repo and with GitHub actions uh like I
said there's a Marketplace of pre-built
actions that we can use to um you know
essentially perform various tasks so
pulling your code is a very common task
so they've definitely got an action for
this and so if I just search for
checkout because I know that's what it's
called Uh you can see this is the one we
want and so this is uh this is what's
going to be responsible for pulling your
code and so here you just say uses you
do actions SL checkout
V2 and you could specify a specific
repository that you want to pull however
GitHub already knows what repository
we're working on because we did a get
push and since all of this is integrated
together we don't actually have to pass
in any other field however um you know
if you look at the documentation you can
specify what specific repository you
want uh as well as you know any SSH keys
that you may need and things like that
but this is GitHub action so it's all
already hosted on GitHub so it's a
pretty simplified process so all we have
to do is just copy this right here and
we can just kind of continue down and
just provide as many extra steps as we
want um I'm just going to provide a very
simple step after this just to show you
you know a step is just nothing more
than us giving a command so I'm going to
name this
one uh say hi to
seve and what we can do is this is a
special um action that's that we grab
from the marketplace but if you just
want to run a command on the machine uh
which is just a Linux machine we can run
any specific Linux command that we want
because we have access to the CLI all we
have to do is just use the Run keyword
and then we specify the command we want
so if you wanted to install a you know a
package we could do you know pseudo apt
install whatever or if you want to
reload the machine you know you could do
a reboot I'm not sure why you would do
that so all I'm just going to do is I'm
going to just make it say echo which is
just going to uh Echo out exactly what I
type in here I'm going to say hello
sanie and so it's just going to run this
command on our Linux machine uh and so
this is a very simple uh example so far
but I think that's a good starting point
so that we can actually understand
what's happening and what we want to do
is we now want to actually push this
changes uh to our git repository so let
me open up my
terminal make sure you do uh save all
and so once we push this this will
actually be part of our repository and
it's going to actually trigger um GitHub
actions to actually trigger this
workflow because we said that on every
push we should run this workflow so I'll
do a get add
all I'll do a get push sorry get commit
DM
adding first GitHub
action and then we'll do a git push and
we can do an origin main if you want to
be
specific all right so it's been
pushed uh and so now if we go to our
GitHub repository there's a actions tab
right
here and so you'll see that I had a
previous I had a couple of other uh
actions that ran because I was you know
doing a dry run but you'll see that the
most recent one which is the one we had
which is called adding first GitHub
action so this actually comes from the
commit name and we could select this and
we can see exactly what happened so this
uh gives us a little summary we can see
that we have one job called job one and
then we can see that the job uh ran and
it successfully ran and it took 4
seconds and if you click on the job
you'll see all of the steps so the first
thing is it sets up the job and so you
can see that it's creating a runner
which is once again just a virtual
machine and then it's going to provide
us a buntu because we specified that as
our operating system
uh it's going to set up a virtual
environment don't worry too much about
that uh it's going to handle all of the
GitHub permissions because it's all
integrated with GitHub uh then we go
down to the first action which was
pulling the git repo because we did say
action checkout V2 so then it's going to
pull the GitHub repo and then we could
see the second option uh sorry the
second action which was say hi to sanj
so all it's doing is just running this
command on our Linux machine so it's
just saying Echo hello sanjie and then
it just prints out hello sanjie so this
is all a cicd pipeline is it's just
providing a bunch of instructions for a
little machine on the internet to run
for us now technically the machine
doesn't have to be on the internet it
doesn't have to be hosted uh there's
some uh cicd tools that you host
yourselves on your on your own machine
or your own server so that they actually
handle uh running all of this because uh
even though GitHub actions is free they
only give you a certain number of build
minutes for free and then after that
they'll start charging for it so uh
depending on how many times you build it
may actually be more cost effective eff
if to just set it up
yourself and then it looks like you know
GitHub actions there's a post pulling
git repo uh so it's going to perform a
few other like cleanup actions and then
it's going to then clean up the job so
we have successfully uh created our
first simple example cicd pipeline or
GitHub actions workflow in this case so
let's take our GitHub actions to the
next step and I'm going to actually
remove this uh example I just wanted to
show you guys how to do that but after
we pull our GitHub
the next thing that I want to do is I
want to set up
Python and so to set up python once
again we can go back to um the
marketplace if I can find it because you
know setting up python seems like a very
common task so um we can just search for
Python and keep in mind when it comes to
setting up python you could technically
uh just do the same thing where we can
say uses and then we can you know run
the command on a Linux machine to
install python which would be something
like pseudo app install python right we
could 100% do that and that would 100%
work but because this is such a common
task task there's already a pre-built
action so we don't even have to do
that and uh I think I searched for
python did that work it didn't look like
it
worked um here we go set up python down
here so this is going to be responsible
for setting up and installing python on
our machine and you'll see an example of
how to do this you just say uses action
setup Python atv2 and then you you say
with and then you specify the version
and then you can also provide the
architecture as well and what's really
cool about this is that let's say we
wanted to test our code on multiple
different versions of python well we can
go under the strategy section so right
under where it says runs on we can do
strategy and then we can provide a
matrix and then a list of versions so if
we wanted to test version 3.7 version
3.8 3.9 3.6 uh and make sure that our
code works on all of them we can then
create this Matrix here and then when we
go to set up our python right we would
say with and then for python version
instead of providing one specific
version we actually pass this is a
essentially a variable syntax in yl and
then we just call matrix. python version
which is referencing this list right
here and so it'll just run our actions
for all of these versions just to verify
that everything works in all of the
versions but we're going to keep it
simple we're just going to do version
3.9 if you want to play around with it I
definitely recommend you try testing
this out but for us it doesn't really
matter
um but keep in mind it looks like you
can even do the same thing for different
operating systems so if you want to test
on a buntu Mac and windows you can do
the same thing as well but like I said
we're going to keep things very
simple and I'm actually going to change
this to name give this a name I'm going
to say
install
python version
3.9 and we'll say uses and then we'll
call that action now so we'll do actions
slash set up-
python at
V2 and then we pass in wi Tab and we'll
say python Das
version and we'll say
3.9 and I think that's all we have to do
let me see the example uh python version
3.9 yep that's all uh we can leave the
architecture I'm going to use the
default uh which looks like it defaults
to x64 so not a problem in our case
all right and then after installing
python the next thing that I want to do
is I want to upgrade
pip so I'll create um a description of
update pip and then we'll say
uses actually instead of uses we're just
going to run a command on the the Linux
shell so we'll say
run and we just run python
DM pip install -- upgrade pip so this is
the command that you would run on any
Linux operating system or even on a
Windows machine to upgrade pip and then
the next thing that I want to do is
we're going to install all of our
dependencies so since we pulled our git
repo right with the actions checkout
we're going to have access to all of
this code and we're going to have access
to our requirements.txt so we have to
make sure that we install all of these
packages there as
well and so here I'll just say this is
install
all
dependencies and uh the command that
we're going to run for
this is going to be a and you guys
should know this this is just pip
install
dasr requirements.txt
all right so let's I think this is a
good starting point let's try um
committing our code again I'll just do
get add-- all we'll do a get commit DM
added more
steps and then we'll do a get push
origin
main all right and then we'll go back to
actions right and we can see that our
workflow is starting to run that's why
it's yellow and we can take a look at
its current status so it's still running
job one which is the name we gave it and
we can just kind of follow along so it
looks like it pulled our repo in whoops
installed python version 3.9 it's then
in updated pip and that's already
completed and now it's installing all
the dependencies so obviously installing
all the dependencies takes a certain
amount of time that's probably going to
be the longest specific step in our uh
GitHub workflow at this point all right
and it looks like that ran and then it's
essentially cleaning things up and then
it's completed and we get the beautiful
green check
mark so we can just close out of this go
back and you can even see the list of
all of our workflows that GitHub actions
uh detected so we have buil-in deploy
code so that's the only workflow that we
have but keep in mind I can create
essentially as many different yaml files
inside this workflow folders to have uh
different uh workflows so I might have
one specific set of uh I might have a
workflow specifically for one branch and
a completely separate workflow for
another Branch um it just gives you a
lot of customizability but we're just
going to have one workflow that works
across all of our branches now the next
thing that I want to do is I want to run
py
test so to run py test right it's a
pretty simple process so let me set up
the name
first and we'll say uh
whoops test with py
test and then we'll say
run all right and I need to run two
commands so if you ever want to provide
a list of commands to run uh instead of
having to create multiple different
steps I can do uh a pipe go down a line
and just provide the list of commands so
we'll do pip install py test and then we
can go down the line and provide the
second command so then we just run P
test and you can you know pass in
whatever Flags if you want the- V and
the- S but I'm going to keep it simple
and we're just going to keep it blank
for
now let's save this and I'm going to
then do the same thing we'll do a get
add-- all we'll do a get commit
DM and I'll say um added P test
step and then we'll do a get push origin
main
again and so from a from a learning
perspective right this is kind of a slow
process cuz we have to push all of our
changes and then now we have to wait for
this whole thing to run but once you
understand how all of this works and how
easy it is to set up you won't have to
keep doing this every single time or
every single project you can just
essentially copy and paste most of your
workflow all right so it looks like it's
completed and we get a red X so it looks
like something broke and that's to be
expected and it's going to highlight
what uh specific test failed or sorry
what specific step failed but we can see
that it was the uh running pie test so
if I just open this up a bit and then
expand it we can take a look at what the
error was so it looks like it installed
P test and that seems to have worked
fine and then down here you can see that
there's a couple of validation errors
and so it says that you know we didn't
provide a
database um host name Port so it looks
like there's issues with environment
variables and that makes sense because
this is a brand new computer that we
haven't touched so none of the
environment variables have been set up
so obviously it has no environment
variables in in our uh pantic validation
of environment variables should have
failed and it did absolutely fail so
this is all to be expected uh and so in
the next video we'll figure out how we
can set environment variables in our
workflows so that we can provide the
information for reaching our specific
database so there's a couple of
different ways that we can set up
environment variables um uh and there's
a couple of different places where we
can Define them so I'm going to show you
a job how to set a job specific
environment variable that means this is
an environment variable that will only
be accessible from within one job so in
this case our job that we've been
working on is called job one and so if
you want to set an environment variable
you just set it right here so we say EnV
and then you provide all of your
environment variables so in this case
let's say we want database host
name and in this case is going to
be Local Host we've now successfully
sent uh set up one environment variable
and I'm just going to copy and paste all
the
others and so now we've defined all of
our environment variables in this case
and that should fix the issue um but I
want to show you guys what other
environment variables that we have as
well and if you want to know where I'm
kind of getting all this information
like I said we have the documentation
and there should be a section for
environment variables here and so I
think we should see the same thing right
yep we see the same thing so EnV under
the specific job and you just provide uh
the list of all of your environment
variables and then there's some built-in
ones so these are default environment
variables that get set for you so here
you can see um uh what's the run number
what's the GitHub job uh what's the uh
action path we can even see what's a
repository so if you want to get the
name of your repository you can
reference this specific environment
variable but we don't need to do any of
that um but what I do want to show you
is uh you know if I had gone in and then
created a second job called job two
right this environment variable that we
defined here is not available because
this is defined under job one so if you
want to have a environment variable
that's shared across all of your jobs I
can specify an environment variable here
so I can say
EnV and then I just provide my
environment VAR so I can just copy this
one as an example and we can provide so
then database host name is going to be
available for job one and job
two but for now we're just going to
remove that cuz we don't really need we
don't really need that right now and I'm
going to keep everything as a default in
this
case and we're going to check this into
git so I'm going to do a git add-- all
we'll do a g commit DM added EnV
variables and we'll do a get push origin
Main
okay and then back to our actions page
if I see the added environment variable
section uh we can see that failed once
again this is going to be uh expected so
if we go under oh it looks like there's
a weird failure no steps defin okay so
we got an error because I accidentally
left job two so it doesn't like it the
fact that I have jobs 2 with no steps so
we're going to save this again and we're
going to do another
commit and I'll just call this commit
committing again cuz I'm getting
lazy right and let's just make sure that
we've kicked this off all right so it
looks like we kicked it off and there's
no um like major showstopping errors at
the beginning but we should still see
this fail and that's to be expected but
I just want to make sure that we no
longer have issues with environment
variables and I want to make sure that
the environment variables that we set
did successfully get applied to our
runner okay guys so uh couple things to
point out so there's a whole bunch of
errors and that's to be expected and
that's okay um but we can see that it
did process all of our environment
variables so that's great so we did fix
that issue but you'll notice that you
know when we're running our test we get
a whole bunch of errors and then
eventually you'll see a whole bunch of
SQL Alchemy errors and the reason we see
a whole bunch of SQL Alchemy errors is
because uh if you look at the
environment variables we're pointing to
Local Host for our database there's no
database on this Runner this is a brand
new computer that why would there be a
database installed so we do eventually
have to set up a database for testing on
the runner itself or we would have to
point it to a remote database whether
that's hosted on Heroku or AWS it
doesn't matter but you know for testing
purposes in your cicd pipeline I'd
rather create one on our runner that we
can just quickly spin up for
testing so once again I just wanted to
point out how to set up environment
variables the one thing I don't like and
I want to make sure I want to teach you
guys is that in this case we're
hardcoding these values in here and so
this is all stored in our reposit anyone
can have access to it this is our test
day base so it's not a big deal but I do
want to show you how we can um how we
can store these as secrets so that the
runner has access to them but no one
else can see them because storing in
here could potentially cause issues uh
you know if you didn't want this uh
these these um the the password and the
username for your test database to get
out in my case I don't really care but
um you know it is important for you guys
to understand how to actually do
that so as I mentioned in the last video
um our environment variables are
hardcoded into our workflow so
technically when we check this into git
anyone can see it which may or may not
be a problem but if it is a problem I'm
going to show you guys how we can work
with GitHub secrets so if we go to our
GitHub page and go to settings here
there's a section called secrets so we
can Define secrets that we can use an
access in our
workflows uh and so this is a repository
secret that means it's um globally
accessible across the entire repository
across all branches uh there's no you
know any kind of environments or
anything like that so we'll select new
repository secret and here we just give
it a name so if you take a look at our
environment variables I figured since
that's what it's going to represent we
might as well use the same one so I'll
say database host name in this case and
then just give it a value so Local Host
that's it right it's just a key value
pair we do add secret and then you'll
see it's stored in here and so now in
our code if if we want to reference the
uh this secret which I happen to call
database host name we just copy the name
of the
secret and then what we do is we use
dollar curly brace curly brace so two
sets of curly braces and we say Secrets
Dot and then the name of the secret so
this will allow the runner to access the
secret from our GitHub repo so that our
our workflow code doesn't actually
expose all of this information
and so this is what you want to do for
your passwords and things like that
especially when it comes to storing the
information for um connecting to your
production database which we will do in
one of the later
lessons um but before we proceed any
further I want to actually show you
another option so I'm actually going to
remove this repository Secret in this
case which is once again a global secret
that um our entire uh repo can access
instead what I like to do is I like to
set up environments so you can set up a
whole bunch of secrets that are
available depending on what the
environment is so I can create one for
testing one for development one for
production it gives us a lot of
flexibility so I'm going to create a new
environment and I'm going to call this
testing and within the environment we're
right we're under the testing
environment we can add a secret
here and so we're going to do the same
thing I'm going to call it database host
name and in this case we'll say
Local Host we'll add the
secret and we can provide as many
Secrets as we want and then what we can
do is in our job we can specify what the
environment is for the job so I can say
en oops
environment and then we provide the name
which is going to
be testing right this is going to match
up with whatever name we gave here so I
called it testing so we give this the
name t testing and it's going to have
access to all of the environment
variables that we defined here and the
way to access them is exactly the same
way you just do dollar two curly braces
secrets and then the name of the
environment variable now if there's an
overlap uh with the name of your
environment variables when it comes to
uh the ones that you set in your
environment as well as the one you set
globally for the repository I don't
actually know who takes precedence um I
suspect it's probably the environment
but you should check the documentation
to verify but we don't have any Global
secrets I'm going to be using
environments for everything so this
keeps things nice and simple and so now
that we've set up this one let's go
ahead and just set up all of these uh
while we have the
option and so we're going to set the
port as
well here we'll set the
password now we've got the database name
which will just say fast API
uh then the database username it autof
fil because uh you know I I ran through
this all in a quick trial run before I
started recording so it's kind of cached
in
there all right and so now that we have
all of our environment variables or our
environment Secrets Set uh we can just
change all of these to reference those
uh secrets we just do the same process
and in this case it's just going to be
the same exact name as the the key in
this
case all right and so now that we got
all of these Set uh let's just save this
and I'm going to check this into git now
uh just to make sure that you know
everything is kind of working so
far and we'll take a look at the job
real quick and hopefully there's uh no
errors or only errors that we expect to
see and what did I call this
one ASDF oh okay so it looks like it
failed already so we clearly did
something wrong this workflow is not
valid unrecognized name database Port
well what happened there and it even
tells me the position so if I select
show
more uh database password so let's see
what did we mess
up yeah simple mistake I forgot the
secrets dot before all of my variables
so that's why it had no idea what that
was we have to reference secrets to
actually get access to them
and now let's try this one more
time right this looks a little
better all right and so now if we look
at the test with P test you could see
that the environment variables were
passed in and GitHub will automatically
um kind of uh hide what all of the uh V
the secrets are because once again
they're secret so you shouldn't see them
but it does show that we were
successfully able to retrieve them and
we got the same error down here this is
just an issue with accessing the
database because there is no database on
on Local Host so it's trying to connect
to a database that doesn't exist which
is going to create all sorts of issues
so in the next video we'll figure out
what we can do to set up a test database
on our runner so that we can actually
run our tests so when it comes to
setting up a database on our runner the
easiest way to do that is to create a
service container so what's going to
happen is GitHub actions is actually
going to allow us to spin up a Docker
container which really is the easiest
way to set up Docker on uh sorry to set
up postgress on a remote machine that
way we don't have to worry about any
issues with potential installation of a
postgress database and so I recommend
you take a look at this um tutorial
which kind of walks you through how to
set up a postgress service container uh
and it just gives you an example in this
case which we are essentially just going
to copy in this case but here we just
under jobs we specify a service uh we
give this service a specific name or
label and then we just tell the image
that we want to use uh and in this case
we're just using the default postgress
image this is the one that comes from
Docker Hub by the way but you could
technically use any image that you
wanted to but it's post so we might as
well just use the default one and then
we can pass environment variables into
the docker container as well so one of
the things that we want to do is set up
the uh password for postgress as well us
even potentially the database
name and then what we want to do is we
want to set up some health checks to
wait until post Chris is started because
until postgress starts we should not run
any tests because the tests are going to
fail because the database is down so we
want to make sure that postgress is up
and ready before we actually start
running our test so we're essentially
just going to uh copy this line here but
let's go back to our code and we'll take
a look at how to do this step by step
and so I'll just go under the
environment variable section here and
we'll create a section called
services and I'm going to create a
service called
postgress and we're going to provide the
image just like we saw in that example
and that's going to be uh
postgress and let's uh pass some
environment variables so the first thing
is going to be the postgress password so
we're going to do
postgress
password and here for the password we
can literally reference the same exact
secret because we're going to be using
the same password
and then we also want to give it a uh
custom database name so we want to
automatically create the uh fast API
uncore test database so that we don't
have to do it in code so I'll do
postgress
DB and we'll do dollar dollar and then
here I can pass in uh where's my
database
name so this is just going to be fast
API at this point but we want fast API
uncore test because that's what our code
has been set up to run so we'll do
underscore test right so this is kind of
like string interpolation so same thing
uh and then at that point I think our
Docker container is pretty much set up
we do have to specify the ports that we
want to open up uh so we'll say
ports and you know we want to do
5432 uh and then 54 32 so this is what
we want and you're probably thinking
well
can we use the uh uh the variables here
and I tried to do this I tried to paste
this here and then paste this here and I
actually got errors I don't know why it
didn't work but for some reason this
wasn't allowed so you have to hardcode
these values
unfortunately and then lastly let's set
up the options so I'm going to just copy
these options right here CU we want
those health checks for sure
let's save this uh and make sure that
all the spacing lines up because a lot
of times the spacings can mess up things
I have a auto formatter so with a for yo
syntax uh it'll automatically format it
so that all the spacing is set up
properly uh you want to make sure that
you do it manually or set up or install
a extension in VSS code if that's an
option for
you okay so we've got our post database
and I think we should be good to go so
let's try this get add all get
commit all right and so we can see that
our most recent test in this case
happened to succeed and uh if you
actually go to the test test with P test
and just see the results we could see
that 46 tests pass with no
issues uh and so that means it did
successfully connect to our database and
after that it essentially completed the
job so now we've successfully added a
database and we've successfully set up
our CI pipeline this is the CI portion
of things to pull our code I install
python set up uh you know install all
the dependencies and run our test so all
of this happens in an automated fashion
now just by doing a git push so you
could see how easy it is to get things
started and so um I think from the CI
perspective the last thing I want to
show you guys is how to uh essentially
create a Docker image uh in our runner
and push that out to um to uh Docker Hub
so that our production Network can then
pull that brand new image so there's a
couple things that we have to do to get
Docker working in our GitHub workflow um
the first thing is we need to have a
repository set up on Docker Hub to store
our images and if you did not create one
during the docker section go ahead and
create a new one so log into Docker Hub
select create repository and just give
this a name that you can remember in
this case this is going to be fast API
I'm going to call it that and then make
it public just to keep it simple and so
this is our repo and then it's going to
tell us how to actually push an image to
it uh and then if you go to uh this page
right here so docs. do.com UHC cd/
GitHub actions it's got an excellent
tutorial that we can follow for setting
up Docker with our GitHub
actions and so if we go back to our
Docker Hub the first thing that we want
to do is we want to get an access token
so let's go here and I think we go under
settings or well it doesn't look like
it's here maybe account
settings yep and then security and then
we can select new access token
and I'll maybe we can call this uh
GitHub
actions and we're going to give it um
you know whatever permission that you
want uh does the docker give us
information on what permissions uh it
doesn't look like it
um in this case so just go ahead and
select all of them for
now all right and so it's going to give
you your access token uh make sure that
uh you don't share this with anyone else
and it's only going to be displayed once
so go ahead and copy it and make sure
that you have this
then what it's telling us to do is we
want to create a
um a secret for both our username as
well as the dockerhub access token so
let's create these two secrets in GitHub
for dockerhub Access token and dockerhub
username and I actually forgot what my
username was okay so it's sloppy
networks and so here we'll go into
settings
and uh feel free to use uh either um the
global repository Secrets or uh
environment secrets I'm going to just
put this in the testing environment for
now but you can use either one in this
case and so we got Docker uncore hubor
username so this is going to be sloppy
networks for me but it's going to be
something else for you
guys and the last one is going to be
dockerhub uh what is it dockerhub access
token all right and so once we've got
that set up uh you'll see that they're
going to give us the steps on how to
actually set this up in our yaml file
you can ignore the original the the
setup process and what we want to do is
we want to go down to the this section
right here which shows us how to log
into dockerhub so we can literally just
copy this straight
up and just paste it in here so we can
just say uh we'll do it at
the uh what step should we do this at um
we'll do it at the end just because why
not um because some of you guys might
not be interested in setting up Docker
uh so it's going to be an optional Step
at the end so we'll log into Docker hub
using this built-in action uh from the
marketplace and then here it's just
going to provide two properties username
and password which is going to reference
the two secrets that we
created all right and then we want to
set up a Docker build
X so we'll copy this one as
well right and then we have the build
and
push uh step right here which it in this
case it's a Once Again a built-in action
uh and all it's going to do is we're
going to provide a path to the context
so this is essentially where is the
docker file located uh and we I this is
technically optional but if you want to
you can hardcode the specific Docker
file um I think it should default to
this one because that's the default
Docker file but we'll just put it in
just in case and then the push is means
not only are we going to build the
docker image we're also going to push it
up to uh Docker Hub and then we have to
give it a specific tag and if we go back
to Docker Hub and I go to my
repositories and I go to my fast API
it's going to show me the format of the
tag that I need so that I can actually
push it up properly so it's going to be
the username slash and then the name of
the repository which is fast API and
then we can also give it an optional tag
name as
well so once again we're going to copy
this and just update a few
Fields uh everything else should be just
fine uh the only thing that we have to
change CH is this is going to be fast
API and it's going to reference the
username so it's going to be in the
exact format and if you want to give it
a very specific tag you can give that as
well but I'm going to just give it the
default latest and then here it's just
printing out the image digest which is
for us is optional uh you'll see that it
does provide us some uh optional things
that we can do for optimization so we
can use uh um the build cache so that we
don't have to redownload all of our
images every time we run because that's
going to extend the build time and the
the run time for our runner which is
eventually going to cost us a certain
amount of um money so this is the code
that you can use and if you look at the
bottom right here this is going to show
us all of the uh code at the very end so
we can literally just copy all of this
if we wanted to and just use that
instead of what we put so that's what we
will do so let
me just delete all of
this and then paste it
in and we have have everything and once
again we just want to change the name to
be the our repository name which is
right here we could also use a secret
for that but don't worry too much about
that and that should be all that we have
to do um for uh the docker integration
um if you don't have a Docker file then
i' recommend you well I'll just pause
this video create a file in your root in
the root of your project directory
called Docker file with a capital D and
just copy all of this or you can follow
what I go through in the docker section
if you guys skip
that and I think that should be
everything that we need so let's go
ahead and push this and pray that it
does not break anything and it works
just the way we expected to so we'll do
get add-- all get
commit added
Docker and then we'll do a get push
origin
yep and it failed so fully expected this
a step cannot have both uses and run key
so what did we break here actually it
should
uh where is it telling us
this yeah this spacing got messed up so
that was a very obvious mistake that I
should have
caught and I just have to move this
back right there and that should fix
everything so let's do this
again all right so so far it's not AED
out so it looks like things look
okay and we can see the build uh and
push section failed so let's see if
there's an error
and it looks like the there's some issue
with the driver um please switch to a
different driver Docker build X create--
use so let's see what that is in this
case and I realized the documentation
was a little confusing this section that
we copied at the end uh it didn't
include one of these steps which is the
build X step so before we or actually
after we log in we want to set up a
buildex which is the mistake that we ran
into so we want to copy this page right
here this section and then we'll run
that right after the
login and so now if we do a get ad
all get commit
DM and then I get push origin
main okay so I think this time
everything should should work um but
just to reiterate uh cuz I think I went
a little bit quickly um the steps are we
first log into Docker using the login
action right here then the next thing is
we used uh we set up uh build x uh and
then we call the build and push action
in this case and here we specify the
context which is saying just this
current directory and then the location
of our Docker file and then we're going
to use buildex for the Builder and we
set push to be true because we want to
actually push it to the um to the GitHub
repo and then here the repo is going to
be our user username slash then the
repository name which is it happens to
be fast API we could store this in a
secret but I decided not to uh and then
these are just copied from the uh the
documentation so that we can cach all of
the images so that we don't have to keep
running all of this from scratch which
is a fairly long process and then here
we're just spitting out the image digest
and if we take a look at our uh
workflows and we can see that the last
one which is called ASDF uh successfully
ran and if I actually go back to my
Docker Hub in this case and just hit
refresh right we can see that we did
successfully push an image a minute ago
so that means we have now successfully
completed our uh entire CI portion of
our CI uh cicd pipeline the next step is
to set up the continuous delivery which
is a matter of just providing a whole
bunch of commands needed
to um actually push out our new code to
our production Network and you know
moving forward um just to kind of keep
things simple and as quick as possible
I'm actually going to copy out all of
the docker steps because we're not even
using Docker and production so we don't
actually need this so we'll just comment
that out just to make things as quick
and snappy as possible so that we don't
use too many of our build
minutes so now that we set up the
continuous integration part of our cicd
pipeline it's now time to move on to the
continuous delivery aspect of our cicd
pipeline so this part is going to be
responsible for pushing out the update
to our production environment so that
our code or our production environment
is running our newest and latest
code so there's a couple things we can
do uh and I'm actually going
to uh do this up here actually we'll
just do it down here it's fine so what
we could do is you know just to keep
things simple um I could just provide
another step right and we can give this
you know whatever name we want I could
say name and then hey this is uh push
changes to
production and then we can you know
provide the steps needed to actually
push those changes out um however
instead of doing it like this what I
would like to do is I actually want to
break it out into a separate job so that
we can kind of have things nice and
organized and uh what I actually want to
do is I want to rename job one because
it's not very uh descriptive I'm going
to rename it to
build and then I'm going to create a
second job and we'll call this one
deploy
so we've got two different jobs however
the uh the issue with jobs is that they
don't behave the way that you think they
would and let me delete this uh the way
that jobs work is that by default in
GitHub the jobs run in
parallel and so what I mean by that is
that when our workflow runs uh GitHub is
actually going to run the build job and
the deploy job in parallel at the same
exact time now we would definitely not
want to do that because that would mean
before we've even you know run our tests
and done anything else we would try to
actually deploy our new changes which
would be a terrible thing to happen so
we don't want it to run in parallel how
exactly do we configure that well we
pass in an option called runs uh sorry
needs so you say needs and here we we
tell it the list of uh jobs that need to
complete before this job can run so here
we just say this needs to wait for uh
the build job to run before this job
runs and so we just pass that into here
and you could pass in multiple uh
multiple jobs if you wanted to we only
have one other one so this is going to
cause this to run in a sequential
order and just like with uh the other
job we need the
runson property to Define you know that
we want to run this on a bun to latest
and then I'm just going to create a test
step in this case we'll do steps and and
the first step is going to say uh
uses actually I'm just going to say
name uh you know deploying stuff and
here I'm just going to run a command on
our
server and I'll just say
Echo uh going to deploy some
stuff all right so let's test this
out do a get add-
Dall get commit DM
and if we go ahead and check
GitHub and go to our actions let's take
a look at what happened in the adding
deploy and so you could see now that we
have two different jobs uh we can
actually see the two different jobs here
and so it looked like build ran just
fine and then it looked like deploy also
ran just fine and so if I take a look at
the deploying stuff we can see that I
ran the command going to deploy some
stuff and it was successfully deployed
although we didn't actually deploy
anything but you get the gist of it so
now it's just a matter of figuring out
what commands we need to run to actually
push those changes out to our production
server and so you know we covered two
different deployment models in this
course there's Heroku and then there's
the auntu server so we're going to start
off by going over how we can actually
handle this with Heroku uh and if we go
to our code right here we're going to
provide the steps to actually um push an
update to Heroku now if you don't
remember what we actually did to push
changes out to Heroku uh do a get remote
I think yep so this is going to list out
the um the Heroku remote so if you want
to actually push out the changes to your
Heroku application you would do a get
push Heroku and then your branch which
is Main and that's going to update our
application it's pretty simple with
Heroku uh so in this machine right in
our cicd pipeline it's not quite as
simple as running get push uh Heroku
main just because
we don't have Heroku installed on this
machine because when we set up Heroku we
had to install the Heroku CLI we had to
run Heroku login put in our credentials
and then we had to um pull we have to
get our git repo we have to add the
Heroku remote and then we have to do a
get push so there's a couple of
different steps uh and so manually doing
it I just want to kind of write this out
we would you know install Heroku
CLI we would actually before we even do
that we would
uh first of all you know pull our GitHub
repo um because remember this job is
essentially starting everything from
scratch uh potentially on a different
machine so anything we did here none of
this stuff is available so we don't
actually have access to the the repo
that we pulled here so we would have to
do it again here so we pull the repo we
install Heroku C then we do a Heroku
login and then we do
a um we have to add in a remote in git
and I forget the command so but we'll
just say add git remote for Heroku and
then we have to do a
get push Heroku main so those are the
steps that we would have to run to
actually deploy our application uh in
our cicd Pipeline and this is all
technically possible you can manually do
this but it's actually a kind of a pain
in the uh the butt to actually do this
and instead
what I recommend you do is look for a um
a a action in the GitHub Marketplace
that kind of does this all under the
hood so that's what we're going to do
because uh you know deploying to Heroku
is a very common task so if I go to the
marketplace which I forget which tab was
the
marketplace oh I think it's this one
yeah and so here if I search for
Heroku uh you'll see that we have a
couple of different options
for deploying to Heroku in the
marketplace let me just see view all
because I got to figure out which one is
the one that I want and this is the one
that I want by ailesh NS so this is the
one that's got the most stars so we'll
select this one uh and you'll see that
in the example the way that we actually
deploy to Heroku is we have to get a
Heroku API key we have to provide our
Heroku app name and then we have to
provide our Heroku
email so let's get this from our account
and then we will create
Secrets within our GitHub repository so
we can store the information because we
don't want to hard code that uh into our
um yaml file so going back to Heroku uh
if you go to your account which is your
the little logo here then select account
settings uh you'll see that the API key
is right here so we can just s
reveal and then I'm just going to copy
this key and what we're going to do is
we're going to go to our uh GitHub
repository we'll go to
settings and then we can create our
secrets so you can create a global
repository secret or you can do what I'm
going to do which is I'm going to create
a brand new environment uh for
production we'll call this
production that is not how you spell
production and we're going to add a
secret and um I'm going to well paste
the value here but the name I'm going to
just stick to what they used uh just to
make it easier to
remember so Heroku API key add
secret uh and then what else do we need
uh we have to add the email so let's
create uh a secret for the email as well
cuz why not they didn't do that but
we're going to be a little bit more
secure and I'll call this a
Heroku
email and this is just going to be your
email that you use to
register and then if you want to you can
also add the Heroku app name uh as a
secret as well you don't have to do this
but I'm going to do it and what did I
call my app I can't even
remember uh fast API s yours is going to
be different so make sure you update it
accordingly okay
so wait what happened here why is there
only
two I think I may have accidentally
overridden one of these
keys so let me let me put this
information back in just in case because
you can't actually look at the keys
after you save them you can only update
them okay so we
updated that and
then the API key I have to copy this
once
more all right so we got those and then
let me once again add the Heroku app
name this is going to
be all right so now we've got our three
keys hopefully I set those all up
correctly uh and keep in mind the name
of
this environment is called production so
for the other job which is the the
deploy job we're going to specify the
Environ
the same way we did with the first job
um just by referencing this code right
here and just updating the
name and so this is going to be
production and then we can remove this
unnecessary X step and I actually I'll
change this to be deploying to
Heroku and then we'll change this to be
Ed
and so just like in the documentation
actually I might as well just copy it
because it's a little bit easier so I
can just
copy
this and we can just update the app name
with the secret that we defined
as well as the secret for the
email and that's all we have to do for
the Heroku side of things we don't it's
as simple as that so that's why I always
recommend you look for a built-in action
uh so that you don't have to perform all
of these steps by
yourself and I realized before we even
do that we have to actually pull our
code just like we did in the first job
so we're going to copy uh that section
right here where we pull the
repo all right so we've got the repo and
then we deploy to
Heroku and so what I'm going to do now
is we want to check our code real quick
um and make some changes uh that that'll
be easy to kind of quickly just test and
see that we actually pushed out a
changes so under our main.py file you
know I'm just going to do what I always
do uh I'm just going to add um
successfully
deployed from CI CD pipeline okay and so
going to save that and then now we want
to do a get add --all
uh get commit
DM push to Heroku
example and then we'll do a get push
origin
Main and before I do that uh let me go
to my
app so if I actually go to my app on
Heroku we can see it just says message
hello world and so after we commit these
changes we should see it send the new
meage message so I'm going to send uh
I'm going to push this to GitHub now and
our cicd pipeline should run and push
those changes
out all right so now if I go back to
GitHub and we take a look at the actions
I can see my push to Heroku example
succeeded and so you can see both the
build phase and the deploy phase both
succeeded and if we want to take a look
at the notes um and just see what
happened with the deploying to Heroku
section we'll see the logs for this
specific step and so it looks like yeah
we can see Heroku is running in this
case and it looks like everything worked
so if I go back to my app and hit
refresh right we can see we get the new
message so we have successfully updated
Heroku using our cicd pipeline it's as
simple as that um and before I wrap up
this video uh this section or this video
on uh deploying to Heroku um I found
this one good article that shows you how
to deploy to Heroku in a manual way so
if you don't want to use the built-in um
or the preconfigured GitHub action you
can actually create a custom workflow
when it comes to uh you know actually
manually logging in um and then pushing
all of these changes out to Heroku um
the manual way instead of using that
pre-built action um but this is a little
bit more complex and this would uh only
really be needed under very specific
circumstances or just for a learning uh
or just for learning purposes so take a
look at it if you want to see how it's
done manually but you never actually
have to do that now before we move any
further there's one thing that I want to
check to make sure that our cicd uh
pipeline properly does and that is that
if we get any kind of errors in the
build job I want to make sure that the
deploy job does not run right and so
when I say errors it could be anything
right maybe we're uh unable to install
all of our dependencies or maybe and
more importantly if our tests fail right
if my tests fail I don't want to push my
broken code out to production so I want
to make sure that if the test fails we
stop right there and we don't proceed
any further with the deploy and so from
a configuration perspective you don't
technically have to do anything that's
the default configuration but I do want
to verify that it actually does what we
expected to so in the tests files if I
can find it uh tests I'm going to go to
you know it doesn't really matter what
test I'm just going to go under test
posts and I'm just going to um modify
this to an incorrect
value I'm going to put this in the notes
change to this one so I I remember which
one I changed so I can change it back
from 200 so this should cause this test
to fail and if the test fails then we
want to make sure that we don't deploy
and I'm also going to go back to our
main.py file to actually make some
Visible
Changes um by changing this back to
hello world to see if our code actually
got updated accidentally or not so we
got everything
set we'll do a get ad once
again we'll do a get
commit
DM broke stuff and then we'll do a get
or get push origin
Main and we'll let that
run all right so going back to GitHub
now um let me go back to the the actions
page and we can see the last run it
looks like it failed so let's see where
it failed and so you could see here um
it failed in the build build stage and
then the deploy stage if I select this
uh this check was skipped so that means
we actually did properly skip the deploy
phase because the build phase failed and
we can see that um we exited with an
error code because one of our tests
failed awesome so let's go back let's
fix this code real
quick and what is it test
posts and we'll change that back to a
200 don't need those notes
anymore and now let's push out those
changes once
more all right and uh we'll go back to
GitHub
again and let's go back to actions and
let's take a look and we can see the
last one did get deployed built and
deployed successfully so if I go to
Heroku refresh this we should see that
this gets updated just fine all right so
now that we can uh deploy our updates to
Heroku let's take a look at how we can
deploy our updates to our auntu server
so once again it's just a matter of
figuring out um what exactly are the
commands that we would need to run to
update our production environment so
there's going to be a couple things uh
the first thing is first of all we would
have to log into our uh a buntu
server and then once we log and when I
say a log into our buntu server I mean
like SSH to it we would then have
to move into our slapp SL Source
directory and then we would run a get
pull so that we can pull the latest code
and then we'd have to do a
um a uh a system CTL restart
API so how exactly do we do all of this
how do we log into our buntu server how
do we SSH to it well there's a there's a
really nice um built-in action I can
find the marketplace
again and I believe it's called um s-
action and uh I don't think that's I
can't find it in here the one I used um
but it's by Apple
boy and I'll just do Apple boy SSH so
search for that that's there we go this
is the one we want SSH remote command so
this will allow you to run commands on a
remote machine so let's take a look at
how to do this um here they give you an
example so you have to pass in the host
which is the IP address the username and
the password and then the SSH Port is
optional but I think it should default
to um uh to Port 22 which is the one
that's running on our abun server so we
don't actually have to Define that um
but that's all we really need and then
the script is going to be the uh
commands that we want to run on the
remote machine so so let's set this
up uh and I'll go down to
here and I'll say
name deploy to auntu
server and we're going to say
uses Apple boy SL s-
action
atmas and then
with so first we have to provide a host
and I'm going to store this in a secret
and we'll call this uh
um what do you think we should call this
about
auntu uncore
host actually we'll call this prod
host and then username same thing we're
going to store this in a uh secret so
we'll do secrets. prod
username and then
password once again in another Secret
and I'll call this
prod
password all right then we have to
provide the commands that we want to run
and so since we're going to use more
than one command we're going to do the
little pipe symbol and then here we just
list out the command so the first thing
that we want to do is we need to move
into our app directory so we just going
to be app SL
source and make sure there is no front
slash that's going to break
things uh then we we want to do a git
pull now this is where it might get a
little interesting um I'm going to do it
the wrong way first so we do a system
CTL restart API but we do need pseudo
privilege so we'll do
pseudo restart API or whatever you call
it yours uh and so let's define these
secrets real quick and we'll go into the
environments and then we'll go to our
production environment and so just go
ahead and just create them here
all right and then we're going to put in
our password I'm not going to show this
one to you guys so I'll just going to
pause the video and then add it
myself and then finally we need
the uh the username
and I believe I called mine just sanie I
think that should work
hopefully and so now we've got all of
our secrets and um I think we should be
good to go prod host username password
so let's try
this actually before we do that going to
make one more change to the code that we
can actually see the changes and so this
is uh pushing out to a
buntu and and we're going to have to do
a get ad once again then a get
commit and then get push origin
main all right and let's go back now
let's check on our actions it looks like
it's still running so it's in the deploy
phase and it looks like it's uh
connecting oh and it looks like it just
finished and it failed so what exactly
happened here uh if we take a look at
the logs it says pseudo a terminal is
required to read the password so uh it's
basically saying that when you run the
pseudo command you know you get the
prompt so that you can input the Pudo
password and since this is all through a
remote SSH connection that's not really
an option so we have to pass in the dash
s option the- s
flag and so the way we actually Define
this is going to be actually pretty
interesting
um but let's see where where's my file
so to use the- S flag what we're going
to do is we're going to say
Echo and then we're going to Echo the
password our pseudo password and then we
pipe into the next command and we do
pseudo- s so the- s means that we're
going to accept what um the password as
an argument essentially and the this
pipe command what it's doing is we um we
run Echo and then whatever our password
is uh so this we actually replace with
the actual password and it's going to
pass that into the input of this command
so it's going to pass it into the- s
flag essentially so that's how you do
this with the oneline command um here
we're just going to um pass our same
environment variable so we'll do
Secrets do uh prod
password and I think that should fix it
actually so we'll do a get add--
all get commit
DM password fix and a get
push okay so let's go back to our
actions uh we can see that the password
fix commit ran just fine and it
succeeded so the build phase and the
deploy phase succeeded so if I go to my
uh buntu server and I and we take a look
at this we can see that uh we did get
the updated code so we did successfully
update our production server and on top
of that um technically since we never
took out the code for Heroku we should
see Heroku also deploy so um if I go to
my Heroku app we can see that pushed out
to a bunch so we now have successfully
completed our cicd pipeline we set up
all of the uh continuous integration
steps which included um copying our
source code uh installing all of the uh
python dependencies testing our
application and then we set up the CD
phase which was just a matter of pushing
those changes out to our production
environment